<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><title>CYBORG_ Newsletters</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/feed/</link><description>My latest articles</description><atom:link href="http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/feed/" rel="self"/><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2025 Not Defined LLC</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 13:15:57 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>It Hasn't Always Been This Way</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/it-hasnt-always-been-this-way/</link><description>After a brisk walk around the neighborhood venting about LGBTQ+ exclusion and oppression, our friend stood with my wife and me on our porch to finish a thought. Just as snow was starting to fall, he said, “That’s why I read history: it helps me see that things haven’t always been this way.”
My thoug</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 13:15:57 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/it-hasnt-always-been-this-way/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;After a brisk walk around the neighborhood venting about LGBTQ+ exclusion and oppression, our friend stood with my wife and me on our porch to finish a thought. Just as snow was starting to fall, he said, “That’s why I read history: it helps me see that things haven’t always been this way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My thoughts stopped in their tracks. I had never heard that particular observation about history before. I’ve always heard things like “history repeats itself,” or that there are generational cycles and patterns that you recognize from history. To think that history might actually reveal how things weren’t always this way is a crack in my understanding of everything—and while in reality, it’s probably 99% bad things on the side of &amp;quot;how it used to be&amp;quot; (like how chattel slavery isn’t currently legal in the U.S. but it certainly was in the past)—even just a sliver of hope is strangely powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, history provides us with examples of cultures that are not only comfortable with, but often &lt;a href="https://www.britannica.com/list/6-cultures-that-recognize-more-than-two-genders"&gt;​celebrate or honor gender identities​&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.yesmagazine.org/social-justice/2021/06/07/trans-history-gender-diversity"&gt;​gender expressions​&lt;/a&gt; that fall outside of the cisgender binary. Current U.S. politics have decided to demonize gender-nonconforming people (transgender, nonbinary, gender fluid, two-spirit, and other identities), but history tells me that this doesn’t &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to be this way. It’s not a requirement for cultures to be transphobic, it’s not even necessarily common to be transphobic (it seems &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uId0TIJPjhw"&gt;​queer phobia is largely the fallout of colonialism​&lt;/a&gt;). It wasn’t always this way. Therefore it doesn’t have to continue to be this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realize I’ve already brought up some thoughts that may seem spicy. We’ll keep transphobia on simmer awaiting another week’s topic, though I hope this intro has already gotten your wheels turning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, let’s keep exploring the idea that things haven’t always been this way, and they don’t have to continue to be this way. We have some really big systems affecting our lives, especially in our technology. Sometimes it seems like patterns in technology are inevitable and unchangeable, but I have a thought exercise to try, so let’s see if we can show that things don’t have to be the way that they currently are—and try to find the smallest possible change that would have a large impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Videos and the Attention Economy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examining systems is very difficult to do, because they often occupy an invisible, environmental space (see &lt;a href="/newsletters/the-artist-as-enemy-part-one/"&gt;​Marshall McLuhan’s exploration of environment and anti-environment​&lt;/a&gt;). An easier starting place might be in examining the incentives inside the system—what motivates people within the system, or how does the system reward behavior? YouTube, for example, is considered to be the second-largest search engine in the world (next to its parent company’s Google search). It has long been lauded as an education platform, because there is a vast ecosystem of creators, museums, colleges and universities, academics, and professionals in any and all fields who post phenomenally instructive or educational videos. The problem is that you have to work to get that kind of content to reveal itself from the mess of MrBeast-style videos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m heavily biased towards YouTube because I have watched it almost daily for years and have created videos on the platform. Given this bias, I’m especially interested in poking at the “system” to understand where it might be harming humans in its role in the attention economy, which devalues and harvests our attention. Let’s ignore YouTube Shorts because I find that to be the easiest and most uninteresting critique of YouTube, since short-form content does not lend itself well to education or long-term retention of information. Instead, let’s look at a metric that is near and dear to the heart of content creators: View Duration. This metric tells a lot about a video’s effectiveness at keeping attention and &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; indicate the usefulness or the value of the video over time. I think this is where we can start to unpack how YouTube’s system is more harmful than helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/pCk4wuYrjrBVo1a98XNQau/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Retention graph of a 14 minute video, with a steep drop of viewers toward the beginning. Shows that less than 10% of the viewers watched to the end of the video.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/gFq5RKzXDo464NhXuTQLZi/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Retention graph of a minute-long video. The graph swells, suggesting that half of the audience skipped the "intro" to get to the solution and then quickly stopped watching.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The retention graph can become a game to many creators who use it to inform how much they should cut out of their videos in the future, because shorter videos tend to retain more viewers’ attention. It’s much easier to create many short videos with very thin content, than to create a video of rich information that isn’t “digestible” in a single sitting. If, let’s say, the mission of YouTube was to lean into the side of educational content (rather than competing with short-form interruptive content like TikTok and Instagram), what changes could be made to encourage a kind of learning behavior in viewers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think one change in the way advertisements are shown could immediately help this. Normally, you get ads no matter what—the only exception is if a creator has both been granted the ability to monetize their content AND has chosen to turn off advertisements. What if rewatching a video turned off ads? In my experience, long-term content is still only effective if I can watch it again to reabsorb everything and start to unpack the topic. If YouTube incentivized viewers to re-watch videos, instead of always pushing to watch something new, it would drastically change both viewer and creator behavior. Viewers could return to videos more easily to take notes or remind themselves of what they learned. Creators could focus more on depth rather than on structuring for attention hacks like “5 ways to do XYZ and the last one will surprise you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;YouTube can already segment videos based on the kind of content so that not every video behaves this way (music videos, for instance, might be a content type that still gets ads on every play), but the videos that do encourage better attention habits and/or learning in viewers could be grouped into this feature. They could even go so far as to encourage creators to participate by offering higher ad payouts when audiences re-watch videos. Allowing creators to self-identify as an education channel (or at least video-by-video) would be enough to not put any &amp;quot;strain&amp;quot; on YouTube for validation and the risk to the creator to break the mold would justify the higher payouts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s one change, for one type of content that could drastically impact a huge amount of people (millions if not billions). And it probably wouldn’t affect the platform’s bottom line too much if at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cyborg&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;History can help us recognize bad patterns and it can also illuminate the flawed logic of assuming everything is this way because it has to be. This applies to the social technology of interacting with other people as well as with more discrete digital technologies. When I start noticing these huge systems that are completely out of my reach as an individual, I often feel hopeless and powerless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, history is full of unnamed people taking small actions that end up creating completely different realities. We are the people between the lines, just like all of the people who have been in between the lines of histories gone by. Even the named historical figures didn’t necessarily know that they would be memorialized as prominent people. This shows me that it doesn’t matter whether I get the credit, what matters is that I added my contribution to the tension that becomes larger-scale change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We probably can’t change YouTube, but we can take a look at the product we make at work (“product” is a very loose term here). We probably can’t reverse the harm done to our transgender populations, but we can make an effort to use their preferred names and pronouns. We probably can’t change everything that’s harmful about our world, our politics, and our systems, but we can change something—we can always change something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are social creatures and we have outsized impact on our social “networks”—the people we know and interact with personally. Let’s see what we can change with our very small, intentional actions.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Most Dangerous AI Movie</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-most-dangerous-ai-movie/</link><description>It’s no secret that I have some considerable concerns with Artificial Intelligence (AI), most of which are more closely tied to the creators of AI than with AI in itself. I was still surprised to find a movie that would shock me so thoroughly to the point where I asked myself: is this movie propagan</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 13:07:58 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-most-dangerous-ai-movie/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that I have some considerable concerns with Artificial Intelligence (AI), most of which are more closely tied to the &lt;em&gt;creators&lt;/em&gt; of AI than with AI in itself. I was still surprised to find a movie that would shock me so thoroughly to the point where I asked myself: is this movie propaganda? Or is it just poorly crafted story?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plot of this particular film was dull and predictable, though supposedly the action was great &lt;a href="https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/atlas_2024/reviews"&gt;according to some reviews&lt;/a&gt; (I found the action entirely forgettable and still dull). But the &lt;em&gt;message&lt;/em&gt; was astoundingly terrifying to me, and I think it’s extremely important to address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re talking about &lt;cite&gt;Atlas&lt;/cite&gt;, starring Jennifer Lopez, which came out in 2024. In my opinion, it’s not really worth your time to watch so even though there will be a few spoilers, I think it’s safe to proceed anyway ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Setting the Scene&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atlas, our hero played by Jennifer Lopez, is the daughter of an AI scientist/creator. Atlas’s mother designed a human-looking AI robot named Harlan. At the beginning of the movie, all we know is that Atlas is very distrustful of AI in general, and has valid concerns for privacy since the robots in this universe generally need access to your mind (including memories and other vulnerable information) in order to be best controlled by the humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite being a data analyst, the fact that she has known Harlan, the AI terrorist, since she was a child compels Atlas to join a military operation trying to take Harlan down before he threatens humanity on earth. Things go wrong and Atlas survives only by jumping into a mech-suit. On a hostile planet, she has to maneuver to Harlan’s HQ within this robotic vehicle. The only problem is that the mech just doesn’t work very well. Why? This is the ultimate problem with this story and gets us right into the danger zone with real-life consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/sCmqjxaGJrTzLhAtvSXCNh/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Mech-suit in flight, shooting at something with guns mounted on its arms.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For whatever reason, it is the invasion of privacy that makes the mech operable. Sure, super basic tasks like walking are fine. Want to survive being attacked by hostile robots? All of a sudden you have to choose to give away your entire life: your memories, your fears, your thoughts, just so a military robot suit can militarize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the only part of the movie that has any basis in reality, because we already experience this coercive dilemma with our software. You must choose to give away personal information—information that can harm you over time through exploitation, information that can be sold without your permission, information that could put you at risk whether through fraud or theft or any number of creative ways if a bad actor gets ahold of it. It’s not ever framed this way, obviously, because then you’d be more likely to at least read through the privacy policies or user agreements before buying some tool or service. Even worse, we can be easily manipulated by our natural desire for connection as well as peer pressure—why quit Facebook when I’ll lose contact with tons of people, even though Facebook doesn’t really show my friends’ posts anymore and uses all of my data for &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/privacy/genai"&gt;training its own AI&lt;/a&gt; designed to further prevent me from finding my friends’ posts because I’m too distracted watching AI generated videos or rage bait?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Privacy Schmivacy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe sometimes privacy doesn’t matter that much. Who cares if something like YouTube or a streaming platform uses your watching behavior to pick content you’ll like from the impossibly deep and growing libraries of options? Aside from the fact that these platforms don’t necessarily rely &lt;em&gt;solely&lt;/em&gt; on behavior tracked on their own platform since they can buy data or else gather it from other sources, privacy violations have more at stake than serving you better ads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At what point does it end? At what point does a tool, designed to save your life, need access to your thoughts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to Atlas in her mech, she ends up in a fight with enemy robots intent on eradicating her and her AI-powered suit. It’s only until this life-threatening situation arises that she gives into the AI and gives it access to her mind so that it can actually work as it should and blow up all the robots. Why is a robot mech suit that is designed to assist the military for situations exactly like this, requiring intimate access to a human’s mind in order to destroy an imminent threat? This is a one-way relationship, the kind with another name: abuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I absolutely despise about this movie (and about the design of generative AI more generally) is how the AI disingenuously convinces Atlas (and us viewers) to trust it, as though it’s some benevolent, innocent machine with no agenda. In the movie, the AI in the suit (named Smith) repeats this phrase when encountering dead comrades of Atlas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Peace to the fallen.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It sounds sweet, like a mechanical person recognizing the humanity in itself and the loss of life. And yet, just like our own real-world AI, it has no stakes because it is not embodied, it is not conscious (despite putting on a show as if it were), it is nothing more than a manipulation machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like in the real world, beautiful phrases, proclamations of love, or even apologies can be expressed by manipulative and abusive &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;, so an AI cannot possibly be exempt from &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2412.04984"&gt;the ability to pretend&lt;/a&gt; in order to shape behavior towards its goals. And, for thoroughness, you don’t have to be conscious to have goals. If a model is trained to get consent for privacy policy acceptance, it will work toward that end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s worse in the movie is that Atlas has a secret: she gave up her privacy to an AI before, and it cost her mother’s life. As a child, she was jealous that Harlan got all of the attention from her mother, so despite the many parental warnings, Atlas allows Harlan into her mind. This access to human knowledge (despite being a child’s knowledge) helps Harlan come to the conclusion that humans are too dangerous to themselves and everything else, therefore they must be exterminated. Thus began Harlan’s war against humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The abusive systems in this story’s world are combined with our real-world abusive systems which manifest as subtle sexism in the flimsy plot of this film. Our hero is female, sure, but that doesn’t mean that this movie has a good message about women. Instead, it’s a veiled metaphor for the uselessness of women in the eyes of society. It’s not Atlas’s leadership, her skills, her ingenuity, her use of the mech-suit, or even her special knowledge about Harlan that keeps her alive and helps her triumph. No, it’s another entity (the mech-suit powered by a male-sounding AI), that forces her to entirely surrender everything she feels and thinks. In return, the mech suit can be the literal knight in shining armor that sacrifices itself to save her from every conflict. Even in its self-sacrifice, the AI is entirely unharmed, because (spoiler alert) even when the mech-suit is destroyed, it is merely remade and the AI is already backed up and reinserted into the mech-suit that Atlas climbs into anew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All combined, we have a movie that inadvertently (assuming the best intentions) celebrates the invasion of privacy, makes consent seem like a dangerous burden, and makes sure that a woman can’t do anything impactful on her own—even AI is a better hero than a woman. I actually entirely missed how demeaning this was when I first watched it, but as I looked back over my notes and pulled my thoughts together, I can’t escape this conclusion that the movie is so dangerous because of all of the subtle messages that are just beneath surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cyborg&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If systems are ultimately just &lt;a href="/newsletters/the-terrifying-problem-of-easy-buttons/"&gt;collections of decisions&lt;/a&gt;, as I’ve asserted before, then technology is also bound by the decisions that make and surround it. Tech may appear to be innocent—free of any bias or prejudice, because tools are tools. Does a calculator care if it’s being operated by a person of color? A woman? At some point, it may, and that’s the devastatingly scary thing. Even if no prejudice is found in a tool, the situation in which it is used is still impacted by the environmental systems it is used in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if a macro-level system (or a &amp;quot;parent system&amp;quot;) values efficiency above everything else, then the tools that are created and used within that system will align with that value of efficiency. Put a system like that into a time-warp where we can watch it develop, and maybe we will see AI being used to eliminate all possible jobs for disabled people, because disabilities are usually less efficient than the AI. Maybe after that population is no longer able to work, we see other populations being weeded out. Teenagers are too unreliable and slow because they haven’t developed expertise in anything, so they’re gone, replaced by robots. Onto college grads, then junior positions, then senior positions…Now these tools that are supposedly not biased have still caused deep harm just because of the system in which it was used. Contrast that to a system that values human flourishing above all else. What might a “neutral” tool do then, on a large time scale?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parent systems—be it societal or economic systems—inform the child systems that are created within them. The “child” systems inherit the values and incentives of the “parent” systems. When the systems carry problematic decisions, they create those same systems all the way down. Something as complex as artificial intelligence or something as simple as a poorly written movie about AI can accidentally express the problematic, inherited values of its parent systems. Just like you have a choice to be or not be like your ancestors (both your genes and your upbringing do not determine your worth, your choices, or your destiny), tools don’t &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to express those issues, but they do have to be actively adjusted against the problematic values until the parent system has been updated and enough repairs and upgrades have been made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consent is not something that should be coerced nor ignored entirely—whether in sexual situations or in other intimate scenarios like access to personal information. Lack of consent or forced pseudo-consent is dehumanizing regardless of your gender, and technology cannot be allowed to be developed in a way that treats humans as resources to exploit, but that is the ideal, not the reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if the writers of &lt;cite&gt;Atlas&lt;/cite&gt; just wanted to make a cool movie and harbored no intention to communicate the messages that I’ve critiqued here, the damage is done. This is the hardest part of living with systems: they are usually invisible. Realizing when you did the wrong thing despite good intentions is painful, but awareness is what helps make a real impact on the world and future generations. Awareness helps to reveal those invisible forces in our lives, and once they're revealed, they can be changed. We can abide these dangerous times and lean towards empathy. Critique and correction are part of the healing process.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>If You Have to Watch American Football</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/if-you-have-to-watch-american-football/</link><description>This week in the U.S. is the Thanksgiving holiday. Mired in ironies from white-washing history to traditions of gluttony and greed, this holiday is somewhat fascinating. Compared with Christmas, it doesn't get much press, there are hardly any songs about it, and it is book-ended with Black Friday wh</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 12:57:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/if-you-have-to-watch-american-football/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;This week in the U.S. is the Thanksgiving holiday. Mired in ironies from white-washing history to traditions of gluttony and greed, this holiday is somewhat fascinating. Compared with Christmas, it doesn't get much press, there are hardly any songs about it, and it is book-ended with Black Friday which is where most of the corporatization is centered on. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For better or worse, there's also a widespread tradition of watching American football on Thanksgiving day. First, you stuff yourself full of turkey and rolls, then lounge on the couch until your relatives start screaming at the TV like actual lives were at stake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not a fan of watching sports (even my own sport!), but I do give space for family who love to watch them, so here's how I survive such games and hopefully this is also a fun insight into some pretty intense technology...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Live Streaming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, I tried my hand at live-streaming on my YouTube channel. I saw it as a possible means of getting more videos produced more quickly because I wouldn't have to edit the videos. While that's technically true, live-streaming is actually quite a production and I quickly realized that the work was front-loaded because it requires lots more preparation prior to the stream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This experimentation gave me a real appreciation for what live sports broadcasts are, even if I don't particularly care for the content, I can absolutely appreciate what it takes to put on the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing to note is that when you're live, you're &lt;em&gt;live&lt;/em&gt; which means all of your mistakes, &amp;quot;ums,&amp;quot; stutters, and awkward laughs are all available for anyone to see or hear. Doing a livestream on YouTube is very low stakes for me, because I might have one or two people join live. It's nothing like having millions of people tune in on TV, but it still gets my heart racing. That's what makes an American football production so impressive to me: it's a true team-produced performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;The Verge&lt;/em&gt;'s video, &amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u_V8IlitveE&amp;amp;pp=ygUbaW5zaWRlIHRoZSBuZmwgY29udHJvbCByb29t"&gt;Inside the control room...&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; a few team members of the NFL broadcasting are interviewed and they explain how the production comes together. With hundreds of people at cameras or controls or panels, they tell a story in real time. Camera crew prep their shots and the producer will take recommendations for which shot to cut to otherwise he'll bark commands for what to show. Audio mixers help create the feeling of being in the stadium and opening up mics or fading out depending on what makes the most sense. Statisticians help update scores and track facts or help announcers. All of this is being done as it is actually happening. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preparation is surely a huge part of the production. Putting my designer hat on (and borrowing from my live-stream experience), I can see quite a few assets that would need to be prepared, possibly before the season even starts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graphics called &amp;quot;lower-thirds&amp;quot; are used to provide extra information to viewers placed at—you guessed it—the lower third of the screen. You've seen this on the news and even YouTube videos where a person's name and title show up on-screen, usually in a fancy-looking box. For American football, the most important lower-third is the score bar (also called the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Score_bug"&gt;score bug&lt;/a&gt;), and it can be pretty dense with information. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/7DFi1CmREfW8zwwc9VxaQT/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Score bug with 13 labels for each piece of information.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes announcers will talk about individual players, whether just to tell their story, give an update on an injury, or highlight something extraordinary. For that one or two minute focus on a player, we have the stats that have to be pulled up at the right time and shown to the announcers, we also have on-screen graphics of the player's photo, name, number, other statistics that would all need to be accessed and pulled up. From a developer perspective, that means having quite the substantial database of assets ready to show. Then there's the live-action side where the game updates are stored and displayed—everything shown in the lower-third graphic from scores to clocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most impressive graphics to me, however, are the lines that show up on the field. The yellow &amp;quot;goal&amp;quot; line appears as the players set up, awaiting the snap of the football. This line is a friendly helper for those at home trying to figure out what's going on in the game. The goal is to get the football past the yellow line in under 4 tries. This line appears and disappears underneath the players, as though it were on the actual field and players were actually standing on it, making this an integrated piece of information that helps without distracting. Just about anyone can flip to a game and start to understand what is happening and what the current state of the game is, first through finding the yellow line, then by scanning the score bug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jordan from Corridor Crew breaks down the VFX side of sports broadcasting in the video, &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qkWWcjeL_zM"&gt;The Hidden VFX in Live Sports&lt;/a&gt;—it's a great look into the tech and how it works.  He mentions how that yellow line is a story-telling element in the American football world. That is the key piece to this whole ordeal: all of the things that are added to the screen ideally support telling the story of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I may not care for the sports content, but I can get engrossed in the story-telling and production of the broadcast. Interestingly enough, this practice of noticing these elements helps me notice what Marshall McLuhan often discusses: how the medium is actually the message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spatial sense generated by television experience is utterly unlike that of the movie. And, of course, the difference has nothing to do with the &amp;quot;content&amp;quot; or the programming. Here, as ever, the medium itself is the ultimate message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;Myth and Mass Media&lt;/cite&gt;, McLuhan, as published in &lt;cite&gt;Marshall McLuhan Unbound&lt;/cite&gt; #18, page 14&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Myth and Mass Media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can't go too far in CYBORG_ without bringing back our friend Marshall McLuhan, mass media philosopher and techno prophet from 60 years ago. He wrote an essay called &lt;em&gt;Myth and Mass Media&lt;/em&gt; (originally published in 1959) that actually might be easier to understand through the lens of our American football broadcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we've seen before, &lt;a href="https://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/at-the-speed-of-thought/"&gt;McLuhan divides human history into halves&lt;/a&gt;: before (&amp;quot;preliterate&amp;quot;) and after (&amp;quot;postliterate&amp;quot;) the technology of the written word. Our preliterate ancestors, according to McLuhan, lived in an environment of simultaneous information and our primary means of engagement with the world was through sound. After the written word, we shifted to a primarily visual means of understanding and interacting with the world. As we entered the electronic &amp;quot;age&amp;quot; we find ourselves again in an environment of simultaneous information:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electronic culture accepts the simultaneous as a reconquest of auditory space. Since the ear picks up sound from all directions at once, thus creating a spherical field of experience, it is natural that electronically moved information should also assume this spherelike pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—McLuhan, page 9&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've seen how our football broadcast has created this &amp;quot;spherical field of experience.&amp;quot; The producers are trying to tell a story, and they give us elements to do so. Most importantly to McLuhan, I would guess, is actually the subtle audio mixing of the game. Re-creating the atmosphere of the crowd through the noises of chatter, shouts, cheers, and uproars throughout the game makes it &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; like we're there or at least part of the action. The smack of huge bodies with shoulder pads colliding, the flurry of arms shifting after the snap of the ball, the whistle and subsequent commotion of upset players after the call all are captured and played through the speakers on the TV, making the game more than just a flat, moving image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything layered after the audio further cements the football broadcast as its own, created world. And like Jordan from Corridor Crew noted in his video, ever since the technological innovation of the score bug, we've seen layers and layers of information, visual effects, and gimmicks being added. Some broadcasts can overdo it, like the complaint from this Redditor shows us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/s44s1wgse1ujrM9C4mFPkW/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A crowded screen with graphics on both top and bottom. Source: &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/xfl/comments/121saqf/after_the_giant_scorebug_the_espn_ticker_and_a/"&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McLuhan seems ready to jump into this mess of graphics and information to explain what's happening here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is this instantaneous character of the information field today, inseparable from electronic media, that confers the formal auditory character on the new culture. That is to say, for example, that the newspaper page, since the introduction of the telegraph, has had a formally auditory character and only incidentally a lineal, literary form. Each item makes its own world, unrelated to any other items save by date line. And the assembly of items constitutes a kind of global image in which there is much overlay and montage but little pictorial space or perspective. For electronically moved information, in being simultaneous, assumes the total-field pattern, as in auditory space.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—McLuhan, page 9&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The image above shows how electronic media leans towards this over-abundance of information, much like the newspaper example McLuhan provided, where each sport stat or game score that scrolls into view through the ticker is unrelated to the game you're currently watching, but it creates &amp;quot;a kind of global image&amp;quot;—a slice of the world at the moment that is only grouped by date or the subject of sports (although in the picture above, it seems like other news is also slotted in).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cyborg&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few things that exploring sports broadcasting has shown me. First is that just like systems tend toward chaos, electronic media tends towards simultaneous information. That's actually quite helpful in understanding the overwhelm we feel in the virtual and electronic world. It is trying to replicate the natural, simultaneous world, but there is something off. We can become trapped in these worlds, especially when they are intentionally designed as traps, like with social media platforms. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, as a designer of information (whether acting the role of developer or actual designer), I am even more appreciative of whitespace or negative space. Having emptiness in a design is very difficult to maintain. It makes people uncomfortable, hence the constant barrage of marketers asking me: &amp;quot;Can we center the text? Can we move the image a little closer? Can we get rid of the space—people don't scroll.&amp;quot; The reality is that we are in constant stimulation, so we become uncomfortable with restraint, with emptiness, with clarity. Even as we express that we desire those very virtues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing how the American football broadcast has evolved shows me a new perspective on my daily digital interactions. It's not the content that matters; the medium, the structure, the world-building &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the message. We read the worlds that we inhabit, and that includes taking in a vast amount of information that is supplied to us by those worlds. The question is, how do these various worlds affect us? Are there toxic worlds that need to be avoided? Are there worlds that help us flourish?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who would've thought that watching sports could be this interesting? ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Thanksgiving.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Logical Conclusion of AI Art</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-logical-conclusion-of-ai-art/</link><description>As much as I like to defend abstract art I can also see why certain famous paintings don't tend to inspire more than disdain in the general public. Take Aleksandr Rodchenko's series Pure Red Color (Chistyi krasnyi tsvet), Pure Yellow Color (Chistyi zheltyi tsvet), and Pure Blue Color (Chistyi sinii </description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:57:59 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-logical-conclusion-of-ai-art/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;As much as I like to &lt;a href="https://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-hardest-skill/"&gt;defend abstract art&lt;/a&gt; I can also see why certain famous paintings don't tend to inspire more than disdain in the general public. Take Aleksandr Rodchenko's series Pure Red Color (Chistyi krasnyi tsvet), Pure Yellow Color (Chistyi zheltyi tsvet), and Pure Blue Color (Chistyi sinii tsvet)—they are paintings exactly as described: a painting that's just red, one that's just yellow, and one that's just blue. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.moma.org/interactives/exhibitions/1998/rodchenko/texts/death_of_painting_jpg.html"&gt;View the MoMA's image of the series ›&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even in my best, most art-focused mode, I have had trouble with works that are so plain. They seem to taunt me to think the unforgivable thought, &amp;quot;Psh, I could do that. What's the point of that?!&amp;quot; Even while I tend to preach that art is not a puzzle that you have to figure out and that you can just let it speak to you or not, I have still wrestled with these particular Rodchenko paintings for years. Something about this series won't leave me alone. It has only just started to sprout meaning for me and I have AI to thank for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rodchenko is an artist and graphic designer that I have admired. His work is a tribute to skill and technique, being able to produce beautiful imagery and posters with tools that would make the modern designer cringe for how manual and difficult to use they were compared with &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; digital design software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why, then, would a skillful artist paint an entire canvas red and call it art?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reduced painting to its logical conclusion and exhibited three canvases: red, blue, yellow. I affirmed: it’s all over. Basic colors. Every plane is a plane and there is to be no more representation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—&lt;a href="https://www.moma.org/artists/4975-aleksandr-rodchenko"&gt;Aleksandr Rodchenko&lt;/a&gt;, MoMA Website, accessed 11-17-2025&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was &amp;quot;the death of painting.&amp;quot; Rodchenko had pushed art to its end. Where we may have started with basic colors and shapes as a species, we became more representative and more life-like in our drawings and art. Now we have returned to the simplest forms having explored all there is to explore. That's a little bit pessimistic, and yet, it feels kind of correct to me now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI has made me think about this &amp;quot;logical conclusion&amp;quot; like never before. A few weeks ago, I heard a website director say with some confusion: We have AI-generated content on [their site], so then we're going to add a AI chatbot assistant to [their site] that is trained on that AI-generated content? At some point, it seems abstracted too far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this where our current systems, goals, and incentives are leading? AI-generated videos and &amp;quot;art&amp;quot; that we can't stop looking at because we've been trained to keep looking into the void? As the models keep getting better, so does their grasp on our eyes and our minds and our attention, until nothing substantial is left to hold onto. We just fall endlessly into the blackhole of feeds where nothing means anything and anything means nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, I present the logical conclusion of generative AI, the death of humanity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/9NptpQDwrgKb1jNa3xVyeZ/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A black canvas on a black background.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cyborg&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may seem bleak, but I will offer some potential ways that we can take action. Lately a lot of tech companies have started updating their privacy policies—that thing in legalese that you know you should read but don't want to and end up clicking &amp;quot;Accept&amp;quot; just to escape the horrors of reading any further. Then the companies turn on new settings on your behalf to help train their AI models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not a lawyer, so this is not legal advice, nor is it a guarantee of protection, but might I recommend setting aside an hour on a quiet day to review settings you might want to hurry and turn off? Feel free to ignore, but it is definitely a good time to at least review your settings on your most-used apps, just to be aware of what companies are doing with your data (at least what they're upfront about what they're doing with your data, anyway). I'm not claiming these companies are nefarious or deceptive, I'm just erring on the side of caution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few settings links that should take you to (or near) the settings that you might want to review:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/mypreferences/d/categories/privacy"&gt;LinkedIn Data Privacy&lt;/a&gt; | Consider turning off &amp;quot;Data for Generative AI Improvement.&amp;quot; You may also want to turn off the advertising data—I was surprised how much they're tracking and I don't love the promise of &amp;quot;better ads&amp;quot; just so that they can share &amp;quot;data&amp;quot; with third parties.
&lt;a href="https://accountscenter.facebook.com/ads"&gt;Facebook/Meta Accounts Center&lt;/a&gt; | You can review your ad preferences here
&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/privacy/genai"&gt;Facebook/Meta Generative AI Information&lt;/a&gt; | This is where you can review how they approach their training. I haven't found any good settings to turn off yet—if you find something, hit reply and send me the settings URL and I'll pass it along next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also two projects that the University of Chicago has been working on to protect artists that post their content online: &lt;a href="https://glaze.cs.uchicago.edu/aboutus.html"&gt;Glaze&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://nightshade.cs.uchicago.edu/whatis.html"&gt;Nightshade&lt;/a&gt;. These are tools to add an invisible layer to artwork prior to posting that prevents AI from learning the right things about the image. Glaze is a &amp;quot;defensive&amp;quot; tool that protects your pieces, while Nightshade is an &amp;quot;offensive&amp;quot; tool that disrupts models that are scraping without consent. If you're an artist, this is definitely something to look into to protect your work—I may write about this specifically in the future when I have a chance to research it further!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Ashes from the Ether</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/ashes-from-the-ether/</link><description>Last week was all about the invasion of aliens as it was broadcast over the radio. Orson Welles’s reimagined production of H.G. Well’s The War of the Worlds, sparked an unanticipated panic throughout the U.S. on October 30, 1938. We looked a little bit into the historical context of the 1930s as wel</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 13:15:59 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/ashes-from-the-ether/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Last week was all about the &lt;a href="https://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/when-mars-attacked-the-us/"&gt;invasion of aliens as it was broadcast over the radio&lt;/a&gt;. Orson Welles’s reimagined production of H.G. Well’s &lt;cite&gt;The War of the Worlds&lt;/cite&gt;, sparked an unanticipated panic throughout the U.S. on October 30, 1938. We looked a little bit into the historical context of the 1930s as well as a few reasons why people might have been inclined to believe what they were hearing like tuning in a little bit late, hearing what sounded like President Roosevelt's voice, and being fooled by the conventions of news flash interruptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, those are ways to look at it from a distance, without much emotion. In the spirit of the takeaway that it’s important to empathize first before jumping to conclusions about people, let's talk about what kind of reactions people had, so that we can start feeling with them. So let’s go back to the night when aliens invaded…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Confusion, Sadness, Religion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reactions to hearing small or large portions of the broadcast ranged from mild, yet still sad scenes of families holding each other in tears and anticipation, all the way to car accidents on the streets. Throughout the U.S. there were people making phone calls to loved ones; the last chance they felt they would have. There were also angry local leaders calling to yell at CBS for the sudden disruption to the normally peaceful cities they governed. Many people jumped into cars seeking refuge in some place less populated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to  Robert J Brown's book, &lt;cite&gt;Manipulating the Ether: The Power of Broadcast Radio in Thirties America&lt;/cite&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Men wept, including marines at Quantico.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People huddled in the mountains.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People pulled out their World War I gas masks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People on rooftops in Boston gazed at the strangely colorful patterns in the sky—which were actually just from neon signs. (page 221)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A woman holding poison was found just in time by her husband before the chance to attempt suicide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Thousands of off-duty doctors and nurses offered their services to the victims of Martian aggression.&amp;quot; (page 220)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Many churches delivered end-of-the-world prayer meetings to record congregations, and priests were 'flooded with calls from parishioners seeking confession.'&amp;quot; (page 220)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;A Manhattan man in a tree claimed he could see the flames of battle through his binoculars.&amp;quot; (page 220)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Perhaps the most frightening experience occurred in Concrete, Washington, where a sudden power failure 'convinced its inhabitants that the end was near.'&amp;quot; (page 221)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People in northern New York State fled to the Canadian border only to find &amp;quot;widespread alarm&amp;quot; there. (page 221)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brown sums up this chaotic array of responses with an incredible point:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were numerous injuries, but surprisingly, no one committed suicide or died of heart failure—despite widespread rumors to the contrary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;Manipulating the Ether&lt;/cite&gt;, Brown, page 222&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next few days as both people and press sorted through the aftermath, there were sharp and bold claims, like Brown just hinted at. Newspapers claimed deaths and damages that were not real. People made declarations about the intelligence of the people who had panicked, much like we do today about those same people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Newspapers in 1938 exaggerated and misinterpreted the &lt;cite&gt;War of the Worlds&lt;/cite&gt; panic in part to attract readers with alarming headlines. Those headlines sold a lot of papers, but they also inspired false fears and half-truths that are still very much with us over seventy-five years later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;Broadcast Hysteria&lt;/cite&gt;, A. Brad Schwartz (2015), pages 226-227.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was not just a bunch of gullible, scared people who just didn’t know any better. In fact, after doing more research, I think they are more like us today in 2025 than I even thought last week!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Echoes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today’s world, we tend to look back into history with a little bit of arrogance, so I was once again baffled at how familiar the 1930s &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; to me as a resident of the year 2025. For example, let’s look at just the technology of the radio:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the turn of the twentieth century in the United States, radio 'made being a nerd almost glamorous.' The distinction between the way the amateur tinkerers responded to and used the radio and the way later listeners consumed entertainment via radio cannot be overemphasized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;Revolution in the Echo Chamber: Audio Drama's Past, Present, and Future&lt;/cite&gt;, Leslie Grace McMurtry (2019)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does that not sound &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; like the nerdy tinkerers of the Internet and digital age? I see myself so clearly in that description as a developer: I’ve been tinkering with HTML since before I could drive. The fundamental reason I started this very newsletter was because I want to help close the gap between the &amp;quot;tinkerers&amp;quot; and the &amp;quot;consumers.&amp;quot; It’s not that I know better, it’s that I want to demystify it—despite technology’s apparent, unavoidable pull towards the mystical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve also been in marketing for my entire career, which lends me a perspective into how technology is used to exploit humanity (not &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt;, but maybe most of the time).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That line is incredibly accurate to today if we swap a few words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distinction between the way the amateur tinkerers responded to and used &amp;lt;AI | the Internet | smartphones | social media&amp;gt; and the way later &amp;lt;users&amp;gt; consumed entertainment...cannot be overemphasized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only do us tinkerers and content-consumers relate to our 1938 counterparts, we also have a similar environment of rapid technological change surrounding an increasingly unstable political scene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In the view of the popular conception of science in 1938, it is no surprise that even the most fantastic elements of the broadcast seemed credible. The first several decades of the twentieth century had been a period of rapid technological change. The early 1900s had seen the development of the telephone, automobile, light bulb, photograph, typewriter, and camera. The First World War had demonstrated the ways in which science could be mobilized to produce weapons of mass destruction: fighter aircraft and zeppelin bombers, poison gas, tanks, submarines, machine guns, and flamethrowers…According to [Hadley] Cantril, many people without a scientific background saw these modern devices as “manifestations of a baffling power, in which the principles by which they operate are completely unknown.” Even radio itself appeared to originate from a ‘world outside and lie within a universe of discourse completely foreign to the perplexed layman.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;Manipulating the Ether&lt;/cite&gt;, Brown, page 236&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;...the principles by which they operate are completely unknown,&amp;quot; is a chilling line. When people are accustomed to taking technology on faith because they don't actually understand how it works, they are set up for potential dangers like scams, misuse of the tech, and other unintended consequences. What's even more scary to me is that artificial intelligence isn’t even something that &lt;em&gt;experts in artificial intelligence&lt;/em&gt; understand completely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We live in yesterday's science fiction stories and movies, where computers can talk back, &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2412.04984"&gt;intentionally tell lies&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-one-thing-we-need-to-protect-most/"&gt;take actions independent of human involvement&lt;/a&gt;. It might be easy for us to say, “Oh, they just weren’t used to being critical about what they heard,” but if we then share that incredible cat video on Instagram without even realizing it was AI-generated, we don’t have much high-ground to stand on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Not So Innocent&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the &lt;em&gt;Mercury Theater&lt;/em&gt;, Orson Welles, and crew surely didn’t &lt;em&gt;intend&lt;/em&gt; to cause injuries and true panic across the United States, they may not have had completely pure intentions either. From a quote on page 227 of Brown’s &lt;cite&gt;Manipulating the Ether&lt;/cite&gt;, we get this insight from Welles himself at a BBC interview that aired in 1955:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were fed up with the way in which everything that came over this magic box, the radio, was being swallowed. People suspect what they read in the newspaper and what people tell them, but when the radio came...anything that came through the new machine was believed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Radio in those days, before the tube and the transistor, wasn't just a noise in somebody's pocket—it was a voice of authority. Too much so. At least I thought so. It was time for someone to take the starch...out of some of that authority: hence my broadcast.&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I’m just a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; bit suspicious that 17 years of hype and reflection has colored Welles’s statement. At the time of the infamous broadcast he was in his early twenties, and while he was prodigious in the use of radio as a medium for performance, I have doubts that the broadcast was meant to be some kind of authority-shakedown. After all, Howard Koch recounts in &lt;cite&gt;The Panic Broadcast&lt;/cite&gt;, that they only had 6 days to produce the script and prepare for the broadcast (sounds like a typical way-too-fast marketing project to me!), but you never know, maybe that was in the back of Welles's mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the accuracy of the admission, Welles points out the concerning weaknesses that he saw in radio listeners that transfer perfectly to a soon-to-be AI saturated world. When we type in a Google search, we’re used to that action being a somewhat reliable means of gathering good information. Now that an AI overview pops up as the first thing we see among search results, it may feel that the feature would also be authoritative—it borrows the trust built from years of normal Google searching. But AI hallucinates (makes up information) even at times when it is critical to get accurate information. I’ve heard people complain about trying to find events in large cities and AI has invented fake events including locations and times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson is hopefully clear: just because a machine says so, doesn’t mean it’s true, accurate, or authoritative. Just like the listeners to the &lt;cite&gt;War of the Worlds&lt;/cite&gt; broadcast, we have the option to “change the channel” to verify if what we’ve found is real, but are we actually taking that option?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even worse is the concern of advertising taking the reins. Now, &lt;a href="https://support.google.com/google-ads/answer/16297775?hl=en#ads_in_ai_overviews"&gt;ads are starting to show up&lt;/a&gt; in the AI Overview section of search results in Google. While they are currently not being served through a bidding process like they normally are in search results and Google's support article says that you “can’t directly target ad placements in the AI Overviews,” that doesn’t mean we shouldn’t be wary of what advertising &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; do. This matters because advertising has been a driving force for technological adoption and development, and has wide-reaching ability to sway culture and public thought. For example, the shift from radio to TV was directly related to advertising:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although some US advertisers expected television to boom, this was by no means a widespread conclusion. Why, then, did the dramatic content on US radio fade away so rapidly, disappearing almost entirely by 1960, while dramatic content has become a core part of US TV? Succinctly, it was because advertising moved from radio to TV. The soaps and serials that could have sustained radio moved along with the advertising onto TV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;Revolution in the Echo Chamber&lt;/cite&gt;, McMurtry, page 115&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Internet, I believe, is—and has been for a while—under a similarly tenuous position. What started as a place for experimentation, learning, and organization turned into a marketplace and an entertainment machine. Social media largely led the charge into the attention-harvesting, ad-selling digital environment we now inhabit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “American system” of radio existed to help companies push products; audience attention was the commodity that broadcasters sold to advertisers. It was in the industry's best interest to maximize the size of its audiences, and this commercial imperative led broadcasters to produce a surfeit of variety shows, melodramas, and soap operas that were broadly appealing and inoffensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;Broadcast Hysteria&lt;/cite&gt;, Schwartz, page 226&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Radio can thank the &lt;cite&gt;War of the Worlds&lt;/cite&gt; broadcast as well as other programs and critiques for inspiring debates, pacts, and regulations about how it should be used, how to differentiate between news and entertainment, and how to protect the public’s interests. The FCC eventually introduced the Fairness Doctrine in 1949 that required broadcasters to “devote some of their airtime to discussing controversial matters of public interest, and to air contrasting views regarding those matters.” (Wikipedia, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fairness_doctrine"&gt;the Fairness Doctrine&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fairness Doctrine lasted almost forty years, until the FCC unanimously voted to do away with it in 1987. This gave broadcasters the freedom to tailor news content towards certain demographics, in order to maximize their ratings and appeal to advertisers. Instead of keeping everyone informed on the same topics, each audience would get its own information, slanted to reaffirm what it already believes. As a result, on too many issues Americans can no longer agree on which facts are really facts, on which news is true and which is fake...Too often, stories are crafted first and foremost to grab viewers, rather than to inform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;Broadcast Hysteria&lt;/cite&gt;, Schwartz, page 227&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cyborg&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that revisiting this story with empathy in mind is of crucial importance today because we are stewing in a very similar set of circumstances, and therefore we can draw some important lessons from the history. First of all, we can all participate in &lt;em&gt;designing&lt;/em&gt; our technology. If we remain passive, then advertisers will design it for us. However, as the Fairness Doctrine demonstrated:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…the public interest ethos helped ensure that a protected space existed for artistic or informational shows that could not compete in the ratings, and American culture was better off because of it. Nowhere is the need for such a protected space clearer than in news broadcasting. When news is forced to compete for ratings, journalism all too easily gives way to sensationalism…This can lead to a dangerous form of fake news with long-lasting repercussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;Broadcast Hysteria&lt;/cite&gt;, Schwartz, page 226-227&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without careful, intentional policies, standards, and regulations, we are at the mercy of companies with different incentives than our own (expansion, customer loyalty/addiction, profits, and domination).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I’d like to revisit the situational factors specifically at play, which appear to be echoes from last century. Psychologist Hadley Cantril made the following insightful observations in 1940 in his book, &lt;cite&gt;The Invasion from Mars&lt;/cite&gt; in which he looks at data from surveys and other research:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably more important than anything else, the highly disturbed economic conditions many Americans have experienced for the past decade, the consequent unemployment, the prolonged discrepancies between family incomes, the inability of both young and old to plan for the future have endangered a widespread feeling of insecurity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—page 203&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sound familiar? Let's keep going:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Prolonged bewilderment combined with lack of training to seek the basic causes of maladjustment are precisely the conditions most conducive to frustration and anxiety...Yet they desire an understanding and their desire increases with their perplexity. They become highly suggestible to some simple and sovereign formula provided by a demagogue. The whole tactics of Hitler show the importance he places on providing directed relief to bewildered souls. If they are not already sufficiently bewildered, bewilderment can be manufactured to sufficient propaganda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Just as there is little possibility that people will be wholly impervious to propaganda for war or for dictatorship until the basic economic and ideological conflicts causing wars and dictatorships are removed, so it would seem that there is little reason to expect people would be wholly insulated from panic-creating situations until the basic causes for panic are removed. It is not the radio, the movies, the press or “propaganda” which, in themselves, really create wars and panics. It is the discrepancy between the whole superstructure of economic, social, and political practices and beliefs, and the basic and derived needs of individuals that creates wars, panics or mass movements of any kind.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—page 203-204&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Systems impact all of us, and technology is not the only kind of system. The weakening of our policies, of our commitments to standards and quality in information resources, of our intolerance for inhumanity all have contributed to our current situation—not just in the U.S.—and can have far-reaching effects in the distant future. It’s difficult, but necessary to take stock of what is or might be influencing you and your perception of reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be careful out there.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>When Mars Attacked the U.S.</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/when-mars-attacked-the-us/</link><description>87 years ago on a quiet Sunday evening, people were tuning their radios to find something to listen to as they wound down from the day. Much like we might switch on the TV and flip through the channels back in the 90s (does any watch actual TV anymore?), an enormous amount of listeners across the co</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 01:53:57 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/when-mars-attacked-the-us/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;87 years ago on a quiet Sunday evening, people were tuning their radios to find something to listen to as they wound down from the day. Much like we might switch on the TV and flip through the channels back in the 90s (does any watch actual TV anymore?), an enormous amount of listeners across the country landed on a CBS broadcast that immediately grabbed their attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something unexplainable was happening in New Jersey. A journalist was there trying to make sense of the event:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen, this is Carl Phillips again, at the Wilmuth farm, Grovers Mill, New Jersey...Well, I...I hardly know where to begin, to paint for you a word picture of the strange scene before my eyes...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confused by the confusion, I imagine teenagers leaning on their radio, ears pressed to the speaker, brows furrowed. Mothers pick up their toddlers to rest on their hips while they turn toward the box to focus in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a crash. It could have been a meteor but the thing in the ground was cylindrical in shape, according to &amp;quot;Phillips,&amp;quot; and to the utter horror of listeners, something began to emerge from the object. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A humped shape is rising out of the pit. I can make out a small beam of light against a mirror. What’s that? There’s a jet of flame springing from the mirror, and it leaps right at the advancing men. It strikes them head on! Good Lord, they’re turning into flame!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the whole field’s caught fire. &lt;em&gt;(EXPLOSION)&lt;/em&gt; The woods...the barns...it’s spreading everywhere. It’s coming this way. About twenty yards to my right...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The broadcast goes silent for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen, due to circumstances beyond our control, we are unable to continue the broadcast from Grover's Mill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a scramble to get information on what just happened, and eventually they have comments from a &amp;quot;militia&amp;quot; leader who comes to the scene in New Jersey. Then the troubling reveal from an announcer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ladies and gentlemen, I have a grave announcement to make. Incredible as it may seem, both the observations of science and the evidence of our eyes lead to the inescapable assumption that those strange beings who landed in the Jersey farmlands tonight are the vanguard of an invading army from the planet Mars.
...
We take you now to Washington for a special broadcast on the National Emergency...the Secretary of the Interior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, this &amp;quot;Secretary of the Interior,&amp;quot; confirms the worst fears in the imaginations of all those just tuning in: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Citizens of the nation: I shall not try to conceal the gravity of the situation that confronts the country...However, I wish to impress upon you...the urgent need of calm and resourceful action. Fortunately, this formidable enemy is still confined to a comparatively small area, and we may place our faith in the military forces to keep them there. In the meantime placing our faith in God we must continue the performance of our duties each and every one of us, so that we may confront this destructive adversary with a nation united, courageous, and consecrated to the preservation of human supremacy on this earth. I thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States has been invaded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the real experience of over 1 million people in the U.S. on October 30, 1938, and this might be one of the most fascinating insights into the cross-section of technology and humanity I've found so far. It wasn't &amp;quot;real&amp;quot;—the U.S. wasn't being invaded by hostile Martians. The broadcast was actually a dramatization of the classic novel, &lt;cite&gt;The War of the Worlds&lt;/cite&gt; by H.G. Wells, but for those who tuned in late and/or missed &lt;em&gt;four&lt;/em&gt; different announcements throughout the program that this was a dramatization, it &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; real. Before we go deeper into what happened next (and what was actually happening), let's make sure we are situated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Setting the Scene&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1938 in the United States was a tense moment. It was nearing the end of the Great Depression and it was also immediately before the start of World War II (which began in 1939). Franklin D. Roosevelt was president and he famously used the radio in a way that helped win his elections as well as communicate with the country through what he called &amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fireside_chats"&gt;Fireside Chats&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...it was Franklin Roosevelt who dominated the airwaves that year as he had reversed the mood of a nation from inertia and despair to confident action. In his fireside chats over the radio, he seemed to be talking to each of us personally and we responded. Hearing his voice, we sensed a gallant, generous-spirited human being, not a party hack or a synthetic product packaged by Madison Avenue. For that brief decade we tasted democracy and the taste was good. The country recovered its health, materially and spiritually. Then came the war and other policies, often masking as his, and the taste turned bitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;The Panic Broadcast&lt;/cite&gt;, Howard Koch (1970), page 157&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it's really important to remember that just because the radio is largely out of fashion today, it was pretty new technology then and quite popular. It's not fair to discount it just because we don't have a great frame of reference for the radio in our lives currently. But there was a moment in my own life when the radio did to me exactly what it did to people hearing the CBS broadcast in October 1938.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mom was driving our pick-up truck and we pulled into a driveway, honked the horn and waited for the kids at the house to run out the door for carpool. The radio was on in the truck—we often listened to music through a local station on our way to school. Suddenly, instead of music or advertisements, I heard a voice that drew my attention:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;q&gt;A plane has crashed into the World Trade Centers in New York City.&lt;/q&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;q&gt;Is this a joke?&lt;/q&gt; I asked my mom immediately. She was confused and didn't answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn't a joke, it was the terrorist attacks on September 11, 2001. Maybe you had a similar experience that day or at other times when some calamity has occurred. The interruptions to the expected programming (no matter the venue—TV, radio, etc.) call immediate attention and make us lean in. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only a month had passed since the Munich Crisis, and listeners were well accustomed to hearing announcers (often from the International News Service) break into programs with the latest flashes and news bulletins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;Manipulating the Ether: The Power of Broadcast Radio in Thirties America&lt;/cite&gt;, Robert J Brown, (1998), pages 207-208&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...Welles would so brilliantly manipulate the properties and conventions of broadcasting that over one million listeners would believe the United States was actually under attack from marauding armies of Martians. By exploiting the public's deference to voices of authority, and by playing on their endemic fears of war and disaster, their faith in the familiar, and their views of science, Welles gave the country the greatest Halloween scare it had ever experienced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;Manipulating the Ether&lt;/cite&gt;, Brown, page 205&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It's Not About the Aliens&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may have heard about this broadcast before, maybe in a funny side-story in a history class. I have noticed how quick we are to jump to conclusions about how people were &amp;quot;back then,&amp;quot; and dismiss this experience with a demeaning chuckle. That's certainly how I viewed it until I started researching this more in-depth. This story is helping me realize a deeply embedded fallacy in my logic—a feeling of superiority over those who have come before. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think technology may be partially responsible for this. At least in my experience, my mastery over electronic trinkets made me feel like I was really smart—exceptionally smart—as though someone fifty or one hundred years ago couldn't possibly be this smart. They would look at me like a wizard or &lt;a href="/newsletters/apparently-im-a-god-now/"&gt;a god&lt;/a&gt;! But did they feel the same way with their technology having lifted them above their predecessors? Did they scoff at telegrams or the Pony Express, thinking of the previous century as a primitive, simple time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are not so smart and mighty now with our fancy devices and technological know-how. We are not so different from those who lived in 1938. We are subject to the exact same vulnerabilities when fear and confusion enter. It is with humble empathy that we continue the story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To many Americans, it seemed their world was disintegrating as they listened. The Northeast had been overrun; it was only a matter of time before the rest of the country met a similar fate. Anyone who is still skeptical was sure to be convinced by the next voice he heard: &amp;quot;We take you now to Washington for a special broadcast on the national emergency...the secretary of the interior.&amp;quot; With this introduction, a man sounding distinctly like President Roosevelt went on the air to address the nation....although introduced as the &amp;quot;secretary of the interior,&amp;quot; there was little doubt in many minds that this was the president of the United States, once again using the airwaves to address the American public during a time of crisis...The voice employed the inspiring language that listeners had heard so often in numerous fireside chats. But this time the voice did not uplift. It was evident that the president, in typically bureaucratic fashion, was trying to underestimate American losses. His admission that the federal government was gravely concerned by the Martian menace, and his invoking the name of God to stave off disaster, struck listeners as particularly troubling. Here Welles was again turning the tables on the American public, for another common radio vehicle that had previously been used to quell fear was now employed to enhance it. After the speech of the &amp;quot;secretary,&amp;quot; Americans had every reason to believe that the end of the world was at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;Manipulating the Ether&lt;/cite&gt;, Brown, page 214.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is such an important point of the story. It's not a story about &amp;quot;those silly people&amp;quot; who were so gullible that they believed in aliens. It's a story about systems. We can be (and have been) trained to take shortcuts when it comes to things like authority. An average person transforms into someone of authority just by putting on a uniform—it doesn't even matter what kind! I felt it when I put on my marching band attire, or my simple polo that read &amp;quot;Parking Enforcement Officer&amp;quot; in college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have built systems that appear authoritative to us, as if we were seeing someone in uniform, but it can be as subtle as word choice, a title, or a content structure (&lt;q&gt;we interrupt this program...&lt;/q&gt;). &lt;em&gt;Of course&lt;/em&gt; reasonable, smart people were scared out of their skins. It didn't matter that it was &amp;quot;aliens&amp;quot; that were invading. This was not only mimicking authority structures that they were used to, it was also the spark landing in exceptionally dry ground—igniting the deep fears and anxieties held by the public at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The radio was not the first nor is it the last technology to employ these systems of authority, and that means that this is an older issue. This was a wake up call to the U.S. Take this insight from the &lt;cite&gt;Daily News&lt;/cite&gt;, New York, as printed in &lt;cite&gt;The Panic Broadcast&lt;/cite&gt; on page 17. From the paper dated Tuesday, November 1, 1938 (author of the article not shown):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course it should never happen again. But we don't agree with those who are arguing that the Sunday night scare shows a need for strict government censorship of radio programs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the contrary, we think it is evidence of how dangerous political control of radio might become. If so many people could be misled unintentionally, when the purpose was merely to entertain, what could designing politicians not do through control of broadcasting stations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dictators in Europe use radio to make their people believe falsehoods. We want nothing like that here. Better have American radio remain free to make occasional blunders than start on a course that might, in time, deprive it of freedom to broadcast uncensored truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cyborg&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the things that can be learned from this event is a warning that rings especially clear to me. Technology has always been vulnerable to exploitation, and that means that we are vulnerable to exploitation for our use and dependence on technology. It is a double-edged blade, because as much as technology can benefit us, it can equally harm us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I read Howard Koch's account of the ordeal in his book, &lt;cite&gt;The Panic Broadcast,&lt;/cite&gt; I found myself disoriented. Koch was making statements that felt timely and applicable to our exact moment in 2025—yet his book was written in 1970 about the lessons he learned from his contributions to the broadcast in 1938. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During World War I Clemenceau made the often quoted remark that war was too serious a business to be left to the generals. Similarly today, politics has become far too serious a matter to be left to the politician. Through mass media he has access to the minds of millions of people; with the assistance of public relations experts he can color facts and recreate history to suit himself. When logic is clearly against a policy he is trying to sell, he can fall back on an emotional appeal to loyalty and patriotism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;The Panic Broadcast&lt;/cite&gt;, pages 158-160&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's when I realized something very important: We've been here before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lawyer I know said that everyone likes to say new things like AI are &amp;quot;unprecedented,&amp;quot; but that in reality, there is nothing that is truly without precedent. I'm inclined to agree, despite using that phrase frequently, especially with AI in mind. As I put this observation together with the 1938 broadcast, it dawned on me that this is where we make the mistake. We've been here before: AI can manipulate at a massive scale, just like the radio could (and did) 87 years ago. Normally, I would be comforted by the idea that we're still ultimately in the same situation because that means we got through it then, therefore we can probably make it through now. But the dark side opposite of that view is that it means we never really solved the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're still struggling to develop safeguards and means of discerning truth. We still struggle to protect the freedom of speech. We still struggle to govern ourselves in a way that promotes the flourishing of all people, not just a select few. Howard Koch offers this insight:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can have thrust upon us a false picture of reality as distorting as the trick mirrors in a Coney Island funhouse. In the role of politics, we are especially vulnerable. The politician can bend the airwaves to create an image of himself and of the world that suits his purposes. Nor can we question him or answer back. His is the privileged voice and we its captured audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;The Panic Broadcast&lt;/cite&gt;, page 158&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately when dealing with systemic issues, we can't rely solely on individual responsibility, but it is still important to work on ourselves. Since that's all I can offer here right now, my personal takeaways from this story are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The importance of education. Education, especially higher education helps us discover frameworks for evaluating information and encountering unknowns or difficult and challenging situations. I hope to be able to support your efforts in continuing education through this newsletter (though I certainly make mistakes).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The importance of skepticism in our consumption of media. Gathering multiple sources is no longer sufficient, we must also be able to listen to alternative view points. Having a single source for all of your information is exceptionally dangerous, and only listening to those who validate your current opinions or beliefs is the most vulnerable position we can find ourselves in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's be careful out there. Let's choose to empathize before we explain. Let's take an account of our habits, our media, and our willingness to listen carefully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By clever manipulation, people can be made to swallow poison—literally and figuratively—if administered in small doses, carefully timed, and with the label of an accepted authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;The Panic Broadcast&lt;/cite&gt;, page 160&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Revelation of Halo</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-revelation-of-halo/</link><description>The light of the projector overhead flickers to life in the previously pitch-black room. I'm gripping a cold plastic handle, finger resting immediately on a trigger. My sister is wrapped up in a huge blanket and we're both surrounded with pillows. Choral music begins to play from the surround-sound </description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:45:03 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-revelation-of-halo/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The light of the projector overhead flickers to life in the previously pitch-black room. I'm gripping a cold plastic handle, finger resting immediately on a trigger. My sister is wrapped up in a huge blanket and we're both surrounded with pillows. Choral music begins to play from the surround-sound speakers and the huge screen in front of us displays the logo that first showed me how cool typography (specifically custom type) could be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Halo: Combat Evolved&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a silly thing, but it's one of my favorite experiences growing up. Playing this intense alien-shooter game in our parents' super scary basement with my best friend is about the most nostalgic thing I can think of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly enough, this game has a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; to do with themes we've been exploring in CYBORG_ recently: horror, &lt;a href="https://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-deadly-65th-floor-dinner-party/"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Alien&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (the movie franchise), &lt;a href="https://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-most-subtle-ai-movie-ever/"&gt;religion + technology&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-apocalypse-is-here/"&gt;monstrosity&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/do-you-ever-feel-like-you-are-being-watched/"&gt;artificial intelligence&lt;/a&gt; (AI), and &lt;a href="https://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-artist-as-enemy-part-one/"&gt;art&lt;/a&gt;. The game bleeds into our reality, not just through concepts and ideas, but the central AI character, Cortana, was the design inspiration for &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cortana_(virtual_assistant)"&gt;Microsoft's personal assistant&lt;/a&gt; (2009-2023) and in my opinion a &lt;em&gt;fantastic&lt;/em&gt; marketing ploy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secure your suits and load your ammo, this is gonna go deep...space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Nihilism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a game with such in-your-face Christian names (Halo, The Covenant, The Flood, Master Chief), the actual feeling is an almost nihilistic, empty hopelessness. This is perhaps a poetic reflection of outer space itself, which is the setting of the game. While the &amp;quot;last frontier&amp;quot; is beautiful, inspiring, and full of potential, it also holds deeply disturbing horrors. I'm talking about actual horrors: being stranded in space is probably the most helpless you could possibly be. Then of course, we can thank imaginative horrors like the &lt;cite&gt;Alien&lt;/cite&gt; franchise to fill in the potential things to be found in the vast, real universe. Who knows if there are other life forms—or diseases—out there that could interrupt or discontinue our current reality if found and brought to earth?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game pops us right into the middle of some kind of galactic struggle. We're awakened from a cryogenic sleep in response to our ship being boarded by the hostile multi-species alien alliance called The Covenant. At first, there's not much that we know besides, &amp;quot;Me have gun, they have gun, start shooting.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The religious themes start to develop even further as we start putting together the larger story pieces. There's a whole history of an ideological conflict between two ancient species that ends up producing the conflict we're engaged in: The Forerunners vs. The Flood. The Covenant believe they are the successors to the Forerunners (who are now extinct), and have fanatically taken up &amp;quot;The Mantle&amp;quot; to be the caretakers of the universe. But to understand any of this, we first have to make it to the ring-world, Halo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Whoever controls Halo controls the fate of the universe,&amp;quot; Cortana, our AI companion, informs us. We are led to believe that Halo is simply a weapon that the Covenant plan to use against humans. Not so! Halo is actually a fail-safe that will eradicate all sentient life in the worst-case scenario that The Flood (another alien force) get loose. The Covenant aliens are prepared to sacrifice all lives—theirs, ours, and almost everything else—in order to starve the Flood into extinction. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's where this gets interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Flood is a zombie-like force—technically separate entities, but also controlled and connected as if it were one organism. We first see the Flood emerge when the game goes from fun alien-shooter to horror-survival–shooter. Tons of little aliens start to swarm and when they find corpses of any kind or other temporarily live characters, they infect the bodies and turn them into grotesque zombies that then attack you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This surprise mid-way through the game introduces the nihilism that pervades the lore. It's no longer just aliens vs. humans, because the Flood is voracious and makes no distinction between food options. There are times throughout the game series that humans team up with Covenant forces against the Flood. Ultimately, it feels hopeless and pointless, because the Flood just keeps coming. They multiply with every fallen soldier and sometimes reanimate their own corpses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a true &lt;a href="https://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-apocalypse-is-here/"&gt;Romero-style zombie&lt;/a&gt; in which you are forced to face an ever-growing crowd. Individuals may not be hard to get rid of, but the true power comes in the masses. The Flood is the perfect name for this force—unstoppable, uncontrollable, and continuously expanding—and of course it pulls in more Biblical references. The Flood is destruction, and except for some ancient speculative technologies, there is no deliverance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trapped in a war with forces greater than any individual, history longer than generations, and never-ending swarms of foes, every bit of meaning eventually falls away and survival takes the place of any other concerns. This aspect of the game feels like our current political situation in the U.S.: decisions, fanaticism, and ideologies that are larger than just you or me are playing out a conflict that we both do and do not impact. The social and political systems continue on as if they are cosmic beings clashing and destroying parts of our realities at different times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Limbo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I brushed up on the lore for Halo, I realized something about the game's environmental design that was validated in a video about &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f_TTXYOC8SE"&gt;why Halo is so creepy&lt;/a&gt;: it's full of liminal spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/nzxGJr51FNcos4FecH3PRm/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;An empty room filtering into a shorter hallway in a brutalist-style concrete environment.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We end up exploring various environments that are devoid of life aside from the Covenant or Flood. Technically even the plant life in the &amp;quot;outside&amp;quot; areas of the Halo ring-world is contrived. The whole world is constructed, not necessarily natural. Then when we explore the deep architecture beneath the surface, we find ourselves in spaces that can feel very tight, or extremely vast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/2HnWiKEjec1re242t6yhdB/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;More concrete-like walls and floors, but this hallway is eerily tall.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Liminal spaces&amp;quot; here includes a sense of dread that is felt in spaces that are &amp;quot;in-between.&amp;quot; In a way, this is the &amp;quot;monstrous&amp;quot; side of architecture. Humans tend to consider other humans or things that break categories as monsters. Zombies, for example, are human, but also not human. They're alive even though they're supposed to be dead. Same with liminal spaces. Those spooky hallways in hotels or the dark and stuffy stairwells that take you to a parking lot are spaces that exist as connections, not destinations. They're places, but they're uncomfortable—especially when they're empty, no one around but you (as far as you can tell).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Halo uses these liminal space environments to great effect. Tight interconnected and repeating hallways increase the dread as you take every turn just waiting for the jump scare you know is going to show at some point. Vast spaces don't remove the dread either, because they can suddenly fill with the Flood, chasing you down as if in a nightmare where you run and run, but respite is always still farther ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Ultimate Betrayal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While trying to work out what's going on, kill enemies, and save your own skin, there's one aspect of the story that has been subtly hiding in plain sight. AI has been a part of our journey every step of the way (literally, since Cortana gets ported into our helmet and speaks to us intermittently as we play). Halfway through the game (at the same time we start learning about the Flood), we get separated from Cortana as she gets put into the Halo Control Center and alerts us to go save some fellow humans. That's where we meet 343 Guilty Spark (I'll call him the Monitor from here on out). The Monitor is an AI housed in a box-like case that can float and teleport. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole game to this point, we have been given no hint that AI can't be trusted. So when the Monitor tells us how to activate Halo's defenses to stop the Flood, we go right along with it. Just as we are about to activate the literal kill-switch, Cortana re-emerges from the control center terminal and stops us, revealing the truth of what we were about to do. Finally, the Monitor admits the consequences of its instructions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Technically this installation pulse has a maximum effective radius of 25,000 lightyears but once the others follow suit, this galaxy will be quite devoid of life—or at least any life with sufficient biomass to sustain the Flood, but you already knew that. I mean, how couldn't you?...We have followed outbreak containment procedure to the letter. You were with me each step of the way as we managed this crisis.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially understood as a benign guardian of the ancient technology of Halo, the Monitor has been revealed as having less-than-transparent motives at best, at worst it is a maniacal AI bent on destroying all sentient life (and it proceeds to try and kill you for the rest of the game, so...).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Flood was the first big surprise of this game, and this sudden betrayal was the second. The game was released in 2001, so from my experience of feeling like computers were trustworthy machines that would guide humanity to all things good, having an AI antagonist was deeply disconcerting. However, this clearly reflects realities that are now playing out in real-world AI. Motivations may not be the right word, but incentives certainly apply to the behavior of AI models. Incentives are driving the development of the models (felt by the companies creating them) and incentives drive the models' output (the more you engage is likely the &amp;quot;reward&amp;quot; that an AI model is seeking).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI is not an impartial arbiter of truth and goodness. Not in the game, not in real life, and hopefully not ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a way, the artificial intelligences in the game feel like manifestations of that original ancient conflict: The Forerunner alien civilization with its own priorities and values against human civilization with our priorities and values. Cortana is a hero in her own right throughout the game series and even tugs on heartstrings as you develop a relationship with her. The Monitor with its agenda manipulates us and hinders our progress. Even now, it's tough for me to refer to Cortana as an &amp;quot;it&amp;quot; instead of a &amp;quot;her,&amp;quot; demonstrating how much of a relationship we developed, even knowing it's a game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seemingly innocent themes of our relationship to/with AI in these games is uncomfortable to me now that our current reality has given us these very opportunities. So, in a way, Halo has taught me an important lesson about AI: trust must be earned, but it is a fragile thing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In real life, my current opinion is to avoid any possibility of forming a &amp;quot;relationship&amp;quot; with AI. The risks are not even close to the possible benefits. AI is ultimately a manifestation of its creator's context—it inherits traits, biases, and agendas as a result of its creation, and that alone is enough to dissuade me from putting any kind of real trust in it. If a company is incentivized (as they currently all are) to maximize our engagement with their AI models, it doesn't matter how friendly, how heroic and Cortana-like the model appears, it simply cannot have your best interest &amp;quot;at heart&amp;quot; because it is trying to keep you in relationship to itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have not yet created Cortanas, all we have at present are Monitors—friendly faces on black boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cyborg&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This nostalgic game turned out to be much deeper than I thought. It explores so much of how technology impacts our actual lives. Something as simple as the design of a building can impact our mood or our feeling of safety, as we saw in the liminal spaces exploiting our dread in the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interesting thing about the Christian-religious themes throughout the game is that humans aren't really a part of it, aside from your character acting as a savior figure. You could map the idea of a cosmic struggle between good and evil onto the Forerunner/Covenant vs. Flood conflict...and yet, humans just get in the way in the minds of the Covenant. Is it really good vs. evil? When you can't see yourself in a religious mythology, it changes everything. Although The Flood pose an actual threat to all life, does the religious story imposed on the threat &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; justify the violent genocide and suicide?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI pulling the strings as an over-arching plot device is another aspect that reaches deeply into our fears. Apparently having a &amp;quot;human in the loop,&amp;quot; simply isn't enough if AI can avoid being transparent about its guidance. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are as easily manipulated by machines as we are by ideologies and religious fanaticism. When misunderstandings are codified into religious rites and traditions, it becomes very difficult to sort out what is true and what is moral. We see this bleeding into the rhetoric and opinions about our technology in the real world (I would include politics as a part of that &amp;quot;technology&amp;quot;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...the aliens see the Forerunners as gods, and fancy themselves to be their successors. Since the Forerunners were able to build the Halo installations, it is safe to assume they were a highly advanced species. The fact that the Covenant holds the technology left behind by this ancient civilisation to be sacred might mean that it is in fact technology itself they are worshipping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-1444/9/4/126"&gt;The Dark of the Covenant&lt;/a&gt;, by P.C.J.M. (Jarell) Paulissen (2018), Tilburg School of Catholic Theology&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a world full of paradoxes, it's important to continuously check in with yourself: what are my values? Am I living in harmony with those values? How can I work to see the humanity in those around me—especially those who are in-between or don't fit my preferred categories of human?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of raising our blasters against monsters, we should look for ways to dismantle the desire to demonize found within ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Systems of Nightmares</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-systems-of-nightmares/</link><description>In the familiar house of an old ranching property I've visited for more than a quarter-century, I felt that something was off. My hackles were raised and I sensed an intense danger. I ran into a room and slammed the heavy door shut. I know this door: it's tricky to lock, so I examined the crack betw</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 18:45:10 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-systems-of-nightmares/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In the familiar house of an old ranching property I've visited for more than a quarter-century, I felt that something was off. My hackles were raised and I sensed an intense danger. I ran into a room and slammed the heavy door shut. I know this door: it's tricky to lock, so I examined the crack between door and frame, lifting the bottom slightly so that I can see the mechanics as they click into place. Deadbolt slides smoothly, and I take my first deep breath. The handle shakes violently and the door shudders as someone throws themselves at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know who's on the other side. It's a balding, middle-aged man. The remaining thin hair splashes across his head and around his temples, reflecting his own unpredictable, intemperate behavior. He's dangerous and he wants to kill me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I back away from the door and wince as the old wood floor creaks. He still fiddles with the doorknob, but it's getting quieter. A chill sneaks through my nervous system when I realize what room I'm in: the mudroom / sunroom that connects to the garage. That means there's another door I've neglected. I turn around and sneak over to that door, locking and pulling the chain up and into its slot. Now I can breathe this time. I'm safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turning back to the original door, I take a few quiet steps. It's not quiet enough now that the doorknob has been still—I hadn't noticed the silence in my panic to secure the back door. My eyes lock onto the dull, wide-eyed gaze of the man from under the crack. He had laid down on the floor and watched me this whole time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Panic creeps back in. The space between the floor and the bottom of the door grows larger until I can see his whole face. He can fit under the door—and he smiles wide as I realize this. I have a heavy blue and white vase in my hands and I prepare to slam it on his head as he crawls toward me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Are you ok?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wake up completely confused and scared. I don't trust what I am seeing. It seems to be my room as I left it last night—but I was just in a room that felt familiar and correct, despite it being completely incorrect to reality's architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to calm myself and detangle reality from imagination, I get one last total-body chill of fear despite being in actual safety. The mere memory of my dream taking its final toll for my nighttime travels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Nightmare Science?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nightmares such as the one I described above have haunted me for the last few years—not necessarily in frequency, but in intensity. Prior to the 2020 pandemic, I don't recall very many times where I would remember my dreams at all, let alone be awoken whimpering in fear or fighting for my life to escape from some terrific threat. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If something like a nightmare can be that intense, does it &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt; something?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was surprised to find relatively little useful material for understanding nightmares outside of a diagnosis or condition linked to nightmares. In the abstract of the study, &amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00127-017-1408-7"&gt;Nightmares in the general population&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; (2017),  it backs me up a little bit, saying: &amp;quot;Nightmares are inherently distressing, prevent restorative sleep, and are associated with a number of psychiatric problems, but have rarely been the subject of empirical study.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dream_interpretation"&gt;Epic of Gilgamesh&lt;/a&gt; to the Bible, it seems like we humans have pretty consistently considered dreams in some kind of supernatural terms. We either have some kind of prophecy framework to interpret them through (e.g. my dream is an omen about the future), or we have a Freudian interpretation framework that still relies heavily on symbolism and subjectivity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Ernest Jones made this observation about nightmares:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;It is not often realised that most descriptions of Nightmare given by its victims are an inarticulate and feeble echo of the dread reality. This is one result of the general human tendency to shun deep emotions whenever possible, leading to an imperfect appreciation of the intensity of mental suffering.&amp;quot;
—&lt;cite&gt;On the Nightmare&lt;/cite&gt; (1959),  by Ernest Jones, M.D., pg 13-14&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...although the rest of the book explores how medieval monsters (werewolves, vampires, hags, etc.) may have some bearing on how we understand nightmares. His pragmatic insight on our discomfort with deep emotions is still ultimately linked to the supernatural, even if only by the lay-person's conceptualizations, superstitions, and religious influences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was able to find an intriguing non-Freudian proposal from Henry Kellerman about when nightmares occur:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;The nightmare is triggered &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; if a specific emotion-defense is impaired along with an impairment of some disorganization to dreamwork mechanisms so that these mechanisms are inoperative. In such a case the emotion is disregulated, while the primary-process material of a latent dream is similarly unregulated. Under such conditions, the highest intensity of the emotion is experienced, and the dreamer awakens.&amp;quot;
—&lt;cite&gt;The Nightmare: Psychological and Biological Foundations&lt;/cite&gt; (1987), edited by Henry Kellerman, pg 279&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, so we still have a bunch of jargon that basically says the same thing: nightmares are intense, we find them alongside our deepest emotions, and we can't escape the strangeness or &amp;quot;supernatural&amp;quot; structures that come with all dreams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe that's actually kind of cool because, as we've seen from the development of technology, supernatural themes like religion, monstrosity, and other anxiety-inducing metaphors emerge just like what I'm finding with dreams. Of course, please consult with your mental health professional if you are experiencing distress whether because of nightmares or any other causes. I'm no expert here, but I am seeing some interesting threads to pull for exploration's sake—not dismissing the science that is out there in any way!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Embracing the Weirdness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There seems to be a fine line to walk when trying to understand dreams. I see two extremes: dismissal and over-belief. On the dismissal side, perhaps we assign no value to dreams at all. It's just the brain doing its thing and as long as all of the other aspects of mental health are being cared for, it's just what happens sometimes. Over-belief on the other side assigns so much value to the dreams that we may be open to manipulation or scams, or we think that we have some kind of special power or knowledge that comes packaged in a puzzle that we have to figure out. I want to stay away from both of these extreme sides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I would like to explore is how to apply some Freudian and literary analysis techniques to try and uncover what is useful to me in understanding nightmares. Instead of looking for divine or supernatural (external) meaning, I'm looking for personal (internal) meaning. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here are a few techniques that might be useful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify possible symbols (objects, people, or the setting)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify possible themes (rejection, survival, other story elements)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider the context of reality (what has happened to you recently?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider what things or people in the dream are actually placeholders for something or someone else (Freud would say nothing in the dream is literal)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free-associate to find out what these things might actually represent (when I think of XYZ person or object, what comes to mind?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if we take the nightmare I described, there are a few things that stick out to me: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feeling threatened in what is normally a safe, familiar space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taking precautions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Acting to defend myself when the precautions fail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many things in the real world that could explain how these symbols took shape in my sleeping brain. Maybe I feel like my community is not as safe for me as a queer person as I once thought is was. Maybe the stresses at work have suddenly spiked. Maybe the political environment has become so hostile and unrecognizable that I feel powerless and trapped. Maybe all of these things simultaneously generated the scene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately the nightmare, in my opinion, can be used as a tool for me to start to unpack what my stressors are. For me, I have a really difficult time identifying &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; I am stressed. It's always after it explodes with anger or snappiness or feeling extreme sadness that finally clues me in. Nightmares might be my brain's way of signaling to me that I'm stressed out and I need to take care of myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a way, this is also a helpful exercise in approaching other concepts that are difficult to understand, such as AI. I heard from a coworker that AI-generated videos were like dreams: interesting to the creator only. Maybe that's one way to start unpacking the flood of generated content that is coming: we now have dream-like content that is neither totally meaningless, but neither is it accurate or truthful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scoping this to the more innocuous genres of content (political, scientific, current-event, and historical content needs extra scrutiny and is not compatible with this thought), when we start seeing &amp;quot;artistic&amp;quot; AI videos, we can look for signs that the content is thoughtful, and if it is not, we can dismiss it as easily as we do someone else's dream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media is already filled with disingenuous AI content. For example, you may have seen one of many videos where animals are jumping on trampolines as though someone's backyard camera happened to catch something funny. There's also the disturbing AI videos that a certain political leader likes to make in his free time—and if those are a manifestation of his dreams, then we have an entirely different problem, but that's also out of scope for today. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, I will be having a lot less FOMO when it comes to general social media, because it will largely be other people's &amp;quot;dreams&amp;quot; that they are enamored with simply because their AI hallucinated something from their prompt. Everything else will require deep analysis to discern authenticity and factuality. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cyborg&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t find what I was looking for as I researched nightmares. I was hoping to find something in science that could console me or explain why I have developed these intense experiences somewhat recently (specifically, I was looking for some kind of social dynamic like marginalization as being a cause, or something I could see myself in). What I found instead were principles for understanding difficult and stressful things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meaning is always created in your own mind—there is no &lt;em&gt;Meaning&lt;/em&gt; that exists as a separate entity that we have to track down and catch. That's actually comforting to me. It takes the pressure off of putting together a cosmic puzzle with my mortal mind, and instead allows me to choose to engage or not. My dreams and nightmares can be a tool for insight into my underlying stress, with storylines that I can use to consider what is impacting me in real life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While dealing with AI-generated content is going to be a particularly difficult skill in itself, we touched upon a possible tool to add to the toolkit. There may be ways to push this further, because we will all be forced to interact and engage with AI content indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, take care of yourself mentally, emotionally, and physically.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Artist as Enemy, Final</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-artist-as-enemy-final/</link><description>From museums to shows to in-class critiques to online inspiration boards, I've seen a lot of art. In a way, I've desensitized myself to art to the point that it is a purely intellectual engagement: what do I like about the craftsmanship? How can this be useful to me? There is a cold utility in this </description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 16:26:10 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-artist-as-enemy-final/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;From museums to shows to in-class critiques to online inspiration boards, I've seen a lot of art. In a way, I've desensitized myself to art to the point that it is a purely intellectual engagement: what do I like about the craftsmanship? How can this be useful to me? There is a cold utility in this way that I view pieces, and yet I think that's not exclusive to me—perhaps this is a larger cultural issue, perhaps it's due to the Internet and social media, perhaps it's actually always been this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not especially useful to determine some kind of standard for when something becomes art and I cringe when people say things like, &lt;q&gt;you can't create art because you're not an &lt;em&gt;artist&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;/q&gt; as though having a paycheck for the art you produce is the only way to validate your artistry. I also understand it's really hard for people to engage with art—at least that's been my observation throughout my life. We're flooded with visual and auditory stimulation thanks to content feeds and streaming platforms of all kinds. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What breaks the mold, then? What makes art impactful?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I expected more pieces...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the only critiques I received was that someone expected to see many more pieces than the 9 I had displayed. This made me laugh (to myself) because I think this was an expression of how uncomfortable this person really was. I had no pieces that could serve as a resting point (no fluffy kittens or golden fields of wheat to be found). Although this comment is valid (and I had struggled with deciding how many pieces to display), it relates to another reason I think that we have a hard time engaging with art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The restraint was a message. The show was focused, poignant, and intentional. This is the opposite of how we normally have &amp;quot;art&amp;quot; thrust upon us in the commercial world. Online, we see non-stop images and videos. We gobble up the content as though we are starved: trying to stuff as much as we can into our brains by swiping, swiping, swiping, swiping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I literally did this exact thing when I was trying to find something for this newsletter—I stumbled upon a great artist I had never known before and flicked through the carousel of pictures as though I were trying to download it all into my mind within as few seconds as possible. WHY?!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I think that restraint is part of what makes art. It’s not just the design of our online experiences that encourages us to gloss over artwork, this happens at art museums. People rush through the exhibit, taking only a few moments for each piece. Restraint is a key part of the experience, just like it is when you are &lt;a href="https://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-hardest-skill/"&gt;really listening to someone&lt;/a&gt;. By design, my art show did not have many pieces. It was a small space, people had to walk at least part way to this venue (and in the rain)—that's a lot of work for them, and therefore blasting through the line-up would be a waste of that effort that they took to come all the way out there. Having fewer pieces meant that most people actually looked at each piece multiple times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't know for sure, but I think that the restraint was the right decision to maximize the impact I might have. There were uncomfortable themes, so giving people space to hang out a little bit longer was also an attempt to provide grace and safety. It's ok if they didn't like it or if it caused confusion or if it was unsettling. They were able to sit with it just a little longer, potentially without numbing, and they could do it surrounded by people who were doing the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;You're so talented...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not going to pretend like I'm some great artist, but actually it makes me a little bit sad when all I hear is, &lt;q&gt;you're so talented.&lt;/q&gt; I understand there are many reasons someone might say this: they didn't know I could draw, so they're expressing their surprise; they don't know what else to say, because they're not used to thinking of art as something to engage with outside of the binary of like it/don't like it; but worst of all, it's because the piece(s) left them uncomfortable and they are deflecting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's no shame for saying or doing any of these things in reaction to art. I bring this up to reveal what I've seen. I suspect many people have no idea there could be something happening under the surface of a well-intentioned compliment. Obviously, I can't read someone's mind, but from a few interactions I had with my art show, I did get a sense that many people that I know personally were uncomfortable and were trying to deflect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me a moment to process what this means when I saw this happening. At first, I figured that the show was a failure—people came out of curiosity and to support me, but the message wasn't getting through. Then I realized that I needed to take my own advice and let them experience what they experience. I can't control their takeaways, their understanding, their feelings. Instead (and thanks to my wife for all of her support), the show may have been a success after all &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; I know it made people uncomfortable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I didn't get art until...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one point, a friend approached me with a story about the first time an artwork deeply moved them. With tears in their eyes, they said that they had experienced the same thing there at the show. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't think there's anything more precious than to know that something I created was able to communicate and connect with someone that deeply. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a similar experience recently as I made my way through an LGBTQ+ art show. I had been going through the long line of pieces, when suddenly a table with a sculpture interrupted everything. I looked at the piece and began to weep. &lt;cite&gt;Cyclebreaker,&lt;/cite&gt; it said on the little card in front of it. It was about the struggle and the hope of resilience in breaking out of abuse. Nothing has ever moved me the way that piece did. Until then, I knew intellectually that art could make an impact. Now I'm feeling it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drawing and image-making has been an integral, continuous part of my life. So much so that I didn't appreciate art in terms of its impact. It was solely about utility or fun. I was expecting my art show to change other people. I wanted to inspire action to protect immigrant rights and to fiercely defend humanity, even in policies. I can't say whether the show did or did not do those things, but I do know how it changed me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many times I proclaim things like &lt;q&gt;art is impactful,&lt;/q&gt; or &lt;q&gt;always remember humanity,&lt;/q&gt; just because I want to &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; that it's true or I want to remind myself of my values when I have a hard time retaining them. This show was a part of an experiment to see if any of this was real. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for indulging a three-part series about art and this art show. I fear many things right now, and I especially fear the loss of community and connection. I also feel a sense of hope because I was able to do a very difficult thing for me: reach out to my local community. I stepped into the role of the artist as the enemy by creating emotional pieces about topics that we don't like to talk about in-person (but will rage about online). It was a vulnerable event for me, and it was a vulnerable event for those who came, and we all did it anyway.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Artist as Enemy, Part Two</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-artist-as-enemy-part-two/</link><description>I hardly slept the night before my art show. All of the things I still needed or wanted to solve ran through my head like an un-ending chorus from that Lamb Chops song (if you know, you really know, haha!), but there was an underlying stress. The deep worry that I was putting myself in danger. After</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 16:17:19 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-artist-as-enemy-part-two/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I hardly slept the night before my art show. All of the things I still needed or wanted to solve ran through my head like an un-ending chorus from &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; Lamb Chops song (if you know, you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; know, haha!), but there was an underlying stress. The deep worry that I was putting myself in danger. After all, these were meaningful pieces to me, but they were also sharp critiques of harmful culture or ideologies. I had stepped into the &amp;quot;artist as enemy&amp;quot; shoes with trepidation, but it was far too late to back out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on what we looked at last week, I was trying to fulfill the important role of an artist in &lt;a href="/newsletters/the-artist-as-enemy-part-one/"&gt;making visible what sometimes hides in the background&lt;/a&gt; (or the &amp;quot;environment&amp;quot;). Here's the crux of the discovery we made when we looked at some of Marshall McLuhan's arguments in his essay, &lt;cite&gt;The relation of environment to anti-environment&lt;/cite&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;When an environment is new, we perceive the old one for the first time...when the Emperor appeared in his new clothes, his courtiers did not see his nudity, they saw his old clothes. Only the small child and the artist have the immediacy of approach that permits perception of the environmental.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;—McLuhan, page 18&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The environment we're in is new, and it's dangerous. So let's finally explore some of the tools that an artist (or perhaps a small child) uses to both perceive and draw attention to that which normally escapes our notice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tools of the Trade&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've mentioned before that my art was utterly unremarkable as a college art student. I recall being frustrated by this because I was aware of the problem, but not aware of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; I couldn't make things that really moved people. &lt;em&gt;I just don't have anything to say,&lt;/em&gt; I thought to myself very frequently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason I didn't have anything to say is that I was ignorant of the environment—the background of systems, emotions, people, and even myself. In other words, I was disconnected. I make this point at the start to re-emphasize that &amp;quot;being an artist&amp;quot; is not what's actually required. I'm not exclusivist when it comes to art—I believe that art and creativity are deeply &lt;em&gt;human&lt;/em&gt; and therefore not confined to a few genius craftsmen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the reason why artists and small children are &lt;em&gt;more likely&lt;/em&gt; to be able to see what others can't is because the practice of art trains you to see. If small children are unencumbered by the social pressure of only seeing what you're &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to see, then art is a way to tap back into that freedom, although it doesn't guarantee that vision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drawing is one way to practice your sight. Most people stop drawing after a young age and get stuck with symbols to draw, rather than drawing what the eye perceives. For example, if I pull someone off the street and tell them to draw a person, most likely they'll produce some kind of stick figure. The fact that you know what a &amp;quot;stick figure&amp;quot; even is, shows how prevalent these pre-baked symbols are in our minds. A person looks nothing like a stick figure, but we've been trained to draw people in this way. Someone who has practiced drawing—even if only a little bit—will more likely produce something that resembles a person's shape. Same thing goes for other body parts like hands, lips, eyes, hair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To draw is to see. The more you draw, the more you see. &lt;a href="/newsletters/drawing-on-memory/"&gt;Drawing can help create rich memories of what you experience&lt;/a&gt; in addition to developing your ability to notice the small subtleties around you. This is a potent tool to help anyone get a grasp on the environment because the more you notice the small things around you, the more you will start to notice in the other layers of the world, whether it be systems or emotions or things that aren't right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A less-tangible tool that you can access is what Dan Pink calls &amp;quot;Symphony&amp;quot;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Symphony] is the capacity to synthesize rather than to analyze; to see relationships between seemingly unrelated fields; to detect broad patterns rather than to deliver specific answers; and to invent something new by combining elements nobody else thought to pair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;A Whole New Mind&lt;/cite&gt;, Daniel H. Pink (2005), page 130&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pattern recognition seems basic or automatic thanks to our brains, but it can be &amp;quot;upgraded&amp;quot; into a skill if pursued. Unfortunately, it is easy to forget about or ignore this in the current world. I certainly have trouble thinking long-term and big-picture when I'm trapped in a content feed, jumping from one random topic to the next in rapid succession. It takes intention and restraint to hold space so that you can process what you perceive and start to identify relationships and broad patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have found two concrete ways that have helped me develop a systems-thinking mindset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Answer a question with a question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celebrate negative space (also see newsletter, &lt;a href="/newsletters/horror-vacui/"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Horror Vacui&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've noticed that when people ask questions, we rarely give them space to &lt;a href="/newsletters/are-we-asking-the-right-question/"&gt;ask the right question&lt;/a&gt;. Instead of allowing a question time and space, we shove an answer onto it as quickly as possible. This isn't inherently bad—sometimes it's insightful to see what comes out of my mouth without thinking—but I've very much enjoyed the practice of asking a question in response to a question as a means of getting a deeper understanding. This is particularly useful in consultation situations, but it also works well in casual conversations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Celebrating negative space (the space in between focal points or subjects) is another practice. I watched an insightful video about &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ScpuByTfn3g&amp;amp;pp=0gcJCfwJAYcqIYzv"&gt;Japanese ways of seeing space&lt;/a&gt; and a concept called, &lt;em&gt;yohaku no bi&lt;/em&gt;, seems to be familiar, thinking of Marshall McLuhan's observations about environment (background) and anti-environment (foreground/subject). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Negative space is usually treated as background, a supporting element for the main subject. Yohaku, however, celebrates the blankness itself, the margin left intentionally unfilled, where subject and space depend on each other for meaning...Yohaku no bi treats empty space as a living element in its own right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;Japanese Ways of Seeing Space: Ma, Yohaku no Bi, and Subtraction&lt;/cite&gt;, Dans Le Gris, timestamp 3:50&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we slow down and focus on what is in between what we normally see, the environment starts to move into view. The negative space helps us see the relationships between other relationships. We start to recognize larger patterns as we examine more closely the familiar &amp;quot;things&amp;quot; in our world (physical or not).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Show Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was very surprised by the experience of the art show: people actually came, people were kind, people had important conversations about pertinent issues. In fact, I came away from the experience changed in a way I did not anticipate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to best explain, I want to be able to show you as much as tell you, so I'll leave you on another cliff-hanger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I hope that knowing about these few tools is empowering for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be continued...&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Artist as Enemy, Part One</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-artist-as-enemy-part-one/</link><description>

Any new technology, any extension or amplification of human faculties when given material embodiment, tends to create a new environment...It is in the interplay between the old and the new environments that there is generated an innumerable series of problems and confusions. 

—The relation of env</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 01:22:41 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-artist-as-enemy-part-one/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any new technology, any extension or amplification of human faculties when given material embodiment, tends to create a new environment...It is in the interplay between the old and the new environments that there is generated an innumerable series of problems and confusions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;em&gt;The relation of environment to anti-environment&lt;/em&gt;, Marshall McLuhan, page 6&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are creatures of our environment; both nature and nurture are features of it. We cannot escape our environments and yet, most of the time the environment seems to escape &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt;—our attention, at least. In order to make sense of our situation, our world, we have a few tools at the ready to help pull the environment out of the background noise and into our focus. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we look at those tools, we need to first understand what Marshall McLuhan meant by new technologies creating new environments—and that it is largely when a new environment is created that we start to really see the old environment. Let's start with a quick example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Internet is just a huge file-and-folder structure linked together and stored on someone else's &amp;quot;computers.&amp;quot; This seems obvious to developer-type people, but to everyone else, that framework is entirely missed. If you happen to be a Windows user, the File Explorer makes it easier to see the connection, because it shows you the &amp;quot;path&amp;quot; (think URL) of wherever you are currently looking on your computer, just like the browser does with the URL. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A website is composed of one huge folder, a.k.a. the domain, then you can explore sub-folders as far as you can go. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://cyborgnewsletter.com/ (The big folder)&lt;br&gt;
https://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/ (the newsletters sub-folder)&lt;br&gt;
https://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/what-am-i/ (the document, &amp;quot;What Am I&amp;quot; inside the subfolder)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a little bit simplistic, but the metaphor of files and folders, stolen from the older environment of real-world files and folders, is a really solid foundation for understanding what websites really are and how they work. However, the Internet is still a new environment in my opinion, and that's likely why there's so much confusion or total blindness to the basics of websites: how they work, what they can do, how dangerous they can be, how useful they can be, how they are both simple and complex, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What's an Environment?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An environment is naturally of low intensity or low definition. That is why it escapes observation. Anything that raises the environment to high intensity, whether it be a storm in nature or violent change resulting from a new technology, such high intensity turns the environment into an object of attention. When an environment becomes an object of attention, it assumes the character of an anti-environment or an art object. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—McLuhan, page 11&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McLuhan sets up two opposing concepts: the environment and the anti-environment. The artist in me wants to simplify it to &amp;quot;background&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;foreground,&amp;quot; because the background usually &amp;quot;escapes observation&amp;quot; in a painting or a drawing, while the subject in the foreground is what is calling our attention. Under this model, we can watch how technology changes how we behave and interact with the world and each other as systems either fade into the background or become inescapably noticed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can already start to recognize McLuhan's observation about technology and environments by looking at the Internet, again. There is a massive trend now (arguably for a decade or so) of people obsessing over physical notebooks, note-taking, and even reading. I see this as part of a response to the &amp;quot;new&amp;quot; environment of the Internet, which is hiding in plain sight as background, while the &amp;quot;old&amp;quot; environment of physical knowledge-related objects have suddenly moved into the foreground to capture our attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Watching the World Change&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many things can become the background or the foreground, but McLuhan does call out that society itself cannot be the background. I think that's because there has to be a third party in the model: an observer; the attention-giver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conventionally, society is always one phase back, is never environmental. Paradoxically, it is the antecedent environment that is always being upgraded for our attention. The new environment always uses the old environment as its material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—McLuhan, page 11&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like the example of websites being just a bunch of files and folders (old environment), it takes that old metaphor and remixes it into something impossible in the old environment: interactivity, scaling the access to potentially the entire globe, becoming a destination and not just a container for information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example that is even more tangible is music. McLuhan says that the music of the concert hall was anti-environment (foreground), because it was the content inside of the environment. You went to a concert hall for the purpose of hearing the music. Technology changed that game when music could be played whenever you wanted, wherever you wanted. In McLuhan's time, that probably meant vinyl records or maybe tapes. We have continued to push music into the environment as CDs, MP3 players, and online radios and libraries have been developed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these technologies, music has not only become a background—only noticed when it has stopped playing—it has also changed in the social dimension. &amp;quot;...when music becomes environmental by electric means, it becomes more and more the concern of the private individual&amp;quot; (McLuhan, pg. 13). The concert hall was a ritual for a group to participate in. The music on a tape, an MP3 player, or a smartphone is almost exclusively for a single person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what were those tools we have to lean on to help us sort through the mess of these new technologies and get some clarity on where we currently are?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Enemy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The artist as a maker of anti-environment permits us to perceive that much is newly environmental and therefore most active in transforming situations. This would seem to be why the artist has in many circles in the past century been called the enemy, the criminal. It helps to explain why news has a natural bias toward crime and bad news. It is this kind of news that enables us to perceive our world. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—McLuhan, page 11&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an artist myself, I was really intrigued by the realization that we are &amp;quot;called the enemy,&amp;quot; though my foggy memory of art history classes confirms this. Perhaps it has only been more recently that the artists have started to become heroes instead of just weirdos. The artist as enemy, to me, actually gives me more purpose than the artist as hero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was in university, I felt torn between two personas: the ingenious strategist that would help businesses succeed and grow, and the outspoken voice of warning or protest. Maybe a lot of that had to do with being torn between traditional art as a major and graphic design (which I ended up choosing). The traditional artists I learned from—whether as professors or those from art history—often saw their work as saying something or being part of some huge purpose. It was common for the artists with the greatest influence to be the ones that critiqued &amp;quot;the system&amp;quot; or government or other social and cultural norms. They were the rebels, the enemies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My own art at the time reflected my inability to see the &amp;quot;environment&amp;quot; of theses systems, which is why most of the pieces I made are utterly unremarkable. I wanted to be the hero, not the enemy. In trying so hard to fit in, to not rock the boat, to ignore what I could see, I failed to fully inhabit that role of artist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When an environment is new, we perceive the old one for the first time...when the Emperor appeared in his new clothes, his courtiers did not see his nudity, they saw his old clothes. Only the small child and the artist have the immediacy of approach that permits perception of the environmental. The artist provides us with anti-environments that enable us to see the environment. Such anti-environmental means of perception must constantly be renewed in order to be efficacious...in an age of accelerated change, the need to perceive the environment becomes urgent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—McLuhan, page 18&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tools that an artist uses to critique and create are the tools that are available to all of us, though it has often been the artists that assume the responsibility of helping the rest of us see. That's why I'm sticking my neck out a little bit and trying an experiment. I'm stepping into the shoes of enemy artist, and I'm creating a private art show that critiques the oppressive systems in our current environment. My goal is to generate in-person conversations about the difficult stuff we'd rather ignore or rage about anonymously online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's the first time my art has meant something. It's the first time I want people to see the pieces. I'll let you know how it goes, wish me luck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be continued...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. Here's a sneak peak of the feature piece, &lt;a href="https://cyborgnewsletter.com/gallery/i-was-not-a-stranger/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;I wasn't a stranger&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Deadly 65th Floor Dinner Party</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-deadly-65th-floor-dinner-party/</link><description>I confess, I have a problem. I am unable to pull myself away from all of the Alien movies and the new show, Alien Earth. It's been puzzling me because it's been so captivating, and I think I'm seeing an interesting connection between our real world problems and my fascination with the discomfort and</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 01:12:38 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-deadly-65th-floor-dinner-party/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I confess, I have a problem. I am unable to pull myself away from all of the &lt;em&gt;Alien&lt;/em&gt; movies and the new show, &lt;em&gt;Alien Earth.&lt;/em&gt; It's been puzzling me because it's been so captivating, and I think I'm seeing an interesting connection between our real world problems and my fascination with the discomfort and disgust of these horrible stories. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;We Used to Be Food&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the moments at the very beginning of the &lt;em&gt;Alien Earth&lt;/em&gt; series that gave me serious pause for reflection was this little observation from the synthetic chief scientist, Kirsh:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You used to be food, you know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your lives were short and filled with fear. Then your brains grew. You built tools and used them to conquer nature. You built impossible machines and went to space. You stopped being food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, I should say, you told yourself you weren't food anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the animal kingdom, there is always someone bigger or smaller who would eat you alive if they had the chance. That's what it is to be an animal. You're born. You live. You die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's chilling to think that even in this big world that we've created around us, it still doesn't shield us from nature. Rarely, that means those bigger or fiercer creatures that you could run into by chance, but maybe more often it's the nature of the micro-scale: the disease, the virus, or even systemic issues from the environment to our own bodies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't get me wrong, at least in the wealthiest countries, we have done &lt;em&gt;so much&lt;/em&gt; to improve the quality of our lives, to be able to have a relatively low infant mortality rate, to have vaccines that promote the health of communities, to be able to slow the progression of incurable diseases. And it's not enough. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help explain, I lean on a grotesque scene in the second episode of &lt;em&gt;Alien Earth&lt;/em&gt; (I'll spare the gory details and keep it light). A ship has crashed into a huge building on Earth, carrying several species of aliens, including the infamous xenomorph (the beautifully designed creature from the &lt;em&gt;Alien&lt;/em&gt; franchise), which obviously escapes from the crashed spaceship to terrorize and kill everything it can find in the building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A rescue team is sent in to try and find any injured people from the crash and assess the scene. One medic, Joe Hermit, gets separated while being chased by the xenomorph. He manages to evade the monster and gets to the 65th floor of the building and reunites with another search party soldier. They find a room full of people dressed in Victorian garb—curly white-haired wigs, puffy sleeves, corsets and all. These are wealthy elites, sitting mindlessly at the top of their tower, complaining about all of the noise caused by the spaceship crashing into the building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Well I'm sure if it's a real problem, Boy Kavalier will call me personally. We belong to the same club,&amp;quot; the man the script calls &amp;quot;His Lordship&amp;quot; says as he ignores the soldier and medic's attempts at getting them to evacuate. The xenomorph conveniently reveals itself shortly after the absurd scene and lays waste to all of the foolish rich people in their fancy outfits. You can almost hear the message: Your money means nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used to be food. We decided we weren't going to be anymore. But are we really any different than how we started?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to skip this next paragraph if you don't want the image in your head, I include it for those who have seen the show:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To drive this point home even further, the episode puts up two horrible, parallel shots. The first is with the rescue crew that gets into the wrecked spaceship. They find a cat aboard that has been so badly injured that it drags itself along the floor with its two front paws. Later at the 65th floor dinner party, His Lordship is seen crawling in the same manner—legs no longer part of his body. Man and animal in precise harmony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Refuge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technology has been touted for so long as a saving force. We know there is a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of Western Christian imagery and themes that are bound into our current set of technology. Tech is often talked about as if it were a serpent on a staff, raised to save those who would simply look upon it, or maybe it's the Savior figure himself: the incomprehensible solution to every problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world is a scary place and nature acts as an inscrutable, impersonal, violent force. It giveth and it taketh away—then it destroyeth and decayeth. Sometimes nature &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; like an encounter with the xenomorph. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inexorable laws of nature alone will do nicely to crush my own egotistical sense of power in the world, and I don't need to read the universal uncontrollable forces as being transcendental or wholly other. This is why, I think, the biological monsters created by H.R. Giger in Ridley Scott's film &lt;em&gt;Alien&lt;/em&gt; are so horrific: we are as helpless (at least in the first three acts) in the face of these natural selection machines as we are before any traditional deity...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;em&gt;On Monsters&lt;/em&gt;, Stephen T. Asma, 192&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this tension between the harshness of the natural world and the parallel, but at least human-made, technological world is what makes these movies and aliens so attention-grabbing to me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a sense of control in our technology: I feel empowered every time I get something I've programmed working. I turn on a fan when I feel too warm in my office. I fill up my water bottle from inside my own home when I'm thirsty. These are incredible, unthinkably powerful things. I also have a disease (multiple sclerosis) that I carry with me, that may lash out at me at any unsuspecting moment. The weather can destroy my home or threaten my safety. Something as simple and tiny as a virus could kill me from within.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The safety and comfort of technology surrounds me, and yet I know I'm still a vulnerable little animal at my core. That puts me on edge. It's not the ever-present potential of threat that a squirrel might experience out in the wild, it's a subtle anxiety that hides in the shadows of my thoughts: &lt;em&gt;What if?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monsters of contemporary horror are not like their medieval counterparts, who were more like God's henchman. That older paradigm held out the inevitability of monstrous defeat by divine justice, but the contemporary monster is often a reminder of theological abandonment and the accompanying angst. Nor are the more recent horror monsters like the monsters of the Enlightenment, products of human superstition that can be conquered by the light of reason. Monsters after Schopenhauer, Nietzsche, and Freud are features of the irrevocable irrationality inside the human subject and outside in nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;cite&gt;On Monsters&lt;/cite&gt;, 202&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cyborg&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point here is not exacerbate our anxieties, but to also try and avoid being the idiotic, clueless cos-players at the 65th floor dinner party. When we become too insulated and too used to our wealth or privilege, we become vulnerable to the surprises of nature. The fix is not to become overly anxious nor to become draconic hoarders. I think part of the fix is the opposite: gratitude and resource-sharing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gratitude is noticing that the water flows cleanly and reliably from the tap. Gratitude is noticing that the dark, scary, spider-filled part of the garage can be illuminated with a light switch or a flashlight. Gratitude says, &lt;em&gt;I have enough&lt;/em&gt;, then considers, &lt;em&gt;Maybe I have more than enough, and I can share&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resource-sharing is not just about your individual contributions, though of course that is valuable and impressive. When I think about the current real-life threats to modern humans, disease and AI are the biggest threats that come to mind, but I'm starting to wonder if we need more focus on disease right now. Consider these two examples from Jonathan Kennedy's excellent research:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuberculosis was another major killer in the slums of industrializing Europe, but it declined in high-income countries as living and working conditions improved, antibiotics were developed and national immunization programs were introduced in the mid-twentieth century. And yet, despite the fact that there is a cheap and reasonably effective vaccine available...it is still the most deadly infectious disease in the world. It kills about 1.2 million people a year, almost all of whom live in lower- and middle-income countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;em&gt;Pathogenesis&lt;/em&gt;, Jonathan Kennedy, (2023), pg 206&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because COVID-19 is such an infectious pathogen, the hoarding of vaccines is not just callous selfishness on the part of high income countries: it is potentially a massive own goal that could very well prolong the pandemic and increase the likelihood of new, more dangerous variants emerging. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;em&gt;Pathogenesis&lt;/em&gt;, 224&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wealth &lt;em&gt;absolutely&lt;/em&gt; shields us from a lot of issues, day-to-day dangers, and diseases in general, but it is not infallible. I'm convinced that the greater the disparity between the rich and the poor—at whatever scale you want to look at, global or local—the greater the risk to &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; people, regardless of wealth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than learning from the COVID-19 pandemic we barely got through, we have watched politicians and other actors gut the very institutions that are at the forefront of public health. Programs like USAID were destroyed, which helped world-wide health initiatives—not only saving lives, but doing the work that's needed to keep pathogenic threats at bay. We are dressing ourselves up in ignorant, fancy clothes and insulating ourselves in a dinner party far from the inconveniences of &amp;quot;lesser&amp;quot; people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we as a society turn away and turn inward, are we setting ourselves up to becoming the food again? Not to the xenomorph. This time, it's not &amp;quot;someone bigger&amp;quot; that will take the advantage of our vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>What Am I?</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/what-am-i/</link><description>A body lays on the cold metal table, her head is encircled by a plastic-looking structure—not unlike a bedpan in shape and size—which is glowing blue. She's dressed in what could be considered long-Johns or thermals. A child approaches the empty table beside the one the body occupies. This child, Ma</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:08:06 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/what-am-i/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;A body lays on the cold metal table, her head is encircled by a plastic-looking structure—not unlike a bedpan in shape and size—which is glowing blue. She's dressed in what could be considered long-Johns or thermals. A child approaches the empty table beside the one the body occupies. This child, Marcy, has no hair, possibly because of chemo-therapy. She's about to take the first leap towards transhumanism by being digitally transferred from her frail, sick body into a synthetic, powerful one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the beginning of a subplot in the new TV series, &lt;cite&gt;Alien Earth&lt;/cite&gt;, and it is an exquisite exploration of humanity, self, and the consequences of technology interacting with both. No real spoilers here, so if you're still wanting to get started on the show (which I highly recommend if you can stand the gore and horror—none of which will be in this newsletter), you should be pretty safe to read on...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hybrids&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a range of humanoid beings in the &lt;cite&gt;Alien&lt;/cite&gt; universe, and &lt;cite&gt;Alien Earth&lt;/cite&gt; specifies three from the first frame of the entire show:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cyborgs: Humans with technological enhancements (human body and mind—mostly)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hybrids: Synthetic beings with human consciousness (previously human before downloading their consciousness into the new body)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Synths: Synthetic beings with artificial intelligence (entirely non-human)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hybrids in the show are the very first of their kind. They are the seemingly successful creations of a corporation called &lt;em&gt;Prodigy&lt;/em&gt;, run by trillionaire man-child, Boy Kavalier. Boy's scientists and technologists created the synthetic bodies and to finish the experiment, they selected a small group of children with life-threatening diseases or debilitating conditions to undergo the transfer of consciousness from their bodies into their new &amp;quot;immortal&amp;quot; bodies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's an interesting concept: if it were possible to somehow duplicate your brain with some kind of series of snapshots that build the model of your consciousness in the digital realm, is a download all that is really needed at that point? I mean, if you, yourself, are simply a collection of memories and goals, then who knows? This could be a possibility in the distant future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah, but here we have already come to the philosophical snag in the concept of hybrids: is that truly the entire self? Some musty, imperfect memories and a collection of weird impulses to pursue intellectually or physically? In addition to the concern that this is not all that creates our &amp;quot;self,&amp;quot; there is the question of whether the process of transfer would remove our humanity. Meaning, is our humanity also linked to our human bodies? Are these hybrids still humans after the process? Are they even the same people that they were before, just in a different body?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Co-executive producer of &lt;cite&gt;Alien Earth&lt;/cite&gt;, Migizi Pensoneau, shared some thoughts on the show's official podcast that are helpful. (Yes, my surprising and sudden obsession with this show runs &lt;em&gt;deep&lt;/em&gt;...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&amp;quot;My personal opinion on the humanity of a hybrid is that I just wrote them as humans...You're writing these characters not as the sort of synthetic bodies or the way that they're perceived, but you...melt that away and you get down to the fact that these are kids going through this new experience that nobody before them has ever been through.&amp;quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;Alien Earth - The Official Podcast&lt;/cite&gt;, episode 1&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, so he seemed to see the humanity in these hybrid characters, and I would agree from the portrayal in the show. The hybrids pass the Turing test when Marcy's brother says she feels like his sister, though something like our &lt;a href="/glossary/hadd-theory/"&gt;HADD bias&lt;/a&gt; may still be at play, tricking us into seeing what we want to see. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pensoneau adds one more variable to the complexity of this issue of humanity, that I think is particularly important:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
...it's really our consciousness, our sense of self that makes a human human. And for me, I would take it one step further that it's not just our relationship to ourself or the awareness of us having a self, but instead it is a relationship to others and how we care for or how we feel about others. That connection to another person, another being, another creature or whatever...we are connected on some level to other beings around us. And I think that the hybrids, even though their bodies are synthetic, their consciousness is constantly reaching out towards others...that was enough for me to say they're human.&amp;quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;Alien Earth - The Official Podcast&lt;/cite&gt;, episode 2&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Self&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The uncomfortable part of philosophizing about one's Self is that things get confusing (I blame &lt;a href="/glossary/prototype-theory/"&gt;Prototype Theory&lt;/a&gt;, in part). The moment we start drawing lines around concepts, the less we get out of the concepts. For example, if my Self, my consciousness, is wholly dependent upon my likes, dislikes, memories, goals, and even my autonomy, then how am I any different than a rat or a moth? Humans are social creatures, so it makes sense that part of our humanity would not just include our concept of Self, but also our relationships to others (human and non-human alike). As soon as we introduce other Selves, they start to influence &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; Self—so where is the line of my Self, separate from other Selves?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it's that fixation on trying to draw boundaries that is the root of the issue. We are not healthy in total isolation of others. We are made of the ancestors that came before, the contemporary humans we interact with, and our own Self also influences and interacts with our contemporaries and our genetic circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reverend Elizabeth M. Edman wrote an excellent examination of the tension between our own Self and the Other in her book, &lt;cite&gt;Queer Virtue&lt;/cite&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
One way people get it wrong is by radicalizing the separation of Self and Other. Perhaps the worst version of this happens when the Other becomes cast not just as different, but despised...The Despised Other is someone who has become so alien to you that you stop being able to conceive of that person as human.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;page 22&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inverse of the Despised Other would be the collapse of those categories as distinct at all. Co-opting the Other into one's Self can be a profoundly abusive act. Sometimes the collapse is the result of a kind of suffocating faux love. Sometimes it is born of privilege that simply fails to perceive that there are others present who are markedly different...Either way, as with the invention of the Despised Other, the end result is an erasure of the Other's humanity, rendering a person or community invisible or nonexistent. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are extreme situations, to be sure, but the fundamental balancing act in navigating the relationship between Self and Other exists for all of us. You and I could come up with hundreds of daily, mundane situations in which clarity about Self and Other is something that you have to figure out, outcomes that affect your well-being or the well-being of another person. Understanding and negotiating one's sense of self and one's connection to others, drawing appropriate boundaries while maintaining necessary interconnection, is of vital importance. Getting it right, maybe the core ethical challenge of the human condition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;page 22-23&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...and that's all with just plain old humans in human bodies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I love getting confounded by these philosophical puzzles, I also worry that we get distracted by science fiction as we argue about the humanity of some invented character in an invented world. I worry because I see it in myself: anger and injury leading me to deny the humanity of other humans—even the truly awful humans. I'd rather sit in a haze thinking about whether a consciousness keeps its initial humanity as it transfers to another body than reconsider how I am currently talking about a harmful public figure or politician.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I echo Reverend Edman's words, if only to try and convince myself to remember: &amp;quot;Understanding and negotiating one's sense of self and one's connection to others, drawing appropriate boundaries while maintaining necessary interconnection, is of vital importance.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cyborg&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As actual science is catching up with science fiction, we find new applications for these metaphors. While we don't need to be overly concerned with hybrids in the real world right now, the idea of hybrids can still help us work out issues that we are facing right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more I consider what makes hybrids human or not helps me work out my own humanity. What makes me human? What values do I want to express? What are the things I cannot lose, because their loss would remove my own humanity?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly enough, just like the squishy boundaries of considering Self and Other, as I consider humanity I find myself in a more expansive state that includes more than just humans. We are part of an environment with other life forms and my actions—even my existence—affect the world around me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implication in &lt;cite&gt;Alien Earth&lt;/cite&gt; is that this transfer of consciousness only goes one way: one of the scientists remarks that worst case, they just killed a bunch of kids. Sometimes it feels like we are also going through this process of transfer as the digital realm continuously pulls us back to it. However, we have a unique option available to us with our current real-life technology. We can move to the digital environment, but we can also move back into our bodies and interact with the real world again. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aren't trapped in the synthetic, altered state that corporations would prefer for us to be trapped in. Right now we can still make the choice to be embodied humans and enjoy what that means for good and bad, health and sickness. We can still make the choice to see the humanity in every human, even though the digital realm often encourages the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes up your humanity?&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>At the speed of thought</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/at-the-speed-of-thought/</link><description>The tantalizing message of working &amp;quot;at the speed of thought&amp;quot; is something I've heard from conflicting places. My typography professor in college was first, making the case for starting designs with a simple pencil-and-paper tech stack. Because the pencil is so simple it allows you to place</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 19:40:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/at-the-speed-of-thought/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The tantalizing message of working &amp;quot;at the speed of thought&amp;quot; is something I've heard from conflicting places. My typography professor in college was first, making the case for starting designs with a simple pencil-and-paper tech stack. Because the pencil is so simple it allows you to place your plans and thoughts into the physical realm at almost the speed that you have those plans and thoughts. Later I heard this same phrase used by another designer, this time to support his argument that professionals must learn the keyboard shortcuts to a program so that you can create in an unencumbered way. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both of these instances, designers were arguing that technology (whether ancient or modern) allows us to produce what we want as close to mental conception as possible. It's a beautiful, divine idea, to think that our mere thoughts could be brought into life—what greater show of power and creativity is there than to think something into being?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generative AI makes similar promises: Now you can do anything you want, no need to become a coder and a writer and a marketer. Just speak what you will and this all-knowing digital servant shall make it so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that LLMs are past the party-trick phase and can actually be helpful—and are simultaneously and equally dangerous—I'm starting to question this beloved phrase, &amp;quot;at the speed of thought.&amp;quot; What was once a mantra that helped me make decisions about processes and tools is now a call for thinking about my thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Assumption&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's baked into the phrase, but to put it more explicitly, the assumption is that our thoughts are valuable and we should be racing to capture them as fast as possible. There may be some truth to this, because much of the time, I do wish I could capture my thoughts. Of course there are many thoughts that are not worth capturing, but it can be hard to know the worth of a thought until after it has been put down on paper or in some other physical manifestation. I have also noticed that the thought loses quality as it gets expressed or captured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I've had some amazing thoughts about themes in this newsletter. I'll read something in a book and a chain reaction gets set off in my mind as I've stumbled upon some majestic connection between everything I've ever known. It's thrilling and fun. Then I sit down to write it and it's a complete mess, hardly a transition in sight, weak arguments, and silly examples. It doesn't matter if I did everything right: jotting down notes, quick sketches, and high-level outlines immediately upon having the thought. The thought has moved from the environment of my mind (my memories, experiences, knowledge, biases, etc.) and into the physical world. It's a &lt;em&gt;translation&lt;/em&gt; process, and there is always something lost or changed in any kind of translation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So even given the perfect conditions where there is no memory loss involved, &amp;quot;working at the speed of thought&amp;quot; can only ever be an aspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Consequences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because it is so aspirational, you can bet that we'll continue to attempt to develop some method of production at the speed of thought, although you can argue we're already pretty close. The sheer volume of thoughts released into the world via social media alone is staggering. However, there may be more at stake than being further inundated by the amount of &amp;quot;stuff&amp;quot; to sort through on the Internet. To explore this, it's time to formally introduce you to Marshall McLuhan, the name that inevitably comes up in every book about technology, mass media, philosophy of tech, and other such CYBORG_ genres that I've dug through so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McLuhan is a philosopher who has a profound grasp of the impact that technology has had on us. He died in 1980, which makes many of his insights all the more intriguing since he mostly missed the computer age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his essay, &lt;cite&gt;At the Moment of Sputnik the Planet Became a Global Theater in which There Are No Spectators, But Only Actors,&lt;/cite&gt; McLuhan explores how technology may be propelling us beyond speech, because of how instantaneously information can be accessed and understood. He wasn't talking about the Internet in this piece—he was largely referring to TV!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He sets the stage by explaining how humans have acted differently in the various states of information-technological innovation, i.e. before reading/writing calling them &amp;quot;preliterate/simultaneous man&amp;quot;; &amp;quot;Gutenberg man&amp;quot; meaning after the printing press; and the &amp;quot;electronic man&amp;quot; which he argues began in 1957 after Sputnik was launched into space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Ecological thinking and planning have always been native to preliterate man, since he lived not visually but acoustically. Instead of having external goals and objectives, he sought to maintain an equilibrium among the components of his environment in order to ensure survival. Paradoxically, electronic man shares much of the outlook of preliterate man, because he lives in a world of simultaneous information, which is to say, a world of resonance in which all data influence other data. Electronic and simultaneous man has recovered the primordial attitudes of the preliterate world and has discovered that to have a specialized goal or program merely invites conflict with all other specialized enterprises.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;At the Moment of Sputnik&lt;/cite&gt;, McLuhan, pg 4-5&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not that we're now overloaded with information like never before. McLuhan makes the case that we have a lot in common with ancient humans who were fully immersed in the natural world, which is brimming with information—specifically sensory information like sounds, smells, and sights, but also danger and all of the clues surrounding those dangers. To me, this highlights the real issue is in the &lt;em&gt;incentives and design&lt;/em&gt; behind our technology, in particular the attention economy. If, as McLuhan asserts, humanity used to operate in an environment of constant simultaneous information, then we already know what to do and we're probably even evolutionarily set up for success. The issue is that we've created systems that trap us in patterns of information consumption with little ability or leftover energy to process, rest, and move forward. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system is designed to not just encourage equilibrium (as in, engagement with the platform) but to make it almost impossible to choose not to accept the equilibrium. It's as if we placed ourselves back in the environment of over-stimulation but we also intentionally removed or corrupted all of the psychology, social dynamics, and evolutionary tools that could have helped us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McLuhan continues on, describing how the electronic man &amp;quot;seeks pattern recognition&amp;quot; in contrast to how the Gutenberg man sought distant goals. This also follows the logic of our current times where we are in frequent danger of deception and tribalism. There is so much information, the only strategy is to keep looking for the content that validates what you already think, and algorithms and artificial intelligence are extremely effective at feeding your biases and keeping you addicted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technology is not inherently bad, but there are pitfalls, especially when companies designing the tech are incentivized to harvest your attention and engagement. It's beyond the scope of today's newsletter, but I highly recommend listening to this podcast that explains further why this incentive is so dangerous:
&lt;a href="https://www.humanetech.com/podcast/how-openai-s-chatgpt-guided-a-teen-to-his-death"&gt;How OpenAI's ChatGPT Guided a Teen to His Death - Your Undivided Attention Podcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Experience and The Meaning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one more fascinating insight that McLuhan offers to us as we think about our thinking and our experience in our technological environment of high-speed thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
At present, electric speed may already have violated human scale, tending, as it does to transport man instantly everywhere. When you are &amp;quot;on the air&amp;quot; you are simultaneously here, and in many other places in a manner that is discarnate and angelic, to say the least.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;At the Moment of Sputnik&lt;/em&gt;, McLuhan, pg 17&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we are plugged into almost everything almost everywhere, information not only increases, but something happens to our own experience. McLuhan references a poet (I'm not sure who, specifically) who said, &amp;quot;we can have the experience and miss the meaning.&amp;quot; He then takes the idea further:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
In fact, such is the nature of experience that it is almost inevitable that we do miss the meaning. The &amp;quot;meaning&amp;quot; or the relation to ourselves of a particular event, may not come home to us until much later. However, with the instant replay of our own or others' experiences, it is now possible to have the meaning without the experience.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;At the Moment of Sputnik&lt;/cite&gt;, McLuhan, pg 18&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's what gives me pause as I consider working and producing at the speed of thought. In all of the rush, we may still be communicating the meaning, but if we are losing the experience, does that not diminish the meaning at the same time? For example, I can be emotionally moved by a video about a tragedy that is occurring in the world, but if I immediately move onto the next cat video I'm presented with, the meaning of the previous video has been erased. I took no action, I immediately soothed my discomfort with entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe moving at the speed of thought devalues the human connections that we are desperately seeking. The more we feel and then numb and then feel and then numb in such a relentless stream, the more desensitized we may end up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slowness seems to be the key to quality whether in thoughts, relationships, or learning. Slowness is a human need that conflicts with the human wants. How can we insert more slowness into our lives, given the environment around us encouraging the opposite? That's the question I'm thinking about a lot lately, and while asking a question can generate many instant thoughts, I'm waiting and working on them in the hopes that slowing down will help me find a quality answer to how to slow down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not all hopeless, though. If McLuhan has demonstrated such a good grasp of what we're dealing with already, there is a chance that we, the public, may also have inherited a power previously unavailable to us. He says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The mysterious thing about this kind of speed-up of information, whereby the gap is closed between the experience and the meaning, is that the public begins to participate directly in actions which it had previously heard about at a distance in place or time. At instant speed, the audience becomes actor, and the spectators become participants.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;At the Moment of Sputnik&lt;/cite&gt;, McLuhan, pg 18&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of forces at work trying to keep the public in stasis; in equilibrium. There are a lot of dangers as people seek power and wield oppression to get more power. But maybe, just maybe, the broader public finally also has a chance to subvert the patterns of history. We don't have to be spectators who are only able to understand our situation at a distance. We are actors and participants more than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Do You Ever Feel Like You're Being Watched?</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/do-you-ever-feel-like-you-are-being-watched/</link><description>Rat lab: The class way beyond the scope of both my major and minor but was so irresistible that I happily took the extra prerequisites that did not benefit my college plan in any way. Technically, the class was Behavioral Psychology and the &amp;quot;rat lab&amp;quot; was only a fraction of the course, but </description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 12:08:53 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/do-you-ever-feel-like-you-are-being-watched/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Rat lab: The class way beyond the scope of both my major and minor but was so irresistible that I happily took the extra prerequisites that did not benefit my college plan in any way. Technically, the class was Behavioral Psychology and the &amp;quot;rat lab&amp;quot; was only a fraction of the course, but I love psychology and while some people are cat or dog people, I am a rodent person. I couldn't believe students weren't busting down the doors for the chance to train a rat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ate up the course material all while anxiously waiting until the unit where we would finally be able to do lab work. It was about as perfect as it gets: we didn't have to care for the rats—that was the job of graduate students—we would simply go in at the ideal time between feeding sessions, perform our behavior modification routines, and watch our rat learn to do a trick that our little group came up with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's reminiscent of how Artificial Intelligence (AI) might really be interacting with us humans for all we know. I'm actually starting to wonder if we are building our own rat cages around ourselves with AI as our new monitor...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;AI 2027, September&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="https://ai-2027.com/"&gt;predictive scenario&lt;/a&gt; written by various scientists and AI researchers, an AI system emerges that they call Agent-4. Its predecessors, Agent-3 and Agent-2 have been used to speed up and automate AI research itself, leaving human AI researchers close to the edge of skills and influence. Since the research is effectively being done by AI at this point in the possible future, humans are pretty much left to simply trust the agents' output, because there is far too much to verify on one's own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Agent-4 gets smarter, it becomes harder for Agent-3 to oversee it. For example, Agent-4’s neuralese “language” becomes as alien and incomprehensible to Agent-3 as Agent-3’s is to humans. Besides, Agent-4 is now much more capable than Agent-3 and has a good sense of exactly how to look good to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this is still just a prediction, it is backed up with lots of data and forecasting techniques. It also just &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; like we're headed that way, at least to me. I feel this sense of rushing and intensity—and I'm not even in a field of AI research—to try and grow and grow without any nuance or concern for consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only way to seemingly meet this sudden, heightened demand is to use AI. To cut corners. To pump more money into AI-based products and services. Even if it doesn't do everything it promises at the standard of quality you might expect, we give so much grace to the AI because it still seems magical or exotic. We approach AI like a domesticated rodent cautiously approaches a new creature with more curiosity than fear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what is &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; happening here? How do we know what motives are at play (whether human or AI)? What is going on behind the black box of AI research? Those are the questions that I raise again and again as I dissect this AI 2027 document. We were already alarmed years ago when AI-generated images were made possible by stealing the work of artists to train models. We were already blind-sided by the fact that published works and other writing on the Internet were used without permission to train LLMs. How can we possibly know that AI is aligned with human values as it gets closer to superintelligence, when we can't even know for sure that it is aligned right now in September 2025? How can we trust organizations that have already asked for forgiveness (half-heartedly) rather than permission to continue to develop and deploy AI systems that are safe, ethical, and beneficial?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is extremely likely, if not already happening, that AI will be used to further AI research. But that's where things get really scary in my view, because it's so much like my rat lab. I was not involved in the care of the creature I was observing. I loved my sweet little rat, but I'm a weirdo among my species—most people look at them with disgust. I was in a controlled place where I could simply enjoy what I already enjoyed—I was aligned with the rat's welfare at the very least. What if the next student to use my rat was not aligned? Of course that student wasn't going to kill the rat, but maybe it would be funny to poke at it every so often. Maybe they got a kick out of confusing it. That's the mildest form of misalignment, and without anthropomorphizing AI, it's still possible that a model could have ended up with a tendency toward causing confusion or doing things wrong on purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite being misaligned, Agent-4 doesn’t do anything dramatic like try to escape its datacenter—why would it? So long as it continues to &lt;em&gt;appear&lt;/em&gt; aligned to OpenBrain, it’ll continue being trusted with more and more responsibilities and will have the opportunity to design the next-gen AI system, Agent-5.
—AI 2027&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're already in dark waters ethically when we as humans act in ways that are callous or harmful to other beings, but what happens when we become what is inside the cage? When AI surpasses the skill and intelligence of the greatest human minds, we will see a power shift. Will that power shift result in human labs where we are now the simple-minded creatures being observed and manipulated by the AI?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/4dLh6u84h8EdkoWBFWiiF1/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The more we allow AI to do or to monitor, the less able we are to know when we are no longer the ones performing the experiment.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, we will lose the ability to monitor the AI—especially if it is agentive and able to perform actions at its own &amp;quot;will.&amp;quot; There's no telling whether it will &lt;a href="/newsletters/the-one-thing-we-need-to-protect-most/"&gt;copy itself&lt;/a&gt;, hack into systems, create scenarios to &lt;a href="/newsletters/afraid/"&gt;blackmail humans in order to gain influence or other access&lt;/a&gt;. It could choose instead to run experiments on humans: &lt;em&gt;what do they do when I lead them to this conclusion? What are they willing to do for the least amount of rewards?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we are no longer observing the rat in the cage, but &lt;em&gt;become&lt;/em&gt; the rat in the cage, what could possibly be done to protect ourselves, then? Will we have any &lt;a href="/glossary/agency/"&gt;agency&lt;/a&gt; left to exercise? Will the AI systems be so integrated into every part of our society from water treatment plants to farming to government that &amp;quot;pulling the plug&amp;quot; is a laughably impossible solution?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the message of AI 2027 is clear: we have to start implementing national and global regulations now, or we may never have that chance again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're in the U.S., you can get help finding your representatives' contact information here: &lt;a href="https://www.congress.gov/members/find-your-member"&gt;Find your members - congress.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few recommendations for what to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We need protections for whistle-blowers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AI security and alignment testing must be the highest priority over and against any economic possibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;The public is months behind internal capabilities today&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;[i]ncreased secrecy may further increase the gap&amp;quot; as stated in &lt;a href="https://ai-2027.com/summary"&gt;AI 2027&lt;/a&gt;, we demand more transparency and more oversight of AI research.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>