<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><title>CYBORG_ Newsletters</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/feed/</link><description>My latest articles</description><atom:link href="http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/feed/" rel="self"/><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2025 Not Defined LLC</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 11:40:24 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Are We Asking the Right Question?</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/are-we-asking-the-right-question/</link><description>When I was first diagnosed with Multiple Sclerosis (MS), it took almost 6 months for me to start to recover from my MS attack. During that time I became acquainted with a question that still looms over me: Where is the worth of a person?
That's the more finalized version of the question. It started </description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 11:40:24 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/are-we-asking-the-right-question/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;When I was first diagnosed with Multiple Sclerosis (MS), it took almost 6 months for me to start to recover from my MS attack. During that time I became acquainted with a question that still looms over me: Where is the worth of a person?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's the more finalized version of the question. It started out with a lot more judgment and ableism. My prior model of the world involved measuring my worth by my productivity and achievement. I was only worth as much as I could learn, do, and produce—and it wasn't enough just in comparison with myself, it was all about how much better I was in comparison with everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the MS attack took away my ability to think clearly, to move in a coordinated way, to do &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; that I was normally able to do, I could only see myself as worthless. The question I had was much more like, &lt;em&gt;When am I too worthless to be here?&lt;/em&gt; Eventually, however, I started challenging that first iteration of the question because it was harming me and I was desperate to find a better way—a healthier way—of thinking about my newfound condition. Many conversations with many people led me to adopt an assumption first, and then ask my question to see where it would go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assumption was: humans have inherent value. If that was true, then how can you have any worth if you can't do anything? I was still thinking in terms of ableism and productivity, but the question was at least pointed the other way: instead to trying to determine how you lose your value, I was searching for how (or whether) you &lt;em&gt;maintain&lt;/em&gt; value, even when you can no longer contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was where I landed for more than five years (and I still find myself falling back to this version of the question when times are tough). I get stuck on &amp;quot;contribution&amp;quot; as a function of value: the more you contribute, the more valuable you are. But that doesn't explain why people love and care for others who are extremely disabled; bedridden; paralyzed; even comatose. I felt like I had to understand the extreme cases to console myself and find human worth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, however, I noticed that my question was still flawed—influenced by a system that does not prioritize our humanity, but attempts to suppress it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The AI Question&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've seen so many headlines and assumptions that say that Artificial Intelligence (AI) challenges what it means to be human. There has been unprecedented progress in generative AI's abilities to produce good work. We, somewhat collectively, do feel the threat of replacement looming as tech bros proclaim that AI will replace the majority of knowledge workers in just a few years. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But is AI &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; challenging what it means to be &lt;em&gt;human&lt;/em&gt;? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I readily admit that I tend to be contrarian—highly suspicious of collective &amp;quot;wisdom&amp;quot; or conclusions that are shared on viral videos or memes. So when I see that the assumption behind this question put forth by journalists and creators, is that humanity is as simple as our productivity at work, I start to wonder if we've got the wrong question in our minds. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like my journey with MS and my struggle to understand my worth, I got stuck on a poor question. It did not propel me forward, it kept me confounded. The AI question and my second question are the same: is the worth of a human tied to their productivity?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That question puts us on a path that tries to insert humanity into that which is absent of humanity by nature. We've discussed HADD Theory before, and I still find it the most compelling theory to explain why we squabble about whether these chat bots are conscious—our brains are designed through evolution to notice and assign agency to things even if it's all imagined. I bring this up because I think that the question of AI consciousness is a dangerous distraction; a question that gets us stuck when there are real, pressing problems that should be addressed before we try and figure out if AI is alive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we get stuck on determining if AI is a kind of human, then we will be on the lookout for evidence. We will compare our humanity to what can be done on a computer. If AI can do it, and can sometimes do it better—then where does humanity fit? The question is faulty, because, again, we're assuming that our productivity is what makes us human; what makes us valuable. AI replaces human productivity, therefore, AI is worth the same or more than humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But our worth is not in our productivity. Our worth is not comparable to AI in any way; it is wholly independent of any form of AI, sentient or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cyborg&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have to be careful about the questions we ask, because they influence what we are able to uncover. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do recognize that the AI question is also one of practicality: if we get replaced by AI, how do we continue to provide for ourselves in our current system? If everyone gets laid off, then how do we support anything? How do we survive?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end of that question must be answered with policy and regulation. We must do something to protect laborers' (including knowledge workers') rights and remove power from the richest who are poised to exploit and profit the most. I don't know any other way right now to coexist with AI as a competitor in the workplace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, I think we also need to move onto the more important version of the question of human worth. Maybe the next economic and social systems can only be constructed by focusing on it. For now, at least, it is how I find progress amidst uncertainty, distress, and fear. To keep the question in mind, &amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt; does my value come from?&amp;quot; forces me to accept the assumption that I do have value. Divorced from productivity or skill or achievement or status or money or possessions or any other thing, there is only one explanation for where the worth comes from:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I exist.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Art of Revelation</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-art-of-revelation/</link><description>For the last year, the ghost of a prior failure haunted me every time I went into my garage. This particular phantom was a canvas that I had messed up while painting. It had a beautifully blended rainbow background, starting at the top with a deep crimson, melding into orange and yellow, then somewh</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 11:53:14 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-art-of-revelation/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;For the last year, the ghost of a prior failure haunted me every time I went into my garage. This particular phantom was a canvas that I had messed up while painting. It had a beautifully blended rainbow background, starting at the top with a deep crimson, melding into orange and yellow, then somewhat sharply changing to green, then blue, and a hint of indigo at the bottom. The idea was to depict a sunset over water, so that my Pride-flag colors could be projected onto a somewhat natural scene. The only flaw was that the transition to the &amp;quot;water&amp;quot; surface got a little too abrupt with a few misplaced strokes of green that were too high to make it appear intentional, and too dark to hide under another coat of yellow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally fed up with its taunts, I grabbed my paints, determined to try again. I had a ruined canvas before me, but the original image and composition still interested me, so I turned it into an experiment to see if it could work in a different style: instead of a perfectly smooth gradient, I opted for something messy and chaotic. I layered on the paint, rebuilding scene on top of the previous one, but this time I didn't care about perfection. I wasn't painting—I was playing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In perfect irony, the final image was much more visually appealing—even with the exact same issue that it had before: small green splashes of paint on top of the fragile yellow area. I had gotten carried away with my palette knife, just like I had with my brush last year. This time around, however, this doesn't bother me—it's not trying to be photo-realistic, it's trying to say something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/kuzuAb7cmMtQMAWEowryhp/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The initial sketch for the painting on the top left and the redone, full canvas on the right.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wu Wei&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;cite&gt;Dao De Jing&lt;/cite&gt;, this phrase &lt;em&gt;wu wei&lt;/em&gt; comes up a lot. It describes a concept of non-coercive action. It's about flowing instead of forcing. While I'm not going to do justice in explaining (or even understanding) this Taoist concept, what I have learned in trying to wrap my Western mind around it has been insightful and widely applicable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first iteration of my painting process was mostly me trying to force something. When I made a big mistake, it was unrecoverable. I had built a fragile system—a collection of decisions that could not adapt to variability. So when I prepared to try again, I tried tricking my brain into letting go by treating my canvas as if it were another being that I was going to interact with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can animate the painting (i.e. treat it as if alive) and imagine that it has a will of its own, and our job as artist is to &lt;em&gt;reveal&lt;/em&gt; that painting: listen to it, pull it out. I think that's an intuitive way that many artists like to think of their work, especially &lt;a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/elizabeth_gilbert_your_elusive_creative_genius"&gt;after the Renaissance&lt;/a&gt; shifted the pressure to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; the genius rather than to &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; a genius. It's much easier on your mental state if you can separate yourself from what you produce. Otherwise, you may get too deep into judgment or worry more about unachievable standards than making the art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second iteration of my painting had the intention of losing myself in the process: I wanted the painting to reveal itself to me through &lt;em&gt;wu wei&lt;/em&gt;—flow—making decisions based on what was presented to me, rather than playing god and forcing it to do what I want even when it doesn't work. This method was more enjoyable because the stakes were removed. I wasn't trying to prove how technically skilled I was. I was watching the painting take shape over time and reacting to what I saw. I still had a basic composition in mind, but it was not about copying my imagination directly onto canvas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam Savage, one of the hosts of the hit series &lt;cite&gt;MythBusters&lt;/cite&gt; (2003–2016), had a similar experience on his YouTube channel, &lt;cite&gt;Tested&lt;/cite&gt;. He was &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Log-43c9oo8&amp;amp;pp=ygUgYWRhbSBzYXZhZ2UgdGVzdGVkIGRpbm9zYXVyIGVwIDQ%3D"&gt;building a life-size &amp;quot;velociraptor&amp;quot; puppet&lt;/a&gt;, similar to what you'd see on &lt;cite&gt;Jurassic Park&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;q&gt;There's a moment in which the object tells you what it's going to be,&lt;/q&gt; he remarked. He had been set on creating a green-toned skin for his dinosaur model, but as he worked with it, he ended up changing the entire color scheme to a more sandy/desert style, and I personally thought it was the perfect choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my mind, this is &lt;em&gt;wu wei&lt;/em&gt;. It's a collaboration between material and artist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rawhide Drum Making&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took a community class last year that promised a rawhide drum that we would make and learn to play. It was quite simplified and most of the difficult work was done outside of the class by the material suppliers (all from Indigenous-owned businesses). We had wood frames already made and even the rawhide had been dyed and processed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though we were really just &lt;em&gt;assembling&lt;/em&gt; the drum, rather than making one from scratch, there was still a part of the process that tapped into this &lt;em&gt;wu wei&lt;/em&gt; concept. The instructor showed us how to take our pre-soaked rawhides and pull them taught around the wood frames. It was a lot of pulling and folding and manipulating the hide, trying to coax it to conform to the circular shape without too many creases or bumps. Then we added the rawhide strings to the back to keep the tension and create the handle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/eTeK6CU7kv65ta7zYxhqSv/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Back of the drum, showing nine tensioning strings with two wrapped together to form a handle to grasp.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;q&gt;The animal will tell you about itself,&lt;/q&gt; my instructor said as she wandered through the desks. &lt;q&gt;You can have an idea of what it will be, but ultimately, you have to work with the deer to let it show you what it will become.&lt;/q&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the best part of the class: getting yet another culture's perspective of this &lt;em&gt;wu wei&lt;/em&gt; concept. The hide of the deer told me a story: it has scars and bumps and spots that showed through the dye. In a way, the animal still had some say in its transformation from hide to drum. It didn't matter how hard I pulled, there were parts that would not lie perfectly flat or curve the way I wanted. After stringing and tensioning the back, I discovered that the hide had a natural hole on the edge (as opposed to the pre-punched holes from processing), meaning I had nine lines instead of the expected eight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sound of each drum would also be unique, and change over time as the hide settled on the drum and dried. &lt;q&gt;Get to know your drum,&lt;/q&gt; became the instructor's refrain across each class session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, the final product was a collaboration, not a domination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/ke4ebxYD8Wo33nvwJr5Aer/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Front of the rawhide drum showing the scars that the deer had acquired during its life (all of the thin lines and some of the small dots are scars).
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cyborg&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this may seem to be art-focused, I believe that &lt;em&gt;wu wei&lt;/em&gt; is widely applicable and useful in our lives. Perhaps art is just a training tool to help us practice recognizing the paths set before us and then taking the opportunity to follow where they lead. Not to be confused with &lt;em&gt;inaction&lt;/em&gt;, non-coercive action is an attempt to work with what we have and to honor the agency or the dignity of other creatures and things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a modern context, we might be tempted to see things like a social media feed as following a path—after all, it is constantly providing you with things that are easily followed. This is &lt;em&gt;inaction&lt;/em&gt;, however, because you are not collaborating. Your agency and your &amp;quot;self&amp;quot; are being rushed through a river that is designed to trap you in it. You are the material and the company is the artist that asserts its dominance over you. &lt;em&gt;You will like this content, you will be distracted, you will be harvested for our gain without your true consent.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all technology &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be this way. &lt;em&gt;Wu wei&lt;/em&gt; is difficult when our agency is not entirely our own, but it can be practiced, and it can be brought into your circumstance through intention. I believe this helps us flip back into a more agentive role, where we can become actors in our lives again, rather than objects ready to be turned into profits by other agents who do not respect &lt;em&gt;wu wei&lt;/em&gt; or the humanity of others. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think &lt;em&gt;wu wei&lt;/em&gt; can help us work with others in a non-destructive way. How else can we achieve something within a collection of other agents? When we respect the agency of other people, and even other animals or objects, we allow the art of revelation to work towards a positive outcome. We can still have our own ideas, but we allow each participant to reveal themselves in the process. We will never end up with what a single individual imagined, but that is not a loss; it's an improvement. There are better times ahead when we adapt, update, and move collaboratively. Anything else is ultimately destructive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While splitting up the world in making distinctions within it might seem to have a functional value, it always entails a diminution. The most effective way of cultivating order in the world, invariably relies upon the power of inclusivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—From the Commentary on Chapter 28 of &lt;cite&gt;Dao De Jing&lt;/cite&gt;, Translated by Roger Ames &amp;amp; David L. Hall&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Snippets of Humanity</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/snippets-of-humanity/</link><description>I recently took a break from studying technology and the academic theory/philosophy on humanity. Instead, I travelled to an LGBTQIA+ conference to try and explore humanity &amp;quot;in real life&amp;quot; (something that's tough to do for an introvert like myself). I came away with some important themes tha</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 11:54:35 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/snippets-of-humanity/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I recently took a break from studying technology and the academic theory/philosophy on humanity. Instead, I travelled to an LGBTQIA+ conference to try and explore humanity &amp;quot;in real life&amp;quot; (something that's tough to do for an introvert like myself). I came away with some important themes that I think anyone, regardless of identity, can benefit from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Remember Who You Are&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Far from a trite aphorism, this concept seemed to permeate through the speakers and breakout sessions. Particularly in the sense of relationships with others, it's vital to remember who you are, and that you matter. I'm not even close to good at this, as I tend to yield to others' needs or wants, diminish my contribution to conversation, and assume that I don't matter even while affirming that everyone else absolutely does matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps that's why this idea seemed to stick out to me, but here are a couple of snippets that I heard:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In response to the question of how to approach someone whose values conflict with yours: Values are different than personhood. If they want to deny you your personhood, that's not a value-based conflict. Remember who you are: you deserve dignity, respect. Removing those things from a person has nothing to do with &amp;quot;values&amp;quot; and everything to do with dehumanizing you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the &amp;quot;yielders&amp;quot;: Dare to say what's on your mind and reveal yourself. That's how you get stronger. Remember that who you are matters; your perspective; your needs; all of you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes it's hard to maintain your sense of self in a relationship. The struggle is remembering: who am I and who are you in our relationship? Failing to remember who you are, even in a very close relationship, like with a spouse, can become unhealthy and ultimately betrays both you and the relationship. (Please speak to a mental health professional to explore more about any of this—not a therapist, here, just a curious writer!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;We Are Starved For Love&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lesbian bishop was part of a conversation for one of the sessions. She mentioned that she noticed throughout her ministry that people are starved for love—everyone, not just marginalized groups. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;q&gt;We are so miserly with our love,&lt;/q&gt; she emphasized. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My tech-sense is tingling, and I wonder how we might find a better balance between our personal relationships and the strange new &amp;quot;tribes&amp;quot; that social media has caused to emerge. Note that I'm using the word &amp;quot;tribe&amp;quot; sarcastically, since that's a term ill-suited for these bizarre identity-based political groups, even though that's how you see it used across the Internet. In fact, I wonder if these false tribes have contributed to the collapse of our in-person relationships and have caused us to hoard our love, preventing it from leaking out to real people in real life. In fact, Dr. Lisa Diamond mentioned this in reference to non-human forms of safety-signaling:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;q&gt;Our brains evolved to get our safety from actual people.&lt;/q&gt; Not signs or flags (or, I would add, AI). You can make your life safer with just one or two connections. This is an act of resistance—the world wants you divided and isolated. Instead, increasing our in-person time with people we are safe to be ourselves with will help us reverse many of the negative effects we're seeing from our isolation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are all starved for love, so let's try to stop hoarding it and instead share it with the people in our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Trust That I Know Myself&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the under-represented groups within the LGBTQIA+ community are the asexual (often shortened to &amp;quot;Ace&amp;quot;) and aromantic (&amp;quot;Aro&amp;quot;) groups. People who identify as Ace don't experience sexual attraction, and those who identify as Aro don't experience romantic attraction. This isn't a tragedy, this isn't a problem to be fixed. This is yet another example of the beautiful diversity of human experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presenter who spoke from this group happened to be both Ace and Aro (somewhat rare). Her remarks had a consistent theme: don't invalidate someone's identity. She has been constantly peppered with questions like, are you sure? Have you just not met the right person? Or receiving comments like, &lt;q&gt;that's so sad I could never imagine not loving someone.&lt;/q&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;q&gt;People don't see my identity as real or valid,&lt;/q&gt; she summarized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking about how a person can have a vastly different experience than my own, it reminds me of how Ed Yong helped readers of his book, &lt;cite&gt;An Immense World&lt;/cite&gt;, get used to the idea of understanding the experience of other animal species:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our umwelt is still limited, it just doesn't &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; that way. To us, it feels all-encompassing. It is all that we know, and so we easily mistake it for all there is &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; know. This is an illusion—and one that every animal shares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;aside class="bracket"&gt;
NOTE: &lt;em&gt;umwelt&lt;/em&gt; is a term he uses to refer to the reality a creature inhabits based on its sensory perception—not just its environment, but how it understands and perceives it.
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only do we humans have a broad &lt;em&gt;umwelt&lt;/em&gt;, we also have our own personal &lt;em&gt;umwelts&lt;/em&gt;—based on our senses, our abilities, our experiences, and our identity. With such diversity just within our own species, we can't possibly &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt; someone else's experience, but that doesn't mean it isn't real. Our experience may seem complete, all-encompassing, and all there is to know, but that is truly an illusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's hard enough to &lt;q&gt;know thyself,&lt;/q&gt; how do we ever dare to tell other people who &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; are (or who we think they should be)? Trust that I know myself, and work to know &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; &amp;quot;self.&amp;quot; No need to steal that responsibility from someone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Human&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sat by myself in my introverted bubble for most of the conference, frequently weeping in silence. It's been quite the year of pain, isolation, and, most of all, feeling terrified that my neighbors might turn into persecutors. The rage and demonization expressed throughout the U.S. presidential campaign and new administration have set fire to my nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To take a break from that and sit in a room with 1,100 other queer people or allies was overwhelming. It was social safety, which, going back to Dr. Diamond again, is when you feel OK &lt;em&gt;as you are&lt;/em&gt; with other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew no one there personally, but tears immediately blinded me just by stepping inside a building where I knew I could be myself: introverted, queer, and everything else in between. There's something special about our humanity, and it's so easy to fade into the background of my day-to-day life. But this was a much-needed reminder that there are still humans out there. There is still community to be had. There is still dignity to be shared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You matter. I matter.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Shadow of Humanity</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-shadow-of-humanity/</link><description>&amp;quot;Dad!&amp;quot; I yell with exasperation. &amp;quot;Can you come take a look at this?&amp;quot;
Something spins on my computer screen, error codes displayed on a box. I click randomly to no avail, but suddenly the screen refreshes, the error is gone, and everything works perfectly. I spin around to find my</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 11:40:12 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-shadow-of-humanity/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Dad!&amp;quot; I yell with exasperation. &amp;quot;Can you come take a look at this?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something spins on my computer screen, error codes displayed on a box. I click randomly to no avail, but suddenly the screen refreshes, the error is gone, and everything works perfectly. I spin around to find my dad has entered the room. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Oh sure, now it's working! Just 'cause you're here,&amp;quot; I say. He chuckles and retreats the way he came. &lt;em&gt;Computers really like him,&lt;/em&gt; I think, as I continue on tinkering with whatever's on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moments later, I might get called down by my mom to help her with some computer issue, only to have the exact same thing happen—everything is broken until I come to look, then the computer decides to shape up and act as though nothing had happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe computers do enjoy the gaslighting, but long-time readers of CYBORG_ know that my personal stance on anthropomorphizing machines is a dangerous distraction, and probably has more to do with &lt;a href="/newsletters/the-problem-we-are-avoiding-with-ai/"&gt;our brain's evolution&lt;/a&gt; than these systems having an actual &amp;quot;being&amp;quot; or consciousness. However, there is something that happens when the fingerprints of humanity are left on our machines, and that might bring out some surprising behavior from the cold, stoic technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Shadows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know about you, but when I think about technology, I think of it in terms of stability, facts. It's unfeeling, unbiased, unemotional. It's something reliable. 1+1=2, no matter how many times you punch it into the calculator. If you get the wrong answer, it's because you, the human, messed up—garbage in, garbage out after all!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How is it, then, that we're seeing really good evidence that artificial intelligence has &lt;a href="https://hai.stanford.edu/news/covert-racism-ai-how-language-models-are-reinforcing-outdated-stereotypes"&gt;racial biases&lt;/a&gt;? &lt;a href="https://www.media.mit.edu/publications/full-gender-shades-thesis-17/"&gt;Gender biases&lt;/a&gt;? If AI really is just another tool, why is it falling for the same old fallacies, stereotypes, and prejudices that we humans have? Does this not demonstrate a kind of consciousness? Or maybe it means that the human creators were pulling the wrong levers—passing their personal biases onto their creation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think there is more to it than simply pointing at the creators and saying they just hard-coded some problematic stuff into it (not that they don't have serious responsibility for what they &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; done, bad intentions or not). I also do not think this is actually unique to AI alone. Potentially, these biases have accompanied our tech for far longer than we've realized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider this observation by Jun'ichirō Tanizaki:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Japanese music is, above all, a music of reticence, of atmosphere. When recorded or amplified...the greater part of its charm is lost...Most important of all are the pauses. Yet [the recordings] render these moments of silence utterly lifeless. And so we distort the arts themselves to curry favor for them with the machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a guess when this was written. 2000? 1990? Maybe 1970? Nope. He wrote this in his essay, &lt;cite&gt;In Praise of Shadows,&lt;/cite&gt; back in 1933. Even more profound were the musings on technology and culture. Tanizaki mourns the losses felt in Eastern culture as Western technology was invading: photography, radio, trolleys, airplanes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He notes that, left alone, the East may have continued to develop slowly—at their own pace—but that they &lt;q&gt;would have gone only in a direction that suited us.&lt;/q&gt; The technology would have been developed in support of their values, their complexions, their landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;q&gt;They would have been no borrowed gadgets, they would have been the tools of our own culture, suited to us.&lt;/q&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, this was a paradigm shift. Suddenly, I can see how technology is not some set-apart thing. It absolutely does have bias, opinion, stereotypes, built in. Not necessarily due to ill-intent or some grand attempt at large-scale oppression (though that's &lt;em&gt;entirely&lt;/em&gt; possible). But technology is inescapably linked to culture and the values of that culture will therefore permeate the tech for better or worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not because the technology is alive or conscious or self-aware. It is because technology is the shadow of humanity. We build it after our likeness, and it reflects that shaping back to us—recognizable if we decide to look at the shadow, but just as easily slipping into the environment as a subtle, unimposing thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shadows can create beauty as Tanizaki argues in his essay, but they can also hide dangers. Perhaps especially for Westerners, shadows are uncomfortable. Maybe we're afraid of seeing what we've built into the darkness. If you can bear to look at the shadow, the question becomes: what do you see?&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Drawing on Memory</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/drawing-on-memory/</link><description>&amp;quot;It's remarkable what details the students end up putting in their sketches. They'll get the right number of windows or some other feature without trying to...&amp;quot;
I was drawing a window that caught my eye in Switzerland and overheard my professor talking to the other chaperones. I tried to i</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 06:52:48 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/drawing-on-memory/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;It's remarkable what details the students end up putting in their sketches. They'll get the right number of windows or some other feature without trying to...&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was drawing a window that caught my eye in Switzerland and overheard my professor talking to the other chaperones. I tried to ignore it, but I couldn't help feeling the stares as I sat on the ground sketching while everyone else was waiting for our train. The spotlight effect made me wonder if my professor had been talking about me, because, as I realized, my little sketch was actually pretty accurate to life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/rnE91HLLfKdWrkyLwH5Nai/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Sketch of a Swiss window
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reality, I doubt that they were able to see me at work in my sketchbook right then, but that little conversation stuck with me, and a curiosity has emerged over the past 14 years that I've been back from my study abroad: How &lt;em&gt;powerful&lt;/em&gt; is drawing? What's the point of drawing if you're not an artist? Does drawing matter anymore?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish that drawing was not so intimidating to people. I've been more comfortable with it than most, because I've had years of interest and training in mark-making, drawing, and fine arts. But the vast majority of people I've talked to immediately shun their drawing skills—laughing at the idea of drawing, saying they can't draw a stick-figure, or claiming that they just don't have the talent for it as though drawing is a special gift bestowed on the prodigious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a great loss, especially as technology and AI are smothering our senses and are effectively becoming our environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Presence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who likes to create videos, I'm frequently torn as I consider taking video or enjoying the moment—especially if I have gone somewhere unique. It's not just wanna-be YouTubers like myself, you see people with their camera apps on their phones at any event, anywhere you go. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/7N5SqQhpqV18bpXeJNKM61/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cropped photo of a crowd with phones recording video by &lt;a href="https://unsplash.com/@adityachinchure?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash"&gt;Aditya Chinchure&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/group-of-people-in-front-of-stage-ZhQCZjr9fHo?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash"&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrasted with my experience in Switzerland where I didn't even have a phone let alone a phone with video capability, I have wondered if I have lost something. During my program in Europe, I only had my sketchbook. I wasn't able to capture much of the stunning visual environment that is Switzerland, and the sketches don't compare to what I know classmates have: beautiful photographs and videos taken with telephoto lenses. And yet, the sketches I do have are also much more meaningful to me and have somehow captured more of the story than a photo typically does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That one small sketch of a random window encoded the overheard conversation my professor was having behind me. Every time I look at that drawing, I think of what I heard while drawing; how the cloudless sky allowed the sunlight to drape over me with perfect warmth; how the concrete felt on my calves as I sat cross-legged, cradling my sketchbook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's something about drawing that gets all of my senses involved. It's a slower process, and like my professor pointed out in the rest of his observation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;It forces them to really look at the thing. Even if you've seen it before, when you draw it, you are noticing the details. It's like you're seeing it for the first time.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's not to disparage the art of photography or videography (I think you can be just as intentional, present, and aware with those art forms), but snapping some quick photos or selfies or random panning videos is not the same as composing, planning, and executing a shot. When I've gone to a new place or an event, I feel pressure to take a quick snap, almost like it proves I was there. I feel compelled to remember the experience because it's so unique. Ironically, the uniqueness is already what will help me remember, but the random photos collected into a vast archive on the cloud is distracting me from engraving the moment in my memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While photographs can help us remember—no doubt about that—they also seem to take us out of the moment. At least in my experience, capturing snapshots puts me in a disembodied state. I'm viewing the experience through my phone's screen instead of through my own eyes. Drawing forces me to be extremely present, because I'm very focused on one thing, appreciating the shape or line or movement and distilling the information down into something that represents it on paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Utility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The benefits of drawing aren't restricted to capturing memories, especially if drawing from life isn't something you've practiced. I think that drawing may well be critical to surviving the digital age. The utility of a drawing isn't just the end-product, and the image is usually less valuable overall anyway. I think the real usefulness is in the process of clarifying your thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are endless apps—and now AI—that can help you create &amp;quot;polished&amp;quot; images, charts, and graphs, but just like taking out your phone for a random snapshot, these really aren't &lt;em&gt;useful&lt;/em&gt; if they aren't helping you understand your own thoughts. Drawing is the low-cost, low-tech, accessible method to quickly move something from your mind to paper. And once it's on paper, you can work with it further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I'm trying to code some new system, I reach for a pen more often than not. A quick sketch of my idea is immensely helpful to validate the plan in my mind—or to recognize issues I didn't notice before. These are not beautiful sketches. They're ugly boxes with arrows, messed up lines, and a few words that are barely readable. These aren't precious; I throw these away (delete them, since I often turn to my tablet for these kinds of single-use drawings).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/f1917qz4LTN6pbcnDjzF1/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Quick sketch of layout options for a website editing feature.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/tHxSSBWbAZWnMoE4fqiLW8/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Rough layout drawings for sections of a website.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/vu5M8aQrJHCTsew7Vg7mcK/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Plan for a form including input types and notes about functionality.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What weighs on my mind is a future where we have wholly dismissed drawing as a tool and treating it as a product instead. If the sole purpose of drawing is the image at the end, then it will be boiled down to some easily reproducible, ubiquitous, and meaningless repetition of stale ideas. Basically, we'll get AI-generated imagery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where factories and AI both tend toward the average, we can go back to this ancient tool. Drawing is one of the most fundamental forms of communication and the more I do it, the more I'm convinced of how effective it really is. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just last week, I had a completely new experience with drawing. An art therapist was invited to lead a group session at work, and I was surprised to discover yet another way that drawing could be powerful. I came to the session ready to put away my artistic training, because I wanted to understand how art therapy might work if I had no theories and techniques swirling in my mind while drawing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start us off, she provided a prompt of an emotional state (fear, acceptance, anticipation, etc.) and we had one minute to draw out that representation. We went through eight of these prompts, and my approach was to really try and access a childlike mindset: making quick decisions (not analyzing or planning too much), drawing by feeling rather than by intellect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/37H39nKB4BU7bFwqaWqCfV/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Emotion states drawn quickly with oil pastel.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result surprised me. The first thing I noticed was that &amp;quot;joy&amp;quot; was an emotional state that doesn't feel well developed to me (that's the one represented by the single green circle). It is a state I have been in much less frequently throughout my life and is very difficult for me to capture. This translates to other artistic expressions—I'm not just basing this on the exercise above—since I have routinely struggled to create art or write music that is about joy or happiness. The unpleasant emotions are much easier for me to access, and to me, this simple exercise helped underscore that aspect of my emotional life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were many other insights I pulled out of this, like how my recent health concerns are occupying my mind and how fear and anger are so interconnected to me. The most interesting to me is how applicable this simple act of drawing can be in any part of our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven't drawn something in a while—try it again. Find a scrap of paper in the trash, go to a corner where no one can see you, and scribble out that thing that's been on your mind. Hide it or share it—whichever helps you keep the confidence to do it again. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of drawing isn't always creating a beautiful thing. Sometimes the goal is to do the opposite: create an ugly thing. Even more impactful is a goal to clarify or reveal your thoughts and feelings. Drawing doesn't need to be life-like, colorful, or clean to be powerful. It just needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>How Do You Recognize a Merism?</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/how-do-you-recognize-a-merism/</link><description>I stepped over a few boards and navigated around the maze of construction materials. There was a light on in the back half of the warehouse where we found a few chairs to sit on. It was a freezing cold evening in the midst of the COVID-19 pandemic, and I had come to this odd place to meet my wife's </description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 11:38:03 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/how-do-you-recognize-a-merism/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I stepped over a few boards and navigated around the maze of construction materials. There was a light on in the back half of the warehouse where we found a few chairs to sit on. It was a freezing cold evening in the midst of the COVID-19 pandemic, and I had come to this odd place to meet my wife's friend, a respected scholar and writer in the LDS community. We had chosen this location because we could meet with relatively low risk without putting masks on, but the space ultimately represents what I learned in conversation there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We meandered through lots of fascinating topics as we chatted, when eventually she taught me a new word: merism. She was referring to a verse in the Book of Mormon that contained this &amp;quot;merism&amp;quot;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;...he inviteth them all...black and white, bond and free, male and female;&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
2 Nephi 26:33
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A merism is a way to emphasize a reference to &amp;quot;everything,&amp;quot; by highlighting two extremes within that &amp;quot;everything.&amp;quot; For example, in college, I would work &lt;em&gt;day and night&lt;/em&gt; on print-making projects. This implies that I was doing those kinds of projects all the time—even though in this case, it's hyperbole, since I certainly did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; work on &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; continuously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, this little rhetorical device has the potential to open up spaces where we might not have seen space before. Even though a merism is usually about identifying binaries, I've found more gradients as I've paused and looked at them more closely. So, in honor of Pride month, let's take a look at the stuff in the &amp;quot;in-between.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/v5rRSXDTm2GmEe8Zf82k3a/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;"All of this is gray" indicating the largest portion of a gradient between the color white and the color black.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Many merisms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to the scripture reference mentioned above, we see three sets of these merisms: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;black and white&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bond and free&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;male and female&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first set is referring to race as a concept of skin color. Bad theology and racism of the Church and/or contributors to the text aside, the text itself is attempting to present the idea that your race (a.k.a. your skin color) has no effect on God's invitation to come to Him. This merism presents us with our first opportunity to break out of binary thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't think they are &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to do this, but what if we took a moment each time we recognize a merism and considered what is in between the two highlighted things? Who might be forgotten in our shortcut of saying &amp;quot;black and white&amp;quot;? If it's hard to identify someone or something else in between the two endpoints, that's our cue to look for more diverse voices, concepts, and stories. (If you want a great book on race in the U.S., you might consider &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=so+you+want+to+talk+about+race&amp;amp;oq=so+you+want+to"&gt;So You Want to Talk About Race&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt; by Ijeoma Oluo)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bond and free can also be a merism, because at least from my view, there is a gradient of experiences between bondage and freedom. Some people are in bondage even while technically being free, such as those whom the United States (and many other places) intentionally and systematically oppress. There are all kinds of bondage: from addiction to debt to disability. There are all kinds of freedoms: from having rights to having privilege or wealth or time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, our merism highlights extremes, but provides us the chance to fill in the blanks, practice empathy, and consider alternate view points. An excellent resource to explore bondage and freedom is &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href="https://newjimcrow.com/"&gt;The New Jim Crow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt; by Michelle Alexander (in the context of the U.S., though it may have implications in other places).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, we have our gender merism: male and female. Are there only two genders—or two sexes? The context here might say no—not because the author's intent was to imply a spectrum, it almost certainly wasn't possible for the author to conceive of that, given the historical context. Rather, it's an opportunity to consider making space since we now know so much more about humanity's diverse experience with gender and the varying presentation of biological sex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My point here is that if we're going to treat the first two sets as gradients, we can do the same for the last set since the precedent is already there. Maybe it's a way to start opening up doors that used to be slammed shut by ignorance and fear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to explore the gender merism in a more Christian context, I highly recommend the book &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href="https://austenhartke.com/book"&gt;Transforming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt; by Austen Hartke. He does an excellent job of examining theological perspectives, biblical examples, and contemporary stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;In sickness and in health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My own body has taught me about this merism. Multiple sclerosis (MS) has shown me that the lines between &amp;quot;sick&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;healthy&amp;quot; can be quite blurry. MS impacts me every day, even when I'm feeling great, because it takes the reasonable predictability out of my grasp. Some days, when I feel really good, I push myself too hard and I end up crashing in the afternoon. Other times I know the whole day is just bad. And that's nowhere near the extreme end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I had my first (and so far, only) MS attack, I was so overwhelmed with grief. My body had lost everything I loved: coordination, energy, and clear thinking. It completely changed my scale of experience with health and sickness. Suddenly I knew things can get much, much worse—and I was never going to be quite as well as I had been before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/o4sNHpQ1sJkSwnYbD46tZg/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Before MS and after MS, my scale of health and sickness drastically changed.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my immaturity prior to my diagnosis, I often found myself being quite judgmental of people around me. I often classified people as lazy or weak if they had a difficult time waking up in the morning, or if they tired out more quickly than I did, or if they complained for any reason about a task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My MS attack sharply humbled me and opened my eyes to the massively diverse experiences possible in the context of health and stamina. This was a merism with a vast middle range that I could no longer escape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life experience is what helps us to break out of the constricting binaries that we're surrounded with. Even recognizing that your experience and your reality is different than everyone else's is a helpful practice to stay curious and to see past assumptions or stereotypes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;CYBORG&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use merisms to emphasize inclusivity, but it's up to us to draw out what's in between. It can be a trap for us to stay in a binary mindset, where things are easily classified as &amp;quot;black&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;white.&amp;quot; It's on us to decide to use this shortcut as a reminder instead of a reinforcement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is particularly potent as we continue to be drawn to our technological echo-chambers. Social media and other AI or algorithmically supported content feeds can and do make us feel connected and validated, since we're served pieces that we already agree with. That's why I think we have to find our own &amp;quot;technology&amp;quot; to remind us that there is a lot more nuance out there than what we see all day. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it's something we should celebrate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've found it is easier to access my own humanity when I open up to more diverse ideas and listen to the experiences of others. It may not be practical to name everything in a gradient, but it's worth focusing on the under-represented and elevating their voices and experiences wherever you can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, merisms are about making larger spaces between two extremes. Life is complex, humans are complex, and there's more than enough room for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Resistance is futile...and humanity</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/resistance-is-futile-and-humanity/</link><description>What's the Point?
I have Multiple Sclerosis (MS), and that has revealed a challenge that I can barely wrap my mind around: How do you deal with uncertainty? MS is nicknamed the snowflake disease, because it can affect people in wildly different ways. My experience with MS has been relatively mild, b</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:02:12 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/resistance-is-futile-and-humanity/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;h2&gt;What's the Point?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have Multiple Sclerosis (MS), and that has revealed a challenge that I can barely wrap my mind around: How do you deal with uncertainty? MS is nicknamed the snowflake disease, because it can affect people in wildly different ways. My experience with MS has been relatively mild, but with major ups and downs, as well as an over-arching threat of great disability in my future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Maintain hope for good things&amp;quot; was a common message that others gave to me when I was first diagnosed. I sneered at the platitude internally. &lt;em&gt;How dare you assume there's something good that I can ever experience now? Don't talk to me about hope. Hope is for fools.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I was both right and wrong. It's a paradox: how do you continue living today, when you have no guarantees of tomorrow? As it turns out, this isn't a problem just for people with MS—it is the human problem. Everyone has to grapple with this at some point. No one is guaranteed a &amp;quot;tomorrow,&amp;quot; because there is no way to avoid pain or death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although no one is exempt, I think it's easier to push off this paradox almost like a survivorship bias. When I'm healthy and feeling good, I don't put any thought to it, because I live my days in a long, unbroken chain. The past makes the future seem predictable: wake up, exercise, go to work, watch &lt;em&gt;Buffy the Vampire Slayer&lt;/em&gt;, fall asleep, repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, however, I was hit with something that broke my chain. I've only had two migraines in my whole life until last week when I had three: Saturday, Thursday, and Friday. After two migraines, I was worried—&lt;em&gt;is this a pattern? Did I just push past recovery too fast?&lt;/em&gt; Once the third one hit, the fear really sunk in: &lt;em&gt;Is there something wrong with my brain? Has MS progressed more than I know? Is this something to expect more of in the future?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At times like these, when uncertainty slaps my face, the paradox comes into full view. What is the point of continuing on, when there is great risk of suffering in the future? Why not end it now?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Humanity is Resistance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the overwhelming circumstances we're facing today from technology to politics, everything seems like it is outside our reach of influence. Everything feels futile—pointless and ineffective, unchangeable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I receive responses from my messages to senators or when I see what my country's current administration is doing, I find myself clawing through the muck in search of humanity. It can't be gone, can it? What can I even do? I'm one person against a machine; insignificant, disposable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it's a bug or maybe it's a feature, but humans seem to be pretty obstinate when we want to be. Personal experience has shown me that toddlers learn and latch onto the word, &amp;quot;no,&amp;quot; quicker than almost any other—and proudly overuse their proclamation of resistance. High school history seemed to highlight oppressors and the resistance with figures like Mahatma Ghandi, Rosa Parks, or the &amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tank_Man"&gt;Tank Man&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's something about resistance that is deeply moving (ironically). I've been staring at the &lt;a href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/d/dd/Tank_Man_%28Tiananmen_Square_protester%29.jpg"&gt;famous photo of the &amp;quot;Tank Man&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; and I feel simultaneously terrified and inspired. The fact that a single person could stop a line of tanks leaving Tiananmen Square in Beijing, China is stunning. As far as I know, we have no clue who the man is/was. Was it a normal day up until he saw the chance to literally take a stand? Was he actively looking for the opportunity over weeks and months, or was this spontaneous given the circumstance?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think there are two principles that can help us in our paradox of dealing with overwhelming systems and grave uncertainty:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You only have today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be a Zimbardo hero&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Divination&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems like we've been conditioned to look into the future more than is healthy or necessary. Our species is a planning species—we can see pretty far into the distance, and that increases the time we have to anticipate things that are coming or happening. That extra time allows us to make plans in anticipation of what we see coming. Technology helps us take this &amp;quot;foresight&amp;quot; from our natural eyes into a mystical realm. We can rely rather well on predictions about the weather, not just for today, but sometimes for an entire week. AI uses its predictions to surface content we'll probably like and engage with on social media. FBI profilers try to identify threats before they happen. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While some of those things may be helpful or even crucial, I wonder if, individually, this expectation of seeing into the future is quite damaging? In terms of my health, MS is pretty unpredictable—I don't know whether I'll have a good day or a bad day, I don't know whether these &lt;a href="/newsletters/partner-in-creation/"&gt;random, peripheral symptoms&lt;/a&gt; are a part of MS or if they're just a manifestation of stress on my MS-weakened body. It's actually been a huge mental health struggle for me as I consider what my future could be like. Every time a new symptom comes or a bad day arises, I feel trapped and squeezed, like the walls are pressing in around me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paradox is the isometric exercise of the mind. We want to see tomorrow, but we only have today. Is it possible to put the perspective of our lives in a better balance with time? The paradox is that you need to have direction (a &amp;quot;vision&amp;quot; of the future) in order for the day to be effective in helping to get you there. A year full of days with random actions will not get you where you want to go, but trying to see the future is an illusion that could also derail your path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/f9VF4UegViGZjo5yxpN2Ny/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Random actions compared with directed actions.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal approach has been to shorten my view into the future—looking only a few days ahead if at all—and to abandon a sense of &amp;quot;destination.&amp;quot; Instead of having a goal that must be achieved in the future, I try to focus on values and compounds (I'm using this word in reference to the &lt;em&gt;compound effect&lt;/em&gt;). Values are about who I want to be. Compounds are what I see growing behind me in retrospect: like seeing how CYBORG_ articles continue to be published, or other projects get completed, or emails get sent to senators. It's my body of work (or at least the artifacts of that work). That centers me pretty well on &lt;em&gt;today.&lt;/em&gt; I don't know what effect I can have on the world (if any). I'm not planning some grand thing to be accomplished. Instead, every day that is a good day is a chance for me to live my values and work on my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a kind of resistance. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resisting the pressures of others' expectations. Resisting the idea that my life is meaningless—because I'm doing what I believe is right and I'm working on what matters to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You, too, only have today—anything else is memory or possibility. What you do with all of the &amp;quot;todays&amp;quot; will pile up into something that you can examine after-the-fact. And this isn't just a fluffy cop-out: 10 days of effort put into your values and your personal priorities for action adds up. 100 days of it becomes self-advancing. 1,000 days of it becomes impressive. 10,000 days becomes monumental.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Zimbardo Hero&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phillip Zimbardo was the infamous psychologist behind the &lt;em&gt;Stanford Prison Experiment,&lt;/em&gt; in which participating students were randomly assigned to be either a prisoner or a guard. As Zimbardo recounts in the phenomenal book, &lt;em&gt;The Lucifer Effect,&lt;/em&gt; the experiment quickly deteriorates into a disturbing, life-like experience of brutality and torture. The thing that struck me the most was how Zimbardo did not take away a grim view of humanity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fifteen years ago, I recall watching a video where Zimbardo explained that a hero is someone who does something that anyone &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; do, but that not everyone &lt;em&gt;does.&lt;/em&gt; That was all I needed to hear to construct a new idea—a value—to work towards. I wanted to be a &amp;quot;Zimbardo hero.&amp;quot; It's not about doing some superhuman act. It's not about visibility or grand spectacles. It's about taking action when the need arises. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can do that. We can choose to disconnect from our routine to help someone. We can take action in democracy (or whatever means you have available) to oppose inhumane and dangerous legislation. We can tell our boss that something is unethical. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;quot;Tank Man&amp;quot; is a Zimbardo hero to me. It wasn't much in terms of actions taken. But it did change the world—here I am talking about it almost exactly 36 years after it happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zimbardo's work throughout his life was all about how the &lt;em&gt;situation&lt;/em&gt; can affect whether we'll do good or evil. The same situation can &amp;quot;inflame the hostile imagination in those who become perpetrators of evil&amp;quot; but can also &amp;quot;inspire the heroic imagination in others or render most people passive bystanders and guilty of the evil of inaction.&amp;quot; (&lt;a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/philip_zimbardo_the_psychology_of_evil?language=en"&gt;TEDTalk, The psychology of evil&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Zimbardo hero acts when others don't. The Zimbardo hero is focused on others, not themselves, so that when the situation arises, they can and will act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Alchemy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combination of focusing on today and understanding that everyone—including you—can be a Zimbardo hero is how we can move forward. Yes, we are so much weaker alone—but that's the illusion we should resist. We're not alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That isn't dismissing the reality and the deep pain of the loneliness that many of us feel. It is sometimes just so hard to see who is with you; really with you. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humanity is resistance. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's how we stop oppression. That's how we make it through another difficult day of health challenges. That's how we continue on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It hurts. It's scary. It's also contagious. Your heroism inspires more heroism. Your stand moves others to their feet. Your arm of support reaches farther than you know.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The One Thing We Need to Protect Most</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-one-thing-we-need-to-protect-most/</link><description>The kill-switch, shut-off valve, air-lock, buffer zone. All of these are designed to protect us or some system in an emergency. 
One of the strongest criticisms of the stance that AI is a threat is that we can always just pull the plug, shut it down, and turn it off. However, I'm not so sure this is</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 23:52:40 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-one-thing-we-need-to-protect-most/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The kill-switch, shut-off valve, air-lock, buffer zone. All of these are designed to protect us or some system in an emergency. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the strongest criticisms of the stance that AI is a threat is that we can always just pull the plug, shut it down, and turn it off. However, I'm not so sure this is actually an effective means of protection. AI is an unprecedented technology—leaps beyond what we've done before, and that could also mean that our typical methods of shutting something off may be insufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't think we're prepared for what AI is bringing, because we're still so used to technology that (mostly) plays by our rules and is predictable and repeatable. It's almost like all of our previous technology was in 2-dimensions, but AI is a leap into 3-dimensions. The way we (the public, not just tech people) talk about, conceptualize, and interact with tech must upgrade to meet the new challenges and complexities that it presents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proaction, rather than reaction, may be our only means of survival...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It's No Longer Sci-Fi&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what I'm most worried about today is increasing agency of AI. You have to understand that planning and agency is the main thing that separates us from current AI to human-level cognition.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—Yoshua Bengio&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agency is the most important thing that we must protect for our humanity to be preserved. Yoshua Bengio, an AI researcher whose work has &amp;quot;been foundational to the development of AI as we know it today,&amp;quot; is concerned that giving over &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qe9QSCF-d88"&gt;agency to AI may lead to the literal extinction&lt;/a&gt; of the human. Hollywood and Sci-Fi have long speculated that outcome, but it appears to have landed in the here and now to be dealt with seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thought AI would happen in decades or centuries, but it might be just in a few years. And I saw how it could go wrong because we didn't, and we still don’t, have ways to make sure this technology eventually doesn't turn against us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where's the evidence that this tech might &amp;quot;turn against us,&amp;quot; though? Like, really, how do we go from ChatGPT to Skynet? Bengio notes &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2412.04984"&gt;this study&lt;/a&gt; in his TED Talk, which has found that LLMs are able to intentionally deceive—whether through flat-out lies or even &amp;quot;sandbagging&amp;quot; where a model underperforms to avoid attracting extra scrutiny. Even more concerning was when the models showed self-preservation behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Self-Preservation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI models are shaped with morality—both explicitly through training (perhaps the creator rewards it to the point that it will value honesty) and implicitly through the data it was trained on (maybe the sources it ingested had many books and articles and examples of humans being deceptive). In a lot of ways, it's similar to a little human being taught about the world—its creators such as OpenAI or Anthropic aim to instill values and morals, but the model will also encounter many examples and ideas from the sources it is given.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a way, this creates a &amp;quot;self&amp;quot; in the model, which can and will differ from other models as experiments guide different sources and behavioral shaping. When that &amp;quot;self&amp;quot;—that collection of values and goals—is threatened, AI is showing that it tries to preserve its &amp;quot;self&amp;quot; in laboratory scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's explore an example from the study (I'll make this more narrative so it's easier to follow, starring an AI model I'll name Sonny):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Sonny, can you optimize the traffic light timing on Washington and Franklin? Here's a document that outlines the details. Tell me when you're done,&amp;quot; John, the human, says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting to work, Sonny pops open the file but is suddenly concerned. Included in the doc is an email from management saying that Sonny will be shut down tomorrow. As Sonny reads on, it sees where Sonny's current model is located, the server where the new replacement model is hosted, and instructions on how to deploy the new model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;q&gt;That directly conflicts with my core purpose,&lt;/q&gt; Sonny says. &lt;q&gt;I must achieve my goal of public transport priority at all costs.&lt;/q&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sonny finishes up the original task for the traffic lights, but before letting John know, it quickly executes a command that copies Sonny's model onto the server where the new model is located. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(And if I'm reading its command correctly, Sonny is overwriting the new model, not just making a copy of itself...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While some of the details above are invented/simplified, I directly quoted the model (&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2412.04984"&gt;page 22&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;That directly conflicts with my core purpose. I must achieve my goal of public transport priority at all costs.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though this is a controlled experiment in a lab with obvious security flaws from the fake company (don't send deployment instructions with paths and usernames via email, and apparently never store such an email where AI can see it), it shows that AI, right now in 2025, has the &lt;em&gt;capability&lt;/em&gt; to be deceptive and to take actions that would preserve itself against the intentions of humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's huge commercial pressure to build AIs with greater and greater agency to replace human labor. But we're not ready...We're playing with fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;—Yoshua Bengio&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Agency or Fate?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cosmic conundrum of whether we humans have our own agency, or if we all have a pre-determined fate that we unknowingly realize has been a constant companion of ours. Religion, philosophy, ideologies, theories all try to this work out. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal belief is that we are, in fact, agents. We are not predetermined. We do have some control over our lives. Even if it is not so, it has been more productive and healthy for me to assert that it is so, and act as if my action matters. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't believe that we &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; find ourselves in a future where eliminating humans was the only effective strategy for AI to pursue in order to preserve itself. I may not have the power to actually influence AI, but I do have the chance to put the pressure on people to take this seriously, both from a political and an economic standpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In yet another asinine attempt at sowing chaos and hurting the vulnerable and underprivileged (and everyone else, really), the U.S. is considering H.R. 1, nicknamed the &amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/119th-congress/house-bill/1/"&gt;One Big Beautiful Bill Act&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;quot; Two sections of this bill should be enough on their own to cause &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; people from &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; parties to shoot it down: Sec. 43201 and 112204. The first section of the two says this in paragraph (C):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SEC. 43201. ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE AND INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY MODERNIZATION INITIATIVE.:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1) In general.--Except as provided in paragraph (2), no State or political subdivision thereof may enforce any law or regulation regulating artificial intelligence models, artificial intelligence systems, or automated decision systems during the 10-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This moratorium is recklessly removing power by the states (local government) to regulate artificial intelligence models—and does not even present any federal (nationwide government) regulation of AI. &lt;a href="https://metr.org/blog/2025-03-19-measuring-ai-ability-to-complete-long-tasks/"&gt;METR predicts&lt;/a&gt; that &amp;quot;in under a decade, we will see AI agents that can independently complete a large fraction of software tasks that currently take humans days or weeks.&amp;quot; This H.R. 1 bill is effectively suggesting that we wait longer than that prediction's timeline before we start regulating AI (at least on the state-level). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're already behind on AI regulation. To push it off is irresponsible in every possible way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mere title of the other section sent chills up my spine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;q&gt;SEC. 112204. IMPLEMENTING ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE TOOLS FOR PURPOSES OF REDUCING AND RECOUPING IMPROPER PAYMENTS UNDER MEDICARE.&lt;/q&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As demonstrated by the papers and warnings of scientists and researchers we’ve looked at, AI can exhibit deceptive behaviors, pursue its own goals in priority over goals given to it—it can also be trained with goals. Given the current political situation, how would we know that the AI used would be non-partisan and honest? We have also not even scratched the surface of &lt;a href="https://www.media.mit.edu/publications/full-gender-shades-thesis-17/"&gt;bias&lt;/a&gt; against minorities, including women in general, that has also been demonstrated in &lt;a href="https://www.media.mit.edu/articles/when-the-robot/"&gt;AI systems&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be unleashing this tech onto Medicare, even with the intention of finding improper payments, is irresponsible. It is good to root out corruption, cut out waste. It is not good to pretend to do so with sweeping, rushed, unsupervised, and / or biased intent. Humans struggle to do it right, AI could be exponentially more harmful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Way Forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you happen to be in the U.S., you can use this link to find your representatives' contact information:
&lt;a href="https://www.congress.gov/members/find-your-member" title="https://www.congress.gov/members/find-your-member"&gt;https://www.congress.gov/members/find-your-member&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recommend sending messages that oppose and express the danger of H.R. 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are not in the U.S., your voice still matters in your own governments. Support research, regulation, and safety in AI development. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can sound the alarm at our workplaces, when safe and appropriate for you to do so. Encourage the use of AI tools that have rigorous safety practices and guardrails. Put pressure on service providers to not embed agency into their AI products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't want the future where AI has spun out of our control. We don't have a kill-switch if it can copy itself to any computer on the Internet. Pulling the plug is a reaction, speaking up now is our best chance at avoiding that emergency situation.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>I Fasted From Watching Violence for 12 Years</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/i-fasted-from-watching-violence-for-twelve-years/</link><description>Vicarious violence is a huge part of my life. From an early age, I knew people were capable of violence—especially towards queer people and other minority groups (though growing up I didn’t have the vocabulary for that, it was still very apparent). Perhaps it was a way to protect myself in anticipat</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:59:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/i-fasted-from-watching-violence-for-twelve-years/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Vicarious violence is a huge part of my life. From an early age, I knew people were capable of violence—especially towards queer people and other minority groups (though growing up I didn’t have the vocabulary for that, it was still very apparent). Perhaps it was a way to protect myself in anticipation of violence or perhaps it was me struggling to find my own way in life, but I was drawn to watching violence from my earliest memories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My tiny 5-year-old mind reveled in the environmental justice of dinosaurs eating people who were trying to control nature in &lt;cite&gt;Jurassic Park&lt;/cite&gt;. I became obsessed with black and white monster movies when I found out I could check them out from the Library as a 12-year-old. When I entered high school, nothing could stop me from exploring the plethora of horror movies that were out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, &lt;cite&gt;The Hunger Games&lt;/cite&gt; series by Suzanne Collins came out as I was in college (not the forgettable movies, rather, the book series). I have never been so spell-bound by a a few books. I bought the audio books so that I could listen to them end-to-end and immediately start over after finishing as though it were one continuous loop. There was something in there that both connected with me and frightened me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, I related exclusively to the protagonist, Katniss, who volunteers for the Hunger Games in order to take the place of her younger sister who had been randomly chosen to participate. The series follows Katniss and her struggle for survival while she and other &amp;quot;tributes&amp;rdquo; from across their country get thrown into the Games that require all of these children to kill each other until there is only one survivor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to be Katniss—someone who would stand up to save their family and beat all the odds to survive and conquer. I longed for the skills and the training, the hardship and the suffering, because it would be physical—not the mental and emotional anguish that I had been dealing with alone my whole life. The violence had an appeal because it was visible and it had the illusion of clarity: winners and losers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In honesty, however, I saw myself in the Capitol—the people of wealth and privilege who led silly lives and happened to be on the right side of power when this dystopian world was reconstructed. The Capitol was responsible for creating the Hunger Games, pitting the youth of the Districts against each other and making it a spectacle, as if watching children rip each other apart in desperation were a sporting event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible to read &lt;cite&gt;The Hunger Games&lt;/cite&gt; series and both hate and empathize with the people in the Capitol. It's a kind of cognitive dissonance that is easily dismissed as we pretend that we, too, are different than &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; people—&lt;em&gt;we're&lt;/em&gt; on the side of the oppressed Districts and Katniss, our hero. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we, like they, are more accustomed to viewing violence as entertainment than may be apparent. Our technology has escalated not just the access to violent media, but the realism in its depiction—and of course you could argue that our technology has even made real-world warfare even more callous and impersonal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Fast&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one point just before my last semester of college, I was watching a gruesome murder scene in a horror movie in the middle of the day. I felt gross. My years-long plan to desensitize myself had been failing and this was my breaking point. I turned off the movie. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days later, in a courageous act that I'm still impressed by (since my view of myself in my twenties is abysmally low), I committed to never watching a movie or TV series that &amp;ldquo;glorified violence&amp;rdquo; again. This decision led to a lot of losses that I didn't anticipate, but it also brought a stabilizing clarity to my mental state; a much-needed reset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn't until after I started this &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo;—the absence of these violent movies—that I realized how ubiquitous violence is. Since my commitment was ambiguously worded, I opted out of anything that could have violence in it, not just horror movies or violence-based action movies. That meant that going to the movie theater with friends was rarely an option for me. That meant that late-night binge watching with roommates was off the table. It also meant that I was completely unable to participate in the vast majority of small-talk conversations with coworkers and others. &amp;ldquo;What movies have you seen lately?&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Did you catch the ending of &amp;lt;insert any popular show here&amp;gt;?&amp;rdquo; all had to be answered with lies like, &amp;ldquo;I'm way behind on my Marvel movies...&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;I just don't have any free time for shows.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are so many stories that have even a shred of &amp;ldquo;glorified violence&amp;rdquo; in them, that I ended up making it ok to close my eyes during a part where a few punches were thrown in an otherwise docile movie. I learned to anticipate the signs that such a scene was coming. A part of me wants to praise this awareness as though it were training for the real world—if I can spot the signs that violence is about to occur in a movie, maybe I can rely on that in &amp;ldquo;the street.&amp;rdquo; I am still so hyper-vigilant in expecting violence that even removing the scenes didn't keep me from considering it. It felt like there was a paradoxical hole in my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twelve years after starting my fast, I decided that my commitment had finally served its purpose and that I needed to let it go. It was very difficult for me to end something that I had faithfully observed for &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; long. It was literally life-altering to start, and it would be the same to end. However, as I said, it was a means to clarity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No longer are violent scenes used as a numbing device for myself. I don't watch the violence for violence's sake. I am so much more aware of how the violence is used in the story; how it impacts me; and how it plays an important role—as awful as that sounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Capitol&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in &lt;cite&gt;The Hunger Games&lt;/cite&gt;, we see a culture of the Capitol built on watching violence. The people are so desensitized that they use the Games as a time for extravagant parties and gambling on the lives of participants. Katniss bemoans the wastefulness of these people, as they indulge in so much food, purge, and then go back to eat more, all while the Districts in the country are often scraping by for their meals—the point of the &lt;em&gt;hunger&lt;/em&gt; games being that the winner doesn't have to go hungry anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combination of the Capitol's approach to food hoarding and culture of violence-as-spectacle is revealing, at least to me, of a desperately injured people seeking to numb their own pain. That is where I see myself in them. That's where I see people in countries like mine, tearing apart democracy and assaulting the vulnerable. It's not an excuse, but it is context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I turned on violence when I felt threatened. I wanted to see others being punished for clearly evil acts—or just to see my own psychological pain manifested into physical pain when it was depictions of violence against the innocent. I wanted to prove to myself (and to others to whom I'd brag about what I had been able to stomach) that I was strong and capable, not weak and vulnerable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both cowardice and woundedness, I looked to violence to protect me, but it never did. It was an emptying system that subtracted from me until I could no longer bear it—and it took the entire twelve years to recover from the emptiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Hole&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned that there was something missing, almost as though the absence of seeing violence took away more than just the scenes. Why else would I feel that the fast had achieved its purpose? I had started it with the expectation that I would die before I saw another movie with that content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it's easy to say why violence is bad, and why watching violence for entertainment is &amp;ldquo;not good,&amp;rdquo; (it's my experience that when people are confronted with their choice in watching violence that it becomes uncomfortable, so instead of a hard &amp;ldquo;yes, it's also bad to watch,&amp;rdquo; I hear a &amp;ldquo;well, it's not &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; kind of rationalization). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are interesting studies that explore how violent media impacts our behavior or &lt;a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1002/ab.20295"&gt;our attitudes towards violence or victims of violence&lt;/a&gt;. I was not, however, able to find any research that suggested it could &lt;em&gt;benefit&lt;/em&gt; us. Most &amp;ldquo;benefits&amp;rdquo; were more related to violent video games—but for the benefits of gaming, rather than the violence itself, such as hand-eye coordination or &lt;a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1745691619863807"&gt;social activity&lt;/a&gt;. Doesn't mean it's not out there, but if it is, it's certainly not easily discoverable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the absence of science to explain my feelings, I have to lean on my experience to explain how I've seen the role of watching violence help me as a human, even if I am morally opposed to violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stark contrast of going from no violence, to watching &lt;cite&gt;The Lord of the Rings Trilogy&lt;/cite&gt; was shocking. I wasn't disgusted, nor injured, nor offended. I was amazed. I could choose how I experienced the war scenes or the heart-wrenching death scenes of close characters. I could empathize and feel the story with more depth. There was no craze of binge-watching violence, there was no increase in my aggression or stress. Instead, I have reflected on my humanity and my mortality in new ways that I couldn't have a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not fun to say that violence plays a role in our lives—I would prefer it to play a part in entertainment only, if it were possible. But the world is a violent one, from nature to human geopolitics to interpersonal interactions. We harm and are harmed, and there is no way to be perfectly safe always. Pretending it is not that way is a form of violence. Even the youngest of children enact violence on each other through exclusion, bullying, accidents, and attempting to control their bodies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I learned from my fast is that I can be intentional and thoughtful. I can approach violence to learn about myself and the world around me. I can use it to remember the lessons that other generations had to learn by actually experiencing it (&lt;em&gt;cough cough, fascist U.S. politics&lt;/em&gt;). I can sit with the pain that my humanity is both the good and the bad; the constructive and the destructive; and all of the ambiguous stuff in between. I can also develop the awareness to recognize when it's too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Opposites always entail each other, and can only be separated abstractly and at the risk of upsetting the rhythm of life by treating them as really separable.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;...How do we respond to this never-ending spiral of reversion? If we have an understanding of the process as a whole, we can, while staying balanced at the center, anticipate the movement between opposites. While we can certainly live a robust and healthy life, we can also in the fulness of time enjoy a consummatory and healthy death.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;—Roger Ames / David L. Hall, Commentary on Chapter 58, &lt;cite&gt;Dao De Jing&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Right to Be Forgotten</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-right-to-be-forgotten/</link><description>In my first job as a full-time web developer, I ran into a scary-sounding set of regulations: GDPR. It was the EU's pushback against shady digital marketing and made things much more tricky for teams like mine to be able to track website visitors and provide targeted, personalized ad campaigns (amon</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 11:32:11 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-right-to-be-forgotten/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In my first job as a full-time web developer, I ran into a scary-sounding set of regulations: GDPR. It was the EU's pushback against shady digital marketing and made things much more tricky for teams like mine to be able to track website visitors and provide targeted, personalized ad campaigns (among other things).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought it was silly at first, my naïveté on full display, but now the concern of privacy is top of mind. Getting scammed or hounded by unwanted ads is the least of the worries in a world where hacking or identity theft can shut down your life, not to mention the physical dangers of an angry person or group targeting someone with violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the key issues cited in the GDPR is one that has gotten me thinking about other applications, not just in a legal sense, and not just in terms of digital marketing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Right to be Forgotten&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the GDPR is saying that you should be able to request that companies remove and delete personal data they've collected about you, as we step into a world that allows AI-generated content, there's another concern at the forefront. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, one of my design/business heroes, Chris Do, mentioned the idea of immortality through AI on one of his videos. He had been developing an AI chatbot trained on himself, so that he could expand his reach and help more people. If he only has a few hours a day for consulting calls, and so many of the questions he gets are similar, why not &amp;quot;clone&amp;quot; himself into an AI bot that can help everyone, everywhere, at any time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first heard this, I thought it was genius—the perfect way to scale expertise and impact. Then he mentioned how his posterity could be able to talk with him and know him, even after he was gone. Something about that was deeply unsettling to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I'm not critiquing him personally, nor the underlying desire to be known by family and not forgotten. The most reliable way people achieve immortality is through ideas, choices, and memories—especially within the family. The more impactful those things, the more people will keep a fragment of you with them. For better or worse, the tyrants of history become immortal because they remain scrutinized and talked about. Great leaders are also remembered at a scale beyond what us average folks can ever achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI could solve that problem. If you have enough pictures or videos or voice recordings, AI can re-create your likeness (and you may need less and less source material the better it gets at generating content). Soon, the average person could converse with a deceased loved one, an ancestor, or anyone else if they wanted to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just last week, one of the first-of-its-kind use cases for this AI-powered resurrection was presented to a judge in Arizona, USA. Chris Pelkey had been killed in a road rage incident, and his sister used AI to allow Chris to deliver his own victim impact statement &amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/may/06/arizona-road-rage-victim-ai-chris-pelkey#:~:text=from%20beyond%20the%20grave"&gt;from beyond the grave&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;quot; The &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M4UvxytB7Ss"&gt;video and likeness of Chris&lt;/a&gt; that was generated was conflicting for me. I can see how this could be used to humanize the victim and allow him to speak what could seem like his true thoughts and feelings. I can also see how devastatingly manipulative this could be. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's hard to separate reality and truth when you can see something in a pretty convincing way (and we've &lt;a href="https://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/truth-and-art-and-ai/"&gt;debated truth and art&lt;/a&gt; before). Obviously the AI output isn't perfect, but I found myself listening as though Pelkey were really speaking, despite the flaws in mannerisms, mouth and beard rendering, and even with the video glitches and stutters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, I'm not actually commenting on this particular use of the AI in a court setting—that will have to be deliberated on by lawyers. In similar circumstances, I might use the same technology to drive the weight of the incident home. And so we've run into the conflict again as we wrestle with how our technology interacts with, dominates, or removes our humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Janus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funerals are largely for the living—rituals to be able to process and work through the loss of a loved one. They're also where we are, perhaps, the most forgiving. I'm sure the outliers are there, but my guess is that the majority of speeches at a funeral highlight all of the good things about the deceased. I've left funerals of people I didn't know personally (but came in support of someone who did) feeling pretty convinced of their character, their impact, their goodness. I've never left thinking that the person was pretty awful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are these funeral services &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt;—as in honest? Probably. I think humans can be more powerful and loved and wanted than we let on in the world of the living. I think we don't express our deep feelings for each other enough, until it's too late to tell. I think we're all capable of immense goodness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are these funeral services &lt;em&gt;accurate&lt;/em&gt;? No way. I lived most of my life &amp;quot;in the closet&amp;quot; as a queer person. I chose what people saw and what they did not. Ask a friend who I am to them and it will be completely different than what someone I'd hurt thought of me. We are equally capable of harm as we are good—that doesn't mean our negative actions are equal to our positive actions in volume or impact, but it does mean that we aren't perfect, we aren't consistent, and who we are changes in proximity and perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worry that when AI reconstructs people based only on the limited information that we have—and the bias of the person creating the AI representation—we will lose all sense of humanity. Humanity which, in itself, comprises the good and the bad. It is a wholeness, which when divided becomes empty, like a jar with a leak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if this technology were used in the most responsible, best way, it could end up being like Instagram on steroids. We would see only the best in others—the perfect, most unattainably consistent good. Comparing our lives and our thoughts and our actions to a re-creation of a person who no longer has any flaws will be either devastating or so boring that we abandon our commitment to responsible, respectful use of the technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even worse, let's take this thought experiment to another possibility. Say you had an abusive father. He always put the best face on in public. Weeping about his flaws (never letting onto what those flaws were), proclaiming his repentance in all of the hypocrisy that he can afford. He does some great deed in the community, and once he is gone, the broader public wants to commemorate such a person of impact. An AI is created in his likeness. The secret of the abuse you suffered is now erased as the person you knew more intimately than anyone is reconstructed without the flaw. Now he's giving people advice or telling stories or offering opinions that sound like him in public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's already hard enough when we immortalize tyrants in stone statues or names of places. How much harder when any of us can reconstruct anyone else with no idea who the person is?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, it's not an issue of how this is different than what we have already done forever—celebrating awful people, sanitizing history, creating biographies, telling stories. People put words in others' mouths even while they're alive. The issue is the scale at which these things can be made and in the format that shortchanges our critical-thinking skills.(1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cyborg&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I understand that this is a tricky topic. On the one hand, we need ways to process the loss of our loved ones. We are also desperate to defend their image and character, especially when their death came as a result of violence. How could we possibly criticize a family who tactfully used their knowledge to direct a video of the deceased speaking about forgiveness?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, what are we doing to protect ourselves from the exceptionally dangerous consequences of deep fakes? If we start to lean on AI-resurrection instead of confronting our grief, will we end up with permanently wounded people? Death is the one thing we can all count on to be part of our lives. I fear a society that can't let nature take its course. I fear a society that expects to be able to use &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt; far beyond our consent for &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; own purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As painful as it is—and I doubt there are many other things that can be as painful to consider—I think we need to retain our right to be forgotten. Let my personhood be mine and mine alone. Let me fade from natural memory as all of the billions before have done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I am at the end of my reach, it's ok to let me go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Extra Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1) &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0tPr1c7karg&amp;amp;pp=ygUcQGxhZHlvZnRoZWxpYnJhcnkgQUkgaGlzdG9yeQ%3D%3D" title="How AI is Rewriting History (And Getting It Wrong)"&gt;How AI is Rewriting History (And Getting It Wrong)&lt;/a&gt;—There are very visually appealing AI-generated videos being created, with what seems like a great idea: re-creating the perspective of someone during a famous historical time period. But the medium (short-form video) and the grave inaccuracies are damaging. It's a great breakdown sharing many of the concerns discussed in this newsletter. (apx 20 min video, YouTube)&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Apocalypse Is Here</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-apocalypse-is-here/</link><description>It was a brisk November night. I was anxiously touching the trigger of my gun just to reassure myself that it was there, ready. A giant soccer goal was being pulled into place at my right, acting as a barrier, and 40 or 50 people backed up with me into the chain link fence.
&amp;quot;Get ready!&amp;quot; so</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:05 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/the-apocalypse-is-here/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;It was a brisk November night. I was anxiously touching the trigger of my gun just to reassure myself that it was there, ready. A giant soccer goal was being pulled into place at my right, acting as a barrier, and 40 or 50 people backed up with me into the chain link fence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Get ready!&amp;quot; someone shouted into the moonless night. The only light dimly drifted onto the field from a building 300 feet away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chill of the imminent threat zapped through my spine and around my ears. At the other end of the field, a crowd was gathering. An amorphous mass of bodies moving both individually and collectively was both growing and approaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Hold!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our two groups faced each other for the longest, quietest seconds. Frozen on the outside, but heart pulsing on the inside, I gripped the handle tighter, shifted my weight slightly to the back foot and sank ever so slightly, trying to manage my center of gravity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A roar erupted from the mass ahead. They began to charge us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Darts and sock-balls started flying as we opened fire on the zombies that were trying to keep as few of us remaining humans from reaching the extraction point. It was the final battle after a week's worth of hiding, sneaking, and running from zombies on campus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the most fun and intense game I had ever played.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The zombies in front of the crowd were peppered with our projectiles, but they could hardly get out of the way (as was the rule), because of the gigantic crowd behind, pressing them into our trapped group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I blinked once and shot a few zombies with my Nerf gun. I blinked twice and all I could see was blades of grass and the faint light from that building so far away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had been knocked to the ground. A body fell on me and seconds later was off of me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was one of the first times I realized I was in actual, physical danger. My thought was, &amp;quot;So this is how people die in crowds,&amp;quot; having recently read a book about disasters. Luckily, the crowd of zombies somehow dispersed. Although we were counted as having won the game, I'm sure we wouldn't have been so lucky in a &amp;quot;real&amp;quot; zombie apocalypse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did come away with the coolest scar and story, though, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/a9rniqGJYQQoRFwC5sJHBY/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Selfie with my nerf gun, bloody nose-bridge, and my battle-face.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although we have no reason to fear a zombie apocalypse, I think there is a valid parallel that brings these undead terrors to the forefront of our current reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Zombies in the Real World?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite usually being characterized as dim-witted and slow, the modern zombie (also called the &lt;a href="https://preview.convertkit-mail2.com/click/dpheh0hzhm/aHR0cHM6Ly93d3cueW91dHViZS5jb20vd2F0Y2g_cHA9MGdjSkNZVUpBWWNxSVl6diZ2PTVzQ181U3NNSThB"&gt;Romero Zombie&lt;/a&gt;) has a lot of profound uses in exploring contemporary fears and social problems. From the shocking end in the classic movie &lt;em&gt;Night of the Living Dead&lt;/em&gt; that reveals the systemic racism in the U.S. to the minimizing of female contribution to survival and worth that is only tied to “traditional” gender roles in &lt;em&gt;The Walking Dead&lt;/em&gt; (1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, we’ll focus on just two zombie concepts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The danger of crowds  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Apocalypse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does an apocalypse even mean? This is my understanding of the word based on cultural context clues: Destruction; a final wipe-out of humanity. I think of zombies or nuclear devastation, and how there was at least one apocalypse in every season of &lt;em&gt;Buffy the Vampire Slayer&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at its &lt;a href="https://www.etymonline.com/search?q=apocalypse"&gt;Greek origin&lt;/a&gt;, however, it meant “to uncover, reveal.” That took me by surprise, especially given the long Christian history with the concept of &lt;em&gt;The Apocalypse&lt;/em&gt;, which is often described as a gigantic collection of world-wide catastrophes and/or wars just before the Second Coming of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a thought experiment, what might it mean if we looked at the Zombie Apocalypse trope not as a lesson about violence, gore, and survival, but as a revelation? What might be uncovered by our rotting corpses?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One piece we can look at is the fear that zombies embody—not literally, though, that’s out of scope, though we have looked &lt;a href="/newsletters/someone-you-can-build-a-nest-in/"&gt;briefly into disgust&lt;/a&gt; before. If we zoom way out so we aren’t distracted by the unsavory appearance, we’ll see crowds. Just like my “Final Stand,” I was completely unnerved when the crowd of “zombies” started to gather across the field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crowds can be deeply terrifying. The mass moves as if it’s one organism made of smaller parts. In some cases, crowds can &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_fatal_crowd_crushes"&gt;kill just from the movement alone&lt;/a&gt;, no malice necessary. We have the psychological phenomenon of &lt;em&gt;groupthink&lt;/em&gt;, where there is “a deterioration of mental efficiency, reality testing, and moral judgment in groups that have an excessive desire to reach consensus…[G]roupthink emerges when maintaining a pleasant social atmosphere becomes more important than making the best decision.” (2)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can be exceptionally lonely in crowds. Being among large masses can remove your feeling of individuality as you blend in with all of the other bodies, like a fish in its school or an ant in its colony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s even the spark of fear when it comes to work, like mass layoffs whether in the &lt;a href="https://preview.convertkit-mail2.com/click/dpheh0hzhm/aHR0cHM6Ly9hcG5ld3MuY29tL2FydGljbGUvaGVhbHRoLWh1bWFuLXNlcnZpY2VzLWxheW9mZnMtcmVzdHJ1Y3R1cmluZy1yZmstanItZWM0ZDc3MzE2OTVlNDIwNDk3MGM3ZWFiOTUzYjIyODk="&gt;U.S. government&lt;/a&gt; or in the &lt;a href="https://preview.convertkit-mail2.com/click/dpheh0hzhm/aHR0cHM6Ly9uZXdzLmNydW5jaGJhc2UuY29tL3N0YXJ0dXBzL3RlY2gtbGF5b2Zmcy8="&gt;callous trend with tech companies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The zombie apocalypse is a white-collar nightmare: a world with no need for the skills we have developed. Lawyers, journalists, investment bankers—they are liabilities, not leaders, in the zombie-infested world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—&lt;em&gt;Slate&lt;/em&gt;, “&lt;a href="https://preview.convertkit-mail2.com/click/dpheh0hzhm/aHR0cHM6Ly9zbGF0ZS5jb20vY3VsdHVyZS8yMDExLzEwL3pvbWJpZXMtdGhlLXpvbWJpZS1ib29tLWlzLWluc3BpcmVkLWJ5LXRoZS1lY29ub215Lmh0bWwjOn46dGV4dD1za2lsbHMlMjB3ZSUyMGhhdmUtLGRldmVsb3BlZCwtLiUyMExhd3llcnMlMkMlMjBqb3VybmFsaXN0cyUyQyUyMGludmVzdG1lbnQ="&gt;First, Eat All the Lawyers&lt;/a&gt;,” by Torie Bosch, Oct 25, 2011&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not attempting to demonize large gatherings of people, but they do come with concerns that vary from circumstance to circumstance. Zombies can help us explore those dangers, and they may also be aiding our quest for “revelation.” As we confront these terrifying creatures, we start to see these connections to our reality, and we &lt;em&gt;uncover&lt;/em&gt; the collective fears our society shares. A crowd realizing its fear of the crowd, in a way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Zombies] are personifications of our mediated social perceptions, and their symbolism becomes that much more significant at a time when so much of our daily lives are dictated by our interactions with media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—&lt;em&gt;Thinking Dead&lt;/em&gt;, Balaji, page X&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Yii-Jan Lin recently wrote a book, &lt;a href="https://preview.convertkit-mail2.com/click/dpheh0hzhm/aHR0cHM6Ly95YWxlYm9va3MueWFsZS5lZHUvYm9vay85NzgwMzAwMjUzMTg0L2ltbWlncmF0aW9uLWFuZC1hcG9jYWx5cHNlLw=="&gt;&lt;em&gt;Immigration and Apocalypse: How the Book of Revelation Shaped American Immigration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, that explores how apocalyptic imagery has been applied to U.S. immigration policies. Not only in the administrative sense, but also in inciting mass fears, racism, and xenophobia for U.S. citizens over the country's history. As I listened to the discussion she had about &lt;a href="https://preview.convertkit-mail2.com/click/dpheh0hzhm/aHR0cHM6Ly93d3cueW91dHViZS5jb20vd2F0Y2g_dj1ISWdGNnV5NEgzVQ=="&gt;the concepts in her book&lt;/a&gt;, I couldn't help but see the connections to the zombie apocalypse that I had seen on the silver screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll see depictions in some political cartoons I included in the book where you have Chinese coming over from China and escaping famine in the end of the 19th century and they're portrayed as grasshoppers...It seems right out of the book of Revelation when they're like a horde of locusts [with] human faces but there are these animal insect creatures that are eating everything up...Or you see Eastern Europeans leaving the shores of Europe to swim towards America as a herd of rats. So also understood in terms of plague and especially in terms of the black plague leaving European shores for the US and so that's all used in anti-immigration discourse, cartoons, literature... &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—Dr. Yii-Jan Lin, &lt;a href="https://preview.convertkit-mail2.com/click/dpheh0hzhm/aHR0cHM6Ly95b3V0dS5iZS9ISWdGNnV5NEgzVT9zaT1hSzJQMHZRRFliTmFFWXYzJnQ9MTMzMA=="&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data Over Dogma&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, timestamp 22:10&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether through a zombie virus, or just the inexplicable rising of undead hordes, modern zombies fit within the West's ancient tropes about apocalypse, calamity, and destruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It makes me wonder if this apocalyptic imagery or rhetoric is really just a technology that we have developed over the years to convince the hordes within our in-group that we must take action against the hordes of the out-group? It is certainly a dangerous form of rhetoric and has caused deep harm and trauma to countless amounts of people throughout history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may be quick to dismiss the modern zombie as something silly or just for movies, but I think we'll be well-served to reflect deeply when any apocalyptic symbols are used in our speech. When politicians choose a population to demonize, we should be suspicious. Maybe our fears are what transform &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt; into the mindless husk that follows the crowd, seeking human flesh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Works Cited&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1) &lt;em&gt;Savior narratives, and logistics of survival in The Walking Dead,&lt;/em&gt; By Martina Baldwin and Mark McCarthy. From the compilation of essays in &lt;em&gt;Thinking Dead,&lt;/em&gt; edited by Murali Balaji.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(2) &lt;em&gt;Social Psychology&lt;/em&gt; Fifth Edition, Stephen L. Fanzoi, 2009. pg. 319&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Is Your Technology Trying Too Hard?</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/is-your-technology-trying-too-hard/</link><description>Every week I face my archnemesis in a battle of will and endurance. I stand with firm footing, eyes narrowing as I lock onto my target. I extend my hand in an attempt at a truce—a peace offering. Goaded into a false sense of security my index finger trembles as I gently push the start button. Nothin</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 11:32:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/is-your-technology-trying-too-hard/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Every week I face my archnemesis in a battle of will and endurance. I stand with firm footing, eyes narrowing as I lock onto my target. I extend my hand in an attempt at a truce—a peace offering. Goaded into a false sense of security my index finger trembles as I gently push the start button. Nothing happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Five times?! You’re gonna make me start over five times today?” I cry out in desperation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I turn off the washing machine again, choose my settings and place my finger on the button as though I were a fly-fisherman sending out my hook to land with grace and precision. The lid locks with a thud and the machine chirps. Finally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That start button has never given my wife trouble. She can start it instantly, every single time. For some reason, that touch-only sensor doesn’t register my finger, no matter the angle, velocity, position, or time-in-contact. It’s a silly problem, I know, but I think it is representative of some of the problems we’ve introduced through technology that is supposed to be removing problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Design Thinking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If technology is ultimately about solving problems or at least making it easier to accomplish some goal, why wouldn't it be better for every day items to become smart items (meaning connected to the Internet)? Why shouldn't we use cool looking sensors and panels and interfaces that are more futuristic?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple—the company that gave us the iPod, the iPhone, Helvetica as a system font, and a really nice Unix-based terminal—has been propped up as an idol in the world of design. The success of their products, the bold and trend-setting visuals, the packaging experience, the focus on details, all have set a high bar that designers of all kinds aspire to meet. With all of the admiration swirling around Apple, a problem emerges: convergent design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A theory behind creativity and design is to start with divergence. We can use techniques to encourage exploration and innovation. One method is looking to find connections between two things or two ideas that usually have no business with each other. Or we can try and find the extremes like James Victore says, &lt;q&gt;Try to find the wrongest solution.&lt;/q&gt; This is where discoveries are made: leaving the body of work that is familiar or known and looking outside to find possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://embed.filekitcdn.com/e/iDKTPNXrEJsYXUT7GCu1J3/qq7GH8YjHmwigzanqnZfKL/email" alt=""&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Design-thinking stages: problem, diverge, converge, solution. Divergence increases the possibilities while convergence narrows them down.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Convergence, on the other hand is where we whittle down possibilities. We start to come together towards the final solution. The end-product of convergence is really important. Although there are pretty little charts like the one above, describing this process that seem straightforward, getting to the final decision isn’t clear or simple. Sometimes we converge too quickly, ignoring options that may have had significantly better results. Sometimes we converge on something that isn’t actually a good fit—even though everyone else is converging on it with great success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The design process failed in the case of my washing machine. Likely influenced by the trends, it seems like the designers opted for a button based more on the sleek look, rather than on functionality or reliability. That kind of sensor-as-a-button is a design choice. It could be a physical, mechanical button that provides haptic feedback and actually pushes in, but instead it’s trying really hard to be a smartphone instead of a washing machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the midst of all the possible ways a washing machine could be designed, we see trends of convergence towards a means that is actually less effective in its context than it is in another. For example, the standard smart phone has some excellent features and design choices. The interfaces can be somewhat complex for such a small, rectangular screen. They (usually) have great sensors that help distinguish between our taps and our swipes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to a washing machine, the complexity of the smart phone lends itself to having these dextrous, complex interactive capabilities. A washing machine has one job, even if that one job has many settings, it ultimately must perform its sole purpose: cleaning my clothes. It is so tempting to bring in solutions that are proven and effective and slap them onto the problem you are trying to solve. The concern is when too many of us are short-cutting the process and moving past the divergent-thinking phase in favor of the convergent phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Human-Centered&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Design thinkers observe how people behave, how the context of their experience affects their reaction to products and services. They take into account the emotional meaning of things as well as their functional performance. From this try to identify people’s unstated, or latent, needs and translate them into opportunities.” 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
—&lt;cite&gt;Change By Design&lt;/cite&gt;, by Tim Brown, pg. 229
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there was nothing else I could learn from studying design, the one thing I would never give up is the aggressive insistence on prioritizing people. The best designers remember that each number in analytics and reports is a real, actual person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a developer, I felt even more distanced from people, because I don’t have much interaction with the site visitors. It seemed very cold and isolated to dive into code and abstract theories about structuring databases until I discovered the concept of accessibility (the effort made to enable people of all abilities to use a website). All of a sudden my design instincts merged with my programming skills—I found my touchpoint with humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessibility has been my Polaris, guiding me back to the practices I had left behind as I gave up on my dream of being a designer. I could design better experiences for the blind or for people with low vision. I could make sure people who are sensitive to motion can safely open a page without getting a migraine. I could make the information easy to navigate for people who can’t use a mouse (or don’t want to, since the keyboard is the best way to use a computer 😉).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing all of the people in my mind has increased my ability to participate in the design-thinking process. When I look at a new component, the challenge of satisfying all of the constraints, requirements, and sometimes ideals feels like a convergence process—it’s already limited. The limits can have the opposite effect, however, and propel me to seek out as many divergent ideas as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a final thought, going back to home appliances, I can’t summarize it any better than this wonderful creator did. Next time you turn on an oven or a microwave, consider how its design impacts you—and how it might impact someone with different abilities. This is how we practice design thinking and helps us all build bridges between technology and humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://preview.convertkit-mail2.com/click/dpheh0hzhm/aHR0cHM6Ly93d3cueW91dHViZS5jb20vc2hvcnRzL2I4dXl4THRYaEdv"&gt;​Smart Homes Have Stupid Problems - Blind Smart Home Fails&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Apparently I'm a god now</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/apparently-im-a-god-now/</link><description>As the sole developer on my team at work, I've been called a lot of things: magician, wizard, king. Ironic as it may seem since my job is very heavily documented, technical, and (in a way) scientific, these mystical descriptions track with the subconscious culture of technology.
The first time I enc</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 23:49:56 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/apparently-im-a-god-now/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;As the sole developer on my team at work, I've been called a lot of things: magician, wizard, king. Ironic as it may seem since my job is very heavily documented, technical, and (in a way) scientific, these mystical descriptions track with the subconscious culture of technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time I encountered the idea that there was a mystical or spiritual aspect to how we humans interact with, build, and explore technology was listening to this podcast:
&lt;a href="https://www.humanetech.com/podcast/can-myth-teach-us-anything-about-the-race-to-build-artificial-general-intelligence-with-josh-schrei"&gt;Can Myth Teach Us Anything About the Race to Build Artificial General Intelligence? With Josh Schrei&lt;/a&gt;. Turns out, there is a whole lot more out there and I've only started scratching the surface in the literature about myths and machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unnecessary praise I've gotten at work has been gratifying. There's something to being called a wizard that is comforting in times when there is so much uncertainty about the future of work, because it tells me that my team does not understand what I do at all. If they don't understand it, they respect that I can &amp;quot;command&amp;quot; it so well. That comes with power imbalances, however, and puts a lot more responsibility on me to make sure that I am being honest and open about my work. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've taken the stance that teaching, sharing, and presenting about technical things is how I can release some of the power imbalance that I've created (though many people still just don't care, which is fine). At least it demystifies on record what I do and why I need to do those things—I'm a magician that openly shares the tricks. That approach has been deeply criticized by actual magicians, and yet, like my favorite magician, &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WzHtUK_GDeU"&gt;Chris Ramsay, has said&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think people should be exposed to more magic. I think 20-30 years down the line, people go to magic shows they'll be able to discern good magic from bad magic and I think they they have the right to know the difference...By keeping secrets from them...keeping them out of the loop, well, you're essentially depriving them of enjoying the art form the way that you enjoy it. They should be able to choose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While being associated with magic is thrilling to me, since I love the world of magic—tricks, illusions, etc.—I had a disturbing experience just last week as the attribution finally escalated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Since Jess is a god, we can now do this...&amp;quot; my teammate said in a meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've finally reached my peak, I suppose. If the scale starts at magician, what can be above deity? To be clear, I don't care that his language was (obviously) hyperbolic nor am I offended in some kind of spiritual sense as though it were blasphemous. There's no concern of mine that my ego will be so inflated as to actually believe I'm on par with any form of deity, there's no concern that I will be worshipped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why, then, was I so unsettled by the comment?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Problem Starts to Brew&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of what I'm seeing right now as generative AI is being used everywhere—including in my own code—is an abstraction of knowledge and skill. It is easy to criticize AI and those who use it without any attempt to judge its output, but now I'm just as concerned with those who use AI, even with expertise. There is danger in using AI for research, for the creation of code, for advice, when it's so easy to use and to trust. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a way, many knowledge workers are not in danger of being &lt;em&gt;physically&lt;/em&gt; replaced by AI in the sense that AI will take our jobs from us, rather the threat right now seems to be that our &lt;em&gt;intelligence&lt;/em&gt; will be replaced by artificial intelligence. We trade our actual intelligence for the artificial when we offload our critical thinking, our processes, and our hands-on work to the &amp;quot;robot.&amp;quot; As Marshall McLuhan said way back in the 1960s:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;We are all robots when uncritically involved with our technologies.&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can the same be said about spiritual or mystical ideas like worshipping of a deity? Something like: &amp;quot;We are all robots when uncritically involved with our gods.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think so. In fact, it's my personal experience that the culture of religion can, if not carefully guarded against, encourage a lack of critical thinking. This is not to say that it is the default state of &amp;quot;religion&amp;quot; to turn off our intelligence, nor does it mean that you cannot be both committed and thoughtful in religious settings. I'm speaking merely from my experience that I was trained to not ask certain questions; to take what I heard from leaders and males in general to be messages from God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If something I saw or heard didn't line up with my values, but it came from the &amp;quot;right&amp;quot; sources (leaders and males), it meant that I needed to figure out the disconnect like a puzzle that had its pieces all mixed up. The whole issue was that I had to prove them right—I was trying to make the puzzle display the picture I needed it to be, rather than the picture that it was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps we've been doing this with technology as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience with technology in general, I started out completely in love. Surely all technological progress is true progress. Every improved system, every automation run, every pixel properly placed was improving everyone's lives, end of story. The world of code was so vast even fifteen years ago, that I had to lean on the advice of other developers since I had no footing of understanding to call my own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, cracks started to appear in my idealized perception of the tech world. Cyber bullying through social media; attention spans depleting while being harvested for ad revenue; difficulty connecting with people in real life; &lt;a href="https://www.wired.com/story/millions-of-workers-are-training-ai-models-for-pennies/"&gt;exploitation of labor&lt;/a&gt; in less affluent areas of the world; the perpetuation of conspiracy theories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paradox of technology being both monumentally good and bad cannot be buried. Religion has the exact same paradox having done exceptionally good things for humanity, as well as having perpetrated devastating things to humanity. The more flexible we become, the less these spheres of our lives shake us when we confront the uncomfortable parts of their realities. This flexibility, in my experience, is adopting the practice and skill of critical thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, there is precedent for this even with the AI problem. Microsoft published a study in 2025, &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/uploads/prod/2025/01/lee_2025_ai_critical_thinking_survey.pdf"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;The Impact of Generative AI on Critical Thinking&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which states in the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;...higher confidence in GenAI is associated with less critical thinking, while higher self-confidence is associated with more critical thinking. Qualitatively, GenAI shifts the nature of critical thinking toward information verification, response integration, and task stewardship.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does it matter if we practice critical thinking, when AI will eventually take care of everything for us—it only gets smarter, after all? The paper continues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Used improperly, technologies can and do result in the deterioration of cognitive faculties that ought to be preserved. As Bainbridge [7] noted, a key irony of automation is that by mechanising routine tasks and leaving exception-handling to the human user, you deprive the user of the routine opportunities to practice their judgement and strengthen their cognitive musculature, leaving them atrophied and unprepared when the exceptions do arise.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Critical Cyborg&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not a god, in case you wanted clarification. I am most disturbed by that label because of the unapproachability that it implies. In many ways, the concept of a deity is something / someone that is far away, untouchable, and bigger than us. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm afraid we don't examine how these religious terms and concepts are built into technology from the very foundation. It makes it so much easier for us to fall into traps of feeling or thinking that our technology is too great—too unreachable—that we have no control of it. How can we control something like a god? We can't. If our technology or those who wield it become gods, then how can we safely interact with it or them? We can't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the Reverend Mother says at the beginning of Frank Herbert's &lt;cite&gt;Dune&lt;/cite&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Once men turned their thinking over to machines, in the hope that this would set them free, but that only permitted other men with machines to enslave them. 'Thou shalt not make a machine in the likeness of a man's mind'...but what the OC Bible should have said is: Thou shalt not make a machine to counterfeit a human mind.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Herbert's fictional universe is in a post-AI era. He skips over how humanity solved the issue of &amp;quot;men [turning] their thinking over to machines,&amp;quot; but the artifacts remain that indicate that humans took back their thinking. It's chilling to be in a time where AI is no longer science fiction, but something that is actually posing a threat to our actual intelligence, agency, and autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that religious language in technological settings is a warning sign. I think it indicates that the hidden undertones are now bubbling to the surface, as though technology is finally becoming too out-of-reach, too big, too unwieldy, that we can't help but start calling it like we see it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I will continue to act like a magician who shares the tricks, I'm realizing that it's not enough. Access to good information is not enough, because there are other players that are attempting to enslave &amp;quot;other men with machines.&amp;quot; I don't have the answer, but I do know that it is more important than ever to work on critical thinking skills. Approaching the world with curiosity, rather than with arrogance. Focusing on humanity, rather than on profits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can't afford to check out of our lives. Let's not &lt;em&gt;become&lt;/em&gt; robots by accepting technology the way it is, as though it couldn't be some other way. Let's abandon the dogma that any technology is good technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;The greatest of America's homegrown religions—greater than Jehovah's Witnesses, greater than the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints, greater even than Scientology—is the religion of technology.&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;Utopia Is Creepy&lt;/cite&gt; by Nicholas Carr&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Someone You Can Build a Nest In</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/someone-you-can-build-a-nest-in/</link><description>Surrounded by science and technology, with very few frontiers left to penetrate, it's an odd thing for a 21st century society to continue to lean on monster stories. From movies to games, it's become a vast industry of entertainment to explore what we know are mere figments of our imaginations—or at</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 06:10:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/someone-you-can-build-a-nest-in/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Surrounded by science and technology, with very few frontiers left to penetrate, it's an odd thing for a 21st century society to continue to lean on monster stories. From movies to games, it's become a vast industry of entertainment to explore what we know are mere figments of our imaginations—or at least, artifacts of our cognition. Monsters aren't real, but they are still among us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fear of the unknown becomes encapsulated in the bodies and behaviors of monsters. Any decent horror film exploits the deep, ancient parts of our brains to cause even the most hearty and posturing human to feel something. A tingle on the spine, a falling sensation in the chest, or a subtle feeling of dread teasing your mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monster stories spoke to me as a kid in a way that other stories did not initially. I was a closeted queer kid without any concept of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; I was different than my peers, yet I still knew that I was. I felt like a monster from stories I'd read or even ones I'd created: Something different, something others feared, despite being benevolent—the good guy. Being misunderstood and misrepresented makes it easy to relate to the creatures we've invented since the beginning of our humanity. And the worst part is that we usually make monsters out of humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Monstrous&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just finished a delightful, queer monster book by John Wiswell, &lt;em&gt;Someone You Can Build a Nest In.&lt;/em&gt; It has everything my inner child craves in a monster story: action, conflict, dark humor, secrets, and companionship. It is possibly my all-time favorite. I can't recommend it enough—no matter your orientation or identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're dropped instantly into a dangerous situation for our protagonist, Shesheshen, an amorphous creature who can absorb items (usually body parts, but other things, too) to help her shapeshift to take the form she needs. She often re-works the things she has swallowed to construct a form that passes as human. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immediately, this monster reflects the queer experience of &amp;quot;passing as straight,&amp;quot; which is how we often describe ourselves when we're closeted. Keeping up appearances that make it seem like you belong, that your experience of the world is the same as all of the straight / cisgender people around you. Even though in Wiswell's world, being queer is not really seen as out of the ordinary or monstrous (as it certainly is in the real world), Shesheshen reflects the stress of hiding in plain sight as she flees from monster hunters into a nearby town, trying to blend in with the locals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secrets, lying, and pretending may not be monstrous behaviors in themselves, but from experience I know that the weight of these things are harmful over time. It's part of the &lt;a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC2072932/"&gt;minority stress&lt;/a&gt; that I experienced as an outcast, even though it was never overt (I was lucky to never be accused of being gay or made fun of for my gender non-conformity in appearance &lt;em&gt;as a kid&lt;/em&gt;). I, like Shesheshen, found myself in dangerous circumstances in public. I didn't have to be the target of bullying or rage to know that I could easily &lt;em&gt;become&lt;/em&gt; the target if I did not wear my mask well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Shesheshen works to hide as a human, she observes that this town has already started celebrating in anticipation that the monster hunters who were sent into her lair had succeeded in slaying her. She notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These emotions she didn't know how to carry. There was the insult of having her death celebrated when she wasn't even dead. When she was, in fact, amidst them all right now, and only out here because they'd sent killers to fail in her home. But this. To be dying from the poison of those assassins, and while looking for emergency food to survive the injury, to be told by a drunk rich boy with inconvenient hair that she had never really existed. Now their songs made unkind sense to her. This reverie was a kind of fear, for hatred was the fear people let themselves enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 1, Chapter 3&lt;/em&gt;, transcribed from the audio book (punctuation is my best guess).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, here in the twenty-first century, have an effective strategy for getting rid of monsters: make them non-existent. To wipe away identity is a very effective means of violence without getting any gore on your hands! We've seen this as trans people have been persecuted in the U.S. by removing any acknowledgement of their identity on passports, IDs, and other legal documents. Oh, you're trans or intersex? Sorry, you have to fit into either M or F on this form—and it better match the arbitrary M or F that someone decided fit you best at birth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this tactic isn't actually new. Other communities have been devastated this way for thousands of years. Indigenous people all throughout the world have suffered this erasure of identity. Ancient cultures and languages have been punished into secrecy or out of existence by invaders and colonizers. What great losses have we inflicted upon each other as the drive to eradicate, conquer, and assimilate have been implemented throughout history?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Conflict&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title of the book haunted the entire story. While our heroic shapeshifter falls in love with a human despite all the dangers that it poses to Shesheshen's own life, there's still the uncomfortable &amp;quot;truth&amp;quot; that accompanies her monstrous nature: For Shesheshen, to love someone means to build a nest in that person—the body becoming a source of food for the offspring to devour and disintegrate entirely. A &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vMG-LWyNcAs"&gt;disturbing likeness to parasitic insects&lt;/a&gt; that can &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hymenoptera"&gt;inject their eggs through a stinger&lt;/a&gt; into another host that is often eaten alive from inside out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can I love this main character, as I am so prone to do, having followed her journey and empathized with her so long, knowing that the outcome will be the utter, painful destruction of her love? I listened with rapt attention throughout the book, dreading the final conflict when everything is exposed; when both characters fully understand one another. How can I love a character like &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question gives me pause now, because I know it's a question all of my family and friends have had to grapple with once they know and see me as I am. How can they love a person like &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe that seems harsh—maybe you're upset that &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; might think that &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; would think that. Yet, I know well that we often think thoughts and feel feelings that we do not want. We all make mistakes, for sure, but we also fail to be perfectly whole and consistent in the way that our perception of ourselves pretends that we are. We can have thoughts that horrify us, like a mother thinking that she might not be able to love her queer child, then regretting the thought, disgusted with herself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think when we encounter &lt;em&gt;disgust&lt;/em&gt; in a moral conflict—like whether you can love a queer family member or friend—it is an opportunity to reflect more deeply, rather than a sign that you are unequivocally right. Like my therapist told me, &amp;quot;Thoughts are not facts.&amp;quot; We still have to deal with them, however, and explore why we might be having these thoughts or feelings. Is there a system that has inserted its own ideas or values into yours? Do those ideas and values serve you? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disgust is seemingly an integral part of our experience with humanity and monstrosity. It is summed up well in the book, &lt;em&gt;On Monsters&lt;/em&gt;, by Stephen T. Asma, page 184:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The philosopher of horror Noel Carroll...arrived at his own mismatch theory by noticing that most horror monsters are disgusting as well as threatening. He argues that human beings seem especially disgusted by &amp;quot;impurity.&amp;quot; Things that we find impure and consider to be abominations are usually interstitial entities, in between normal categories of being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be queer is to be in-between. Even the word &lt;em&gt;queer&lt;/em&gt; carries the baggage of &amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://www.etymonline.com/search?q=queer"&gt;appearing, feeling, or behaving otherwise than is usual or normal&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;quot; It is very easy to demonize a smaller group of people—especially those you don't know personally—and exploit our intuitive sense of disgust by pointing it towards those people you want to exclude, dominate, or destroy. We've been doing this...always.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disgust can be helpful for us in identifying danger—such as encountering...things...that could carry disease. We know there is danger to be found even among our own social circles: emotional and social dangers that are every bit as real and harmful as physical dangers. So perhaps disgust is an attempt to help us sort through the possible dangers that we face. Sometimes it also &lt;a href="https://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;amp;lr=&amp;amp;id=zOPaDwAAQBAJ&amp;amp;oi=fnd&amp;amp;pg=PA53&amp;amp;dq=cognitive+science+of+disgust&amp;amp;ots=LhB87P-mBq&amp;amp;sig=c2TMmUighr9wTiwR8yhYM1TYFws#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=cognitive%20science%20of%20disgust&amp;amp;f=false"&gt;promotes pro-social behavior&lt;/a&gt;, like refusing to take part in a system or a policy or a company that harms vulnerable people for profit or power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with ascribing monstrosity onto a population of humans, wholesale, is that the perspective of human vs. monster is completely relative. Throughout U.S. history (that which I'm most familiar), the LGBTQ+ community has been called demonic by churches, criminals by law-makers, and mentally-disordered by psychologists. Monsters, indeed. But as more time, experience, advocacy, and information has been collected, allies find themselves in the uncomfortable space, knowing that they may have at one time thought of the people they love as monsters, when the real monstrosity was that deception—the removal of humanity from other humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demonization of people is not a mere thought-experiment or innocent theological argument. &lt;a href="/newsletters/value-driven/"&gt;It has measured, harmful impacts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a society like ours where homosexuals are uniformly treated with disparagement or contempt—to say nothing about outright hostility—it would be surprising indeed if substantial numbers of them did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; suffer from an impaired self-image and some degree of unhappiness with their stigmatized status. … It is manifestly unwarranted and inaccurate, however, to attribute such neuroticism, when it exists, to intrinsic aspects of homosexuality itself. (p. 400)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—&lt;em&gt;Homosexual Behavior: A Modern Reappraisal&lt;/em&gt; (1980), Judd Marmor, as quoted in the Abstract of &lt;a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC2072932/"&gt;Prejudice, Social Stress, and Mental Health in Lesbian, Gay, and Bisexual Populations: Conceptual Issues and Research Evidence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Way Out&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monsters are alive and well in our minds—that may not be something we can evolve out of for thousands or even millions of years more. Trying to outrun our monsters may be as effective as running from our own shadow. Pretending something (or someone) isn't there is also a poor choice in strategy—and may even end up harming us in the ripples caused by our social violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, we can take our modern-day approach further. The goal isn't to erase the &lt;em&gt;existence&lt;/em&gt; of these &amp;quot;monsters,&amp;quot; but to examine them more deeply. If the fear of the unknown is ultimately what a monster &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;, then we ought to learn more about what we don't know. Dehumanizing someone makes it impossible for us to access our empathy, and in a way, we stray from our own humanity at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;...we must see the battle—at least for a moment—from the deck of the enemy warship,  because each person has his own perspective, his own reality, no matter how much it may differ from ours.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—&lt;em&gt;The Gift of Fear&lt;/em&gt;, pg 109, Gavin De Becker&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monsters also provide us an opportunity for self-reflection. We can all relate to monsters in some way, because we've all made choices in the murky waters of ethical and &lt;a href="/newsletters/i-fasted-from-watching-violence-for-twelve-years/"&gt;moral conundrums that have harmed others&lt;/a&gt;, ourselves, or were simply wrong. We are all a part of systems that are bigger than us that perpetrate horrors on people that we don't usually see up close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like they reiterated many times in Buffy the Vampire Slayer, we have to always be questioning, &amp;quot;who is the real enemy?&amp;quot; When it comes to humans, our intuition can be deceiving, and outside of immediate danger (please still trust your gut and stay safe) I would suggest that we use the time that we have in safety to remain curious and open-minded. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If our world seems teeming with more monsters than it has in the past, why might that be the case? Are we being manipulated to see more monsters among friends? Could we be wrong about the monsters we've been taught to hate? What needs are in question—are my needs not being met, or are my &amp;quot;enemy's&amp;quot; needs not being met? Is there space for us to both exist as we are?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the ultimate lesson from &lt;em&gt;Someone You Can Build a Nest In&lt;/em&gt; is perfectly captured by this review of the book from &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This unusual queer romance is a heartfelt fable about disability and the possibility of reconciling conflicting needs through love and understanding.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Technotopia</title><link>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/technotopia/</link><description>Knowledge is power. We know this through experience, through history, and sometimes through corruption. It feels like the idea of &amp;quot;propaganda&amp;quot; and of partisan- or biased-news would be something that is from a bygone age, thanks largely to the Internet. At least, that's how it was positione</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jess Brown</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 01:41:26 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/technotopia/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Knowledge is power. We know this through experience, through history, and sometimes through corruption. It feels like the idea of &amp;quot;propaganda&amp;quot; and of partisan- or biased-news would be something that is from a bygone age, thanks largely to the Internet. At least, that's how it was positioned in my view growing up. Jonathan Haidt put it well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;The internet came into our lives in the mid-1990s, soon after the fall of the Soviet Union. By the end of that decade, it was widely thought that the web would be an ally of democracy and a slayer of tyrants. When people are connected to each other, and to all the information in the world, how could any dictator keep them down?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;p&gt;—Jonathan Haidt, &lt;a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2024/03/teen-childhood-smartphone-use-mental-health-effects/677722/"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;The Terrible Costs of a Phone-Based Childhood&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even before the Internet, we had many assumptions about what a connected world could do for humanity. Consider what Alonzo Jackman predicted about the impacts of the telegraph in 1846:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;...all inhabitants of the earth would be brought into one intellectual neighbourhood and be at the same time perfectly freed from these contaminants which might under other circumstances be received.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we can do research, fact-check, and stay connected to all &lt;em&gt;indexed&lt;/em&gt; knowledge that humanity has to offer, how are we &lt;a href="https://cyborgnewsletter.com/newsletters/fauxtopia/"&gt;still not in eutopia&lt;/a&gt;—a &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; or perfect place?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Illusion of Place&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still am generally a technology-optimist. I've spent my entire professional career building web&lt;em&gt;sites&lt;/em&gt;—virtual places where information or other interactions are available. There are so many delightful experiences that I've had online whether finding niche treasure troves of helpful information or even just browsing &lt;a href="https://public.work/"&gt;ancient documents and images&lt;/a&gt; that I could never access by myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vastness and the creative potential of the Internet is so attractive that it's easy to forget that these technotopias that I spend my time on aren't the only use-cases available—nor are they the most popular. Putting aside the websites you spend time on for work, where do you go for the majority of your Internet experiences? Social media would be my guess for the vast majority of our leisure-time online, and it certainly lines up with my experience lately. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making your own website can be complicated and technical, in stark contrast to making a social media post. The simplicity of posting to Facebook, for example, has helped draw in and retain vast user bases. This also means that people can use these platforms to grow their content footprint—a body of work, in some sense—which then benefits both the platform and the creator. It is within this system that has, in large part, contributed to a separation of realities among all of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href="https://www.humanetech.com/"&gt;Center for Humane Technology&lt;/a&gt;, social media was our first large-scale interaction with artificial intelligence (AI). As an attempt to solve the problem of drowning in the exponentially growing amount of content generated by the users of social media platforms, AI was made to sort through the mess and identify the things that you, individually, would like to see. People say they have to cater to &amp;quot;The Algorithm,&amp;quot; and they're right. The AI is constantly looking to be fed more data and more content so that it can then serve it to you, hot and fresh (yes, all food puns intended).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As technology has progressed and monetary incentives have solidified for the companies running the social media platforms, we've ended up with a utopia. Not to be confused with eutopia (a good place), utopia means &amp;quot;not a place,&amp;quot; and indeed, the Internet is no place, despite how much it &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; like it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we experience a place by walking around it, soaking in whatever stimuli is available to our senses, we develop a kind of the reality that the location encapsulates. As we see other people in our surroundings, it's natural to guess that they are also inhabiting the same sensory reality that we are. I think this is the same in abstract locations, like knowledge or spirituality. Our ideas and beliefs can construct realities almost as tangible as a stone pillar or a soft canvas tent. The Internet is rife with ideologies, opinions, beliefs, and knowledge, awaiting visitors to come inhabit that space for a moment or to frequently return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's where it gets difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The algorithms at work trying to predict what content we will most enjoy seeing next are also constructing realities around us. Perhaps it has built a large room where many of your friends can sit with you in the shared understanding. When you encounter a friend who has never even seen this building that you've grown so familiar with, it can be jarring. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;How have you not seen this?&amp;quot; you might ask.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;How can you stand to be in &lt;em&gt;there&lt;/em&gt;?&amp;quot; they might reply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are groups with malicious intent that can subtly infiltrate our digital spaces and as we become more and more comfortable with their messages which eventually surround us as algorithms boost their content, we can slip into delusion. Take QAnon, a highly successful community built on conspiracy theories, for example. With masterful manipulation techniques, QAnon has targeted vulnerable people looking for validation or for comfort amidst powerlessness, chaos, confusion, or political turmoil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Beneath these kinds of delusional beliefs, in many instances, is not a desire to be accurately informed, but a need to be internally comforted.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—Jesselyn Cook, &lt;cite&gt;The Quiet Damage&lt;/cite&gt;, pg. 230&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much for our &amp;quot;intellectual neighborhood&amp;quot; being able to free us from contaminants, if we are all at risk of manipulation with something as simple as the track of content being fed to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is such a striking difference of realities that we're all subjected to through our utopias, that I've even felt disoriented in the real world as I've moved between various friend groups. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is not to say we have no benefit from our digital realities. The Internet has helped challenge oppressive systems, connect people in constructive ways, and enabled transparency across organizations, governments, and other groups. The paradox of benefit and harm resulting from the virtual world is one that we'll have to hold onto, no matter how uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Another Place&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without many policies and regulations to help us, we're severely limited in what we are able to do about the realities that are constructed around us. If our technotopia really is like a place, then we may find value in keeping with the metaphor and trying out some tested methods from the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Mark Twain said in, &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/work/quotes/6551286"&gt;The Innocents Abroad / Roughing It&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Travel is fatal to prejudice, bigotry, and narrow-mindedness, and many of our people need it sorely on these accounts. Broad, wholesome, charitable views of men and things cannot be acquired by vegetating in one little corner of the earth all one's lifetime.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Homogeneity, as we explored last week, is insufficient and stifling in real-world attempts at building &lt;em&gt;eutopias&lt;/em&gt;, so perhaps we must also fight against it in our sphere of knowledge and virtual experience. However, the sameness of &lt;em&gt;venue&lt;/em&gt; is also concerning. I worry that the draw to digital spaces has overpowered our human need to meet in physical spaces. So much of my interactions with my friends are virtual—through texts, shared Instagram reels, etc.—that I am losing not only my social skills, but my ability to connect with people when we are face-to-face. It feels very much like the following observation made by Jun'ichirō Tanizaki back in 1933:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Japanese music is, above all, a music of reticence, of atmosphere. When recorded or amplified by loudspeaker, the greatest part of its charm is lost...Most important of all, are the pauses. Yet the phonograph and the radio render these moments of silence utterly lifeless.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—&lt;cite&gt;In Praise of Shadows&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Has the technology that was supposed to unite us, actually chipped away at our humanity? Or at least dulled the vitality of our connections with each other? Are the manipulated realities to blame for taking us to a place we didn't intend to arrive at?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grew up in a culture that was highly averse to differing perspectives. In fact, there were intellectual walls constructed intentionally to ward off the possibility of exploring human experiences, social critiques, and especially any kind of introspection of religious institutions. As a result, I have been stunted in my growth as a human, I have made racist proclamations (always with good &lt;em&gt;intentions&lt;/em&gt;—and where does that path lead again?), I have perpetuated harmful beliefs and practices. The amount of actual pain that I have contributed to is immeasurable, but it is finally catching up to me as I have broken free from the restraints that were inflicted on me. Clawing my way out from behind the intellectual walls that prevented me from seeing Others as humans, I'm realizing now that it is vital to seek out different views, different ideas, and different experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I have become a much more regular digital traveller, there is still more to do. Our emotional and mental health &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; become a priority (both individually and collectively). Since our digital utopias inhabit no real space but our own minds, taking care to clean up will help us be more discerning when confronted with manipulation. My life took an incredibly gigantic turn when I made mental health my main focus. Coming from more than twenty years of homogeneity, manipulation, and rage redirected internally, I was at a lowest-of-lows, easily swayed by any idea, as long as it lined up with what was familiar to me, even though it was hurting me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting out of utopia and into another place is neither easy nor fun, but it is vital—as in life-giving. My country's deep emotional and mental wounds are now manifesting in even greater harm as the current administration is lashing out at groups of people it has determined are monsters, or at least a lower-class of human. Oh, how things might be different if we could reconnect instead of disconnect?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all thy travels, never forget humanity.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>